<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A general epistle given forth in obedience to the God of peace. [part 1] for the preservation and increase of charity and unity amongst the professors of Christ Jesus, and the teachings of his divine light within / by ... William Gibson.</title>
            <author>Gibson, William, 1629-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 238 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G684_pt1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18589</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12661863</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12661863</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65439</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42679)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65439)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 355:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A general epistle given forth in obedience to the God of peace. [part 1] for the preservation and increase of charity and unity amongst the professors of Christ Jesus, and the teachings of his divine light within / by ... William Gibson.</title>
                  <author>Gibson, William, 1629-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 164, 99 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold by John Bringhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Between pages 98 and 99 in the second group of paging there are several miscellaneous pages of an introduction to an unidentified work.</note>
                  <note>Pages 161-164 dark and illegible.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [4]-[6].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Friends' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65439:1"/>
            <p>A General Epiſtle Given forth in OBEDIENCE TO THE God of Peace.</p>
            <p>For the Preſervation and Increaſe of CHARITY and UNITY a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Profeſſors of Chriſt Jeſus, and the Teachings of his Divine Light within.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Servant of Chriſt, a True Lover of</hi> Chriſtian-Charity Peace <hi>and</hi> Unity WILLIAM GIBSON.</p>
            <q>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers, for they ſhall be called the Children of God, <bibl>Mat. 5. 9.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Put on Charity, which is the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of perfectneſs, <bibl>Col. 3. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>He that ſaith he abideth in Chriſt, ought himſelf even to walk ſo as he walked, <bibl>1 John 2. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Let your Converſation be as it becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt,—<bibl>Phil. 1. 27.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, and ſold by <hi>John Bringhurſt,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Book</hi> in <hi>Grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-Church ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="complete_errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:65439:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65439:2"/>
            <div type="publishers_note">
               <p>REader, notwithſtanding the Authors great care to prevent. Errors in the following matter, yet ſeveral Errors have eſcaped the Preſs, which thou art deſired to take notice of; as the miſtake of the Printers. Thoſe which are moſt material to hurt the Senſe, I have collected in this <hi>Errata,</hi> ſome other ſmall literal Faults and Errors in pointing and tranſpoſing or miſplacing of words there are, all which may be diſcerned in reading, by ſuch who are skilful and diligent therein, and by ſuch corrected ſo far as may be, for the help of thoſe who are leſs skilful in reading and correcting; the two greateſt Errors take particular notice of, the first is in the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction</hi> page the 5. line the 16. where ſpeaking of the <hi>Spirit of the Creature</hi> Man or Woman, it is there rendred the <hi>Spirit of the Creator;</hi> the ſecond great error is in p. 107. l. 15. where the word <hi>ſenſually</hi> is put inſtead of the word <hi>ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:65439:3"/>
               <head>ERRATA.</head>
               <p>INtroduction page 3. line 10. for <hi>Light</hi> read <hi>Spirit;</hi> p. 5. l. 16. f. <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator</hi> r. <hi>Creature;</hi> p. 6. l. 17. f. <hi>were</hi> read <hi>was;</hi> p. 12. l. 14. f. <hi>word</hi> r. <hi>words;</hi> p. 10. l. 3. blot out <hi>ſome of.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt PART.</head>
               <p>IN Margin, p. 52. r. <hi>God commanded the Light to be and appear, and ſeparated it from the Darkneſs in the Firſt days work;</hi> p. 59. l. the 8. add the word <hi>(one)</hi> p. 76. l. 18. add the word <hi>(ſame)</hi> p. 78. l. 12. f. <hi>nember</hi> r. <hi>member;</hi> p. 95. l. 21. add the word <hi>(the)</hi> p. 102. l. 23. f. <hi>Chrisi</hi> r. <hi>Chriſt;</hi> p. 105. l. 7. f. <hi>Juſtifying</hi> r. <hi>Juſtifie;</hi> p. 107. l. 15 f. <hi>ſenſually</hi> r. <hi>ſenſibly;</hi> p. 109. l. 10. next after the word you make a full ſtop; p. 126. l. 22 and 23. read, <hi>O all ye ends of the Earth;</hi> p. 160. l, 19. dele <hi>and fear;</hi> l. 14. dele <hi>or.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:65439:3"/>
               <head>Second PART.</head>
               <p>PAge the 2. l. 5. blot out <hi>and;</hi> p. the 6. l. 13, 14. r. <hi>thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall;</hi> p. 19. l. 5. r. the verſe 9 and 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> l. 23. blot out <hi>(him;)</hi> l. 29 f. <hi>careful</hi> r. <hi>careful;</hi> p. 20. l. 11. f. <hi>fevere</hi> r. <hi>ſevere;</hi> p. 24. l. 7. add <hi>(ſpoken of)</hi> p. 28. l. 20. f. <hi>underſtanding</hi> r. <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand;</hi> p. 29. l. 12. r. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. p. 45. l. 24. next after <hi>and,</hi> add <hi>(have)</hi> p. 56. l. 12. f. <hi>ſoberly</hi> r. <hi>ſober;</hi> p. 65. l. 31. f. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> r. <hi>to;</hi> p. 80. l. 25. blot out <hi>(to;)</hi> p. 93. l. 22. f. <hi>ſowed</hi> r. <hi>ſoweth;</hi> p. 96. l. 6. f. <hi>ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> r. <hi>ſeal,</hi> p. 99. l. 8. f. <hi>comended</hi> r. <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Several Scriptures which ſhould have been in the <hi>Italick Letter</hi> are omitted, particularly the Firſt Chapter of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> &amp;c. in p. 52, 53, 54, 55.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="publishers_note">
               <pb facs="tcp:65439:4"/>
               <p>Note, this Book being printed by ſeveral Men, occaſioneth it to be in two Parts, only beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning anew of the Figures upon the top of the pages, and that which is called the Second Part begins with the figure 1 at the top of the page or leaf.</p>
               <p>There is alſo ſome part of the Book put in Black Letter, which had been moſt properly in the Roman: theſe improprieties of the different form of Letters, doth no way hurt the matter as to the ſenſe thereof.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:65439:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>AN Exhortation to the Profeſſors of the Light within, to live and walk in the ſame; and the Walker in the Light diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the Talker of it, who walk in Darkneſs, <hi>Page. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Concerning good Conſcience, 21.</item>
               <item>Concerning evil Conſcience, 23.</item>
               <item>Concerning them that are weak in the Faith, 28.</item>
               <item>Concerning days, 30.</item>
               <item>Something concerning Chriſtian Order, or Order in the Church of Chriſt, 42.</item>
               <item>Something more concerning the Order of the Works of God in Heaven and Earth, and particularly in his People, 52.</item>
               <item>Something more particularly concerning the Order of Chriſt in his Church, 72.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Form of the true Apoſtles Doctrine, 95.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Commands of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, which they gave, not of themſelves, or by their own power, but by and in his Power, VViſdom, Strength and Authority; for they were his Ambaſſadors, over them he reigned, in them he ſpake and gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, who is the Head of his Church, and
<pb facs="tcp:65439:5"/> one in the Male and Female, 97</item>
               <item>Concerning the Honour that God gives unto his People, 130.</item>
               <item>Concerning Rule and Government in the Church of Chriſt, 133.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Living Faith with its Fruits and Works, 142.</item>
               <item>Something concerning Self-Separation, 155.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Second PART.</head>
               <item>COncerning falling from God, 1.</item>
               <item>Concerning juſt Judgment amongſt Gods People, given or committed to them, or ſpoken by or through them (in whom God dwells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccording to his promiſe) againſt the Devil and his works, ſin and wickedneſs, 9.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Juſt and Righteous Judgment of God in and by his People under the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the Goſpel, 13.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Mercy of God, and of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 17.</item>
               <item>Something concerning true Love, or Charity, 28.</item>
               <item>Something concerning the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip of true Chriſtians, 53.</item>
               <item>Something concerning the Seven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> who were gathered into the Profeſſion of Chriſt Jeſus, 57.</item>
               <item>Something concerning Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 78.</item>
               <item>Concerning pure Religion, 83.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
                  <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65439:5"/>
            <head>A General Epiſtle TO FRIENDS, &amp;c.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>An <hi>Exhortation</hi> to the <hi>Profeſſors of the Light Within,</hi> to <hi>LIVE and WALK</hi> in the ſame; and the <hi>WALKER</hi> in the Light diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>TALKER</hi> of it who walks in Darkneſs.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>ALL you who profeſs Chriſt Jeſus, the Prince of Life and Peace, to be your Prince, Captain of your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and Biſhop of your Souls, who profeſs to be Taught, Led, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Spiritual Light within you:</p>
            <p>See that you all Live and Walk in the ſame, that you may all poſſeſs that which you do profeſs; and it is moſt certain, <hi>if we walk in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65439:6"/> the light,</hi> (wherewith God in Chriſt hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened us) <hi>then have we fellowſhip one with another, and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son, cleanſeth us from all Sin:</hi> But if there be not a Walking in this precious Divine <hi>Light</hi> (which ſhines from God the Fountain of it) then there can be no Fellowſhip with God the Father, nor with his beloved Son, nor true Fellowſhip one with another: No cleanſing from Sin then, but the ſin of all ſuch who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Talk</hi> of the <hi>Light (Walking contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to it)</hi> remaineth and encreaſeth: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all be very careful in this great weighty Concern, wherein the Glory of the great God, and the Salvation of your Souls are ſo very greatly concerned. O Friends! Be all as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to follow and obey this Spiritual Divine Light, as you are to profeſs it, and talk of it; for if there be not a <hi>Walking in it,</hi> the <hi>Profeſsion of it</hi> will be in vain: For after the Light of Chriſt Within be known, and Good and Evil made known by it, if the Creature do not yield Obedience to it, in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Evil, and embracing, following, and doing that which is Good, then his ſin becomes more grievous to Almighty God than before; for as 'tis written, <hi>In the time of Ignorance God winked;</hi> but after the Goſpel, the Power of God is preached to, and in, the Creature (which hath been ſubjected by Satan under ſin, in the Bondage of Corruption) and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65439:6"/> by which the Creatures Heart and Soul is, in ſome degree, quickened and opened to know what God requireth of it: If then it do not deny Self, take up its Croſs againſt the Devil and Self, then its Oppoſition and Diſobedience to the Divine Goſpel-Light, God accounts the <hi>Sin of ſtebellion,</hi> which is as Witchcraft, from which the Lord God of all our Mercies and Bleſſings deliver and preſerve you. Into this State of Miſery were the fooliſh <hi>Galati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> faln, to whom the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> wrote, and after he had ſharply reprehended them for their Backſliding and Unfaithfulneſs, he travelled again on their behalf, <hi>that Chriſt might be formed in them.</hi> And as their Backſliding became matter of great Sorrow and deep Exerciſe to him, the like hath befaln the ancient and faithful Labourers in the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt in our age <hi>for ſome;</hi> for as he was ſent to turn the People from Darkneſs to the Divine Spiritual Light of God and Chriſt, from the Power of Satan (who had imbondaged them in ſin) to God, whoſe Power is Almighty, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Power of Satan down, and delivering the Creature, by its powerful working, out of the bondage of Corruption, into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God: Even ſo hath the Lord God Almighty and Merciful, ſent his faithful Servants, in this Age, to turn People from Darkneſs unto Light, from the Power
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65439:7"/> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Satan unto God, that through the working of the glorious Power of God in their In ward Man, they might receive true Faith and Repentance, and ſo might receive the Forgiveneſs of their Sins paſt, in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, through the forbearance of God; and not only ſo, but alſo by the ſame power, to know Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of Sin, from the Power of Satan, who led them into it, and ſo come into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Liberty of the Sons of God. This glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous work of Reſtauration hath the Lord in his tender Mercy begun, and effectually carried on in Thouſands, Glory be given unto him for the ſame, and for all his tender Mercies; for he is worthy. But as it was in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles days, ſo is it in <hi>ours;</hi> there were ſome then, who, after they had taſted of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Gift and power of the World to come, and thereby had known the beginning of the work of true Faith and Repentance, and the Exerciſe of a good Conſcience, yet through their <hi>Slothtulneſs, Negligence, and multiplied Diſobedience &amp; Rebellion, they came to make Shipwrack of the Faith which God had given them, and to put away a good Conſcience which God by his powerful Spirit had wrought in them:</hi> Of this ſort the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writ, ſaying, <hi>It had been better they had never known the way of Truth, than after they have known it to depart from the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65439:7"/> delivered to them: But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is come to paſs according to the true Proverb, <hi>The Dog is returned to his own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and the Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the Mire.</hi> Jude &amp; Peter</hi> writ of theſe and ſuch like <hi>ſalſe Apoſtles &amp; deceitful Workers,</hi> ſaying, <hi>They are Wells without Water, Clouds without Rain, carried about of Tempeſts, wandring Stars, to whom is reſerved the Miſt of darkneſs for ever; Trees whoſe. Fruit is <hi>wither<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, without Fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts.</hi>
               </hi> Such were they whom the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writ of, ſaying, (<hi>Acts</hi> 20. 30. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2.) <hi>Men ſhall ariſe among your ſelves, ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things, and ſhall draw Diſciples after them, through whom the way of Truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of.</hi> I ſay, as it is was then, ſo is it come to paſs in our days; diverſe Perſons, who have come among us in a Profeſſion of the Pure, Unchangeable, Divine Light of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who, for ſome time, did in ſome Meaſure know it, and obeyed it, they have turned into Rebellion againſt it; and ſuch have, and do now make War againſt the Children of it, who walk in it, in whom the pure, peaceable Fruits of it do appear. And this ſome Men have done, and do, under the <hi>Profeſsion</hi> of it, and a <hi>ſpecieus pretence of Love to it;</hi> this is abominable Deceit, yea, the deceivableneſs of Unrighteouſneſs, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65439:8"/> worketh in them, which hath been wrought in them by Satan, becauſe they have not kept in true Love and Obedience unto the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Light of Chriſt the Son of God, to which they were turned. They have <hi>not</hi> kept in the <hi>Godly Fear,</hi> not in <hi>true Humility,</hi> therefore hath Satan (the Prince of Darkneſs, and King over all the Children of Pride) dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their <hi>Underſtandings,</hi> adulterated their <hi>Affections,</hi> and corrupted their <hi>Wills:</hi> Thus by him they are prepared and uſed as Inſtruments for him, againſt the Lord and his Divine Light, Grace, and Spirit, under the <hi>Profeſsion</hi> of the ſame. Such by profeſſing and uſing the words of Truth, have, and do deceive the Hearts of the Simple. God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath Confounded the work of ſuch, in our Age we have ſeen it, and do give Glory to him for the ſame. We do believe that he will confound ſuch Evil works, and that the Inſtruments thereof will be eternally miſerable, if they do not find a place of Repentance, which to ſee them find would be matter of great Comfort to us. Several Perſons have gone out of the Truth under ſpecious Pretences of <hi>Greater Manifeſtations of God,</hi> and <hi>Attainments,</hi> and <hi>Growth in the way of Righteouſneſs, than they were come to, whom they turned againſt.</hi> And through thoſe falſe Pretences they have drawn ſome <hi>tender-hearted, well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65439:8"/> Perſons</hi> from the Divine Light and Fellowſhip in it, into evil Imaginations and unrighteous Jealouſies, concerning the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters of Chriſt, and their Labour of Love for the Glory of God, and the Peace, Unity, Preſervation, and Eternal Good of his People.</p>
            <p>But the Lord God in Mercy hath given ſeveral who were thus <hi>hurt,</hi> to ſee how the <hi>hurt</hi> came upon them, and hath recovered them out of the Snare wherein they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly taken, bleſſed be his holy Name for the ſame; and we hope that he will viſit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore ſuch well-meaning Perſons, who are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and yet held in ſuch like Snares, though ſome who are turned aſide after Satan, may grow worſe and worſe, as others have done before them, until God cut them off in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as he hath done ſuch like already.</p>
            <p>My <hi>dear Friends,</hi> you who have <hi>ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> been turned to the Divine Light of Chriſt, who have and do walk in it, you know what I have here briefly touched at is true, and you in this divine Light, may ſee the Old Enemy of our Peace &amp; pure Chriſtian Fellowſhip &amp; Unity at work againſt the ſame, under a <hi>Profeſsion of the Light,</hi> to darken and draw perſons from it, into the works of Darkneſs. And thus, as in the Apoſtles days, he hath, and doth transform himſelf as like an Angel of Light, as he can: <hi>how ſhould he appear like an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65439:9"/> Angel of Light, if he ſhould in words deny the Light of Chriſt Within Man and Woman?</hi> The Apoſtle writing of falſe Apoſtles, ſaith thus, <hi>viz. For ſuch Falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles are deceitful Workers, and faſhion them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like unto the Apoſtles of Chriſt; and no marvel, for Satan himſelf is changed into the faſhion of an Angel of Light: Therefore is it no great thing, though his Miniſters faſhion themſelves as though they were the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, whoſe end ſhall be according to their Deeds.</hi> Thus 'tis rendered in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. Old Tranſlation, Printed in 1566. O con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it all ſuch whom it concerns! And how ſhould the Falſe Apoſtles in the True A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles days, have transformed themſelves like unto them, if they ſhould have in Words denied the Light of Chriſt Within (though in Works they did?) Seeing Chriſt's Command was, and is, <hi>to believe in the Light and walk in at, that Men and Women might then, &amp; may now, and hereafter be Children of the Light,</hi> as the faithful Followers of the Light then were, and now are. The great Meſſage and Work of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and the Apoſtles <hi>Paul, John, Peter,</hi> and the reſt, was to bear witneſs of the Light, and to turn People to it, that they might all believe in it, and obey and walk therein, that they might be ſaved. Now for Satan to ſend his Apoſtles, or Preachers [<hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gſt us</hi>] to ſeek, to deceive us, if they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65439:9"/> ſhould come blaſpheming againſt the Light of Chriſt Within, mocking and ſcoffing at it, as many dark Preachers and Profeſſors of this Age do, (who have been bred up in Darkneſs and Ignorance from their Youth, who yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver underſtood what the Light of Chriſt With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is) he were not like to prevail upon thoſe who have been turned to it, and have had their Hearts tendered, and in ſome meaſure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by it: But if he come under a <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of it, and his Miniſters confeſſing it, and in words owning of it, profeſſing to be taught and led by it in their talking of it, and in the reſt of their Converſation, eſpecially if they do keep out of the common, groſs Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries that are in the World, then they are like to prevail upon ſuch, who do not faithfully watch in the Light which maketh all things manifeſt as they are. Chriſt hath command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us to <hi>Watch and pray, leſt we fall into the Temptation</hi> (of the Devil). He ſaid to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>What I ſay unto one, I ſay unto all, watch.</hi> The holy Prophet ſaid, <hi>I will hear what God the Lord will ſpeak, for he will ſpeak Peace to his People, and to his Saints;</hi> but let them not turn again to folly. O bleſſed are all they who ſo do, they are the Children of the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that comes down from above; their Eye being kept ſingle to God, they are kept by his mighty Power through Faith, ſo that they ſhall not ſtumble, nor walk in the crooked ways
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65439:10"/> of Satan, which leads to the Chambers of Death, even to take hold on Hell.</p>
            <p>My Friends, you, who are ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced of the bleſſed Truth, as 'tis in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, and have kept your Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations therein, ſome of you may remember what great Evils ſome run into, when they <hi>made a Profeſsion of the Light of Chriſt Within,</hi> and when they had ſo done and were reproved for it, and admoniſhed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and reform, they would tell us, <hi>We muſt leave them to their own Meaſures of the Light of Chriſt, and what they did they were juſtified therein by it:</hi> And ſuch would ſay, <hi>The Light Within is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to teach us, (will not you leave us to it?)</hi> And when ſome had acted things which were evil and ſcandalous, they would ſay, <hi>That they were juſtified by the Light in them.</hi> They would have perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us that the Light of Chriſt Within did lead them into thoſe evil and <hi>confuſed, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Practices</hi> which they run into: But the Lord Jeſus Chriſt by his Light ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us plainly, that thoſe things which they ſaid the Light Within taught them, led them into, and juſtified them in, were the Works and Fruits of Darkneſs, proceeding (through them) from Satan, who had betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deceived them, as he did <hi>Eve.</hi> And as we then withſtood thoſe who blaſphemed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65439:10"/> againſt the Divine Light of Chriſt Within, by ſeeking to father their Works of Darkneſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, by rendering it the Author thereof; ſo in the Light of Chriſt we do withſtand thoſe <hi>vain Talkers of the Light</hi> at this time, whoſe <hi>Walking</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> are in <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> and in the Light of Chriſt we teſtifie to the ſufficiency of it, againſt all Prieſts and Profeſſors whatſoever who blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme againſt it, calling it a <hi>Natural Inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Light,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Take notice, Oh my Friends! That Satan the Prince of Darkneſs, and his dark, wicked, prophane, Generation or Offspring, long have, and at this day do profeſs the great, true, and living God, &amp; Chriſt Jeſus, whom he hath ſent, <hi>in Words</hi> but in <hi>Works</hi> they do deny both the Father and the Son.</p>
            <p>And although Satan, the Prince of Darkneſs, may, in ſome of his confuſed, dark Inſtruments, <hi>confeſs to,</hi> and <hi>profeſs the Light of Chriſt Within,</hi> yet he is ſtill Satan, the Adverſary, the Prince of Darkneſs, and his <hi>Profeſsing</hi> and <hi>Talking</hi> of the Light is <hi>only</hi> with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the more readily to prevail upon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thoſe who through Love to the Light, delight to hear it ſpoken of and commended. <hi>And Satan and his dark Inſtruments have done more harm to ſome ſuch in their falſe feigned Profeſsion &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Light than ever they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65439:11"/> did, or could do, by their direct oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to it, and blaſphemous words againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My dear Friends, Conſider what our Lord Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles have teſtified, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the only true God, and left the ſame upon Record in the Scriptures of Truth; Chriſts Teſtimony is, <hi>That God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in the Spirit, and in the Truth.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi>'s Teſtimony is, <hi>That God is Light, and in him there is no darkneſs at all: If we ſay we have fellowſhip with him, and walk in darkneſs, we lye, and do not the Truth; but if we walk in the Light as he is in the Light, then have we Fellowſhip one with another,</hi> &amp;c. Obſerve that <hi>this living true God, who is a Spirit, and Light, is one God; his Light and Spirit in his People is one in its kind or Nature with himſelf, he being the Fountain of it, and it of himſelf, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not contradict him, or itſelf, in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Meaſures, Manifeſtations &amp; Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of it, in thoſe who receive it, believe, and obey it:</hi> For if it ſhould, or could do ſo, then God by it would be render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Author of Confuſion</hi> [and <hi>not of Peace,</hi>] in all the Churches of the Saints; which to believe or ſuppoſe, is very highly blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous againſt him, and directly contrary to the holy Apoſtles Doctrine, who ſaith, <hi>God is not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65439:11"/> the Author of Confuſion, but of Peace, in all the Churches of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The Fruit of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is in all goodneſs, Righteouſneſs, und Truth, proving what is acceptable unto the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd:</hi> And he exhorted the Saints, ſaying, <hi>Have no Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the unfruitful works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but rather reprove them.</hi> To thoſe who walked in the Spirit and Light of God, he ſaid, <hi>Walk in Love as Chriſt alſo hath loved us:</hi> To theſe alſo he ſaid, <hi>Ye were ſometimes Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but now are ye Lighi in the Lord, walk as Children of the Light.</hi> See <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain he ſaith, <hi>The Fruits of the Spirit is Love, Joy, and Peace, Long ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Temperance; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch there is no Law; and they that <hi>are Chriſts</hi> have crucified the Fleſh, with its Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and Luſts: If we live in the Spirit, let us alſo walk in the Spirit; let us <hi>not</hi> be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of <hi>vain Glory,</hi> provoking one another, envying one another.</hi> Again he ſaith, <hi>The Works of the Fleſh are manifeſt, which are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Fornication, Uncleanneſs, Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Idolatry, Witchcraft, <hi>Dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ance, Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies; Envyings,</hi> Murders, Drunkenneſs, Revellings, and ſuch like, of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in times paſt, that they that do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Gal. 5. Again the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65439:12"/> 
               <hi>John</hi> in the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>He that ſaith <hi>he is in the Light,</hi> and <hi>hates his Brother,</hi> is in <hi>Darkneſs</hi> even until now; he that loveth his Brother abideth in the Light, and there is none occaſion of Stumbling in him: But he that hateth his Brother is in Darkneſs, and walketh in Darkneſs, and knoweth not whither he goeth, becauſe that Darkneſs hath <hi>blinded his Eyes.</hi> If a man ſay I love God, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his Brother, he is a Lyar; this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have we from him, that he who loveth God loveth his Brother alſo.</hi> See 1 <hi>John 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>dear Friends,</hi> Obſerve, <hi>That where the Fruits of the Spirit and Light of God and Chriſt are wanting, in thoſe who profeſs the ſame to be their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Ruler, and Orderer, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, the Fruits or Works of the Fleſh do appear, this is a plain proof, that their ſaying they are taught, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, and governed by the Spirit and Light of God and Chriſt, is very notoriouſly falſe, yea blaſphemous againſt God, Chriſt, and his Divine Light and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> For when Chriſt told his Diſciples, that falſe Prophets, Anti-Chriſts, Deceivers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould come, ſaying, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets which come to you in Sheeps Cloathing, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly they are ravening Wolves,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their Fruits. Do men gather Grapes of Thorns, or Figs of Thiſtles?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65439:12"/> Even ſo every good Tree bringeth forth good Fruit, but a corrupt Tree bringeth forth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Fruit. A good Tree cannot bring forth evil Fruit, neither can a corrupt Tree bring forth good Fruit: Every Tree that bringeth not forth good Fruit is hewn down and caſt into the Fire: Wherefore by their <hi>Fruits</hi> ye ſhall know them. <hi>Not</hi> every one that ſaith unto me Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, but he that doth the Will of my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> See <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 15. and 24. Again he ſaith, <hi>Many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſhall deceive many: <hi>And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Iniquity ſhall abound, the Love of many ſhall wax cold;</hi> But he that ſhall endure unto the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved. There ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſigns and Wonders, inſomuch that if it were poſſible, they ſhall deceive the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Elect.</hi> See <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 11, 12, 13, 24. &amp; ſee <hi>Mark</hi> 13. 22. he repeating the ſame words of Chriſt, and there he ſaith, <hi>Take heed, I have told you before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve Chriſt's Promiſe to the faithful cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Elect, notwithſtanding all the deceiveable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of unrighteouſneſs, which then did, now doth, or hereafter may work in the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Satan, (by feigned Words, or fair, or flattering Speeches, falſe ſigns, or lying wonders, whereby he lieth in wait to betray and deceive, by which he hath prevailed upon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65439:13"/> ſome unſtable, unwatchful, unfaithful, and therefore unskilful Souls, who are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the depths of Satan, ſpeaking in his Agents) yet can he not in his Agents, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Elect, the choſen of God.</p>
            <p>Obſerve, all that are convinced of the truth, and come to ſome degree of Obedience to it, are not come to the <hi>ſettled State of Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> (although they are come to a ſight and feeling of the Spirit of Chriſt, in whom the Election ſtands) in which State it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be deceived. Let not the weakeſt amongſt the Believers in, and Obeyers of the Light of Chriſt Within, be diſcouraged at theſe ſayings; for as they keep to the Light, God the Fountain of it will keep them from falling. God ſet <hi>Adam</hi> in a State of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,</hi> in which it was <hi>poſsible for him to ſtand,</hi> yet it was <hi>not impoſsible for him to fall;</hi> for we both read, and believe, he did fall; he could not ſtand in his own ſtrength, but in the ſtrength of the Lord his Maker, through want of his diligent attendance, and waiting upon God his Maker for preſervation, he fell under the power of the Deceiver. But Chriſt who never fell ſpake of a State, &amp; brings thoſe who continue diligent &amp; watchful into it, which is beyond that, as his forecited words do plainly imply. The Apoſtles writ unto the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in the Light of Chriſt thus: <hi>viz. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Brethren give all diligence to make your
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65439:13"/> Calling and Election ſure; for if ye do theſe things ye ſhall never fall.</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 10. Read the Chapter through, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again he ſaith, <hi>Beware, leſt ye being led away with the Errour of the wicked, fall from your own Stedfaſtneſs: But grow in Grace, and in the Knowledge of our Lord and Savior Chriſt, to him be Glory, now and for ever,</hi> Amen. Chap. 3. 17, 18. Again <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> writes thus: <hi>Now to him that is able to keep you from falling, and to preſent you fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs before the preſence of his Glory, with exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joy, to the only wiſe God our Saviour, be Glory and Majeſty, Dominion and Power, now and ever, Amen. Jude</hi> 24, 25. read the Epiſtle throughout.</p>
            <p>Obſerve further, that the <hi>Settled State of Election,</hi> where deceit cannot enter, is not a State <hi>above,</hi> or <hi>beyond Watchfulneſs,</hi> and the <hi>holy Fear of God</hi> (the Son of God himſelf in the daies of his Fleſh, watched and prayed, and was heard in that he feared, as the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> writes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 7.) but in this State, of <hi>Watchfulneſs,</hi> and the <hi>holy Fear</hi> of God, they continually abiding ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in, to ſuch it is become Natural to dwell and abide there, being rooted and ſettled in the Godly, or Divine Nature, of which they are made partakers; as the Apoſtle writ; ſee 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. See how <hi>Fulks</hi> renders this place in his Confutation of the Popiſh Tranſlation at <hi>Rh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes;</hi> he renders the words <hi>Divine Nature, Godly Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:65439:14"/>
            <p>Eternal Glory to him for the preſervation of his People, who daily wait upon him; he gives them Wiſdom, Strength and Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he who keeps them never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs nor ſleeps; holy and migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y is his Wiſdom and Strength, by which he redeems, preſerves, and up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> his People, in doing that which is well pleaſing in his ſight. Bleſſed are all thoſe who diligently wait to be made partakers of the ſame, they ſhall be upheld thereby through all Temptations, Trials, and the Buffetings, and Winnowings of Satan, out of his ſnares, and over him, (in Chriſt the Elect Seed, which bruiſeth his Head) and over all his <hi>ſeveral ſorts of Agents;</hi> for as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Greater is he that is in us than he that is in the World, by whom we over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O my dear Friends! All diligently wait on God in the Divine Light and Spirit of his Son, that you may grow in the Grace and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt more and more, that you may be all firmly rooted and grounded in him; as Trees or Branches of Righteouſneſs, the planting of the Lord God, that you may bring forth much Fruit to the Praiſe and Glory of his name. Chriſt the living true Vine ſaid unto his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of old, <hi>I am the true Vine, and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the Husbandman; every Branch that beareth not fruit in me, he taketh away; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65439:14"/> every Branch that beareth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit—Abide in me, and I in you: As the branch cannot bring forth of itſelf, except it abide in the Vine, no more can ye, except ye abide in me. I am the Vine, ye are the branches; he that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much fruit; for without me ye can do nothing. If a man abide not in me, he is caſt forth as a branch, and is withered.</hi> Joh. 15. 1, 2, 4, 5. <hi>Herein is my Father glorified, that ye bear much fruit, ſo ſhall ye be my Diſciples. As the Father hath loved me, ſo have I loved you, continue ye in my love. If ye keep my Commandments ye ſhall abide in my love, even as I have kept my Fathers Commandments, and abide in his love. This is my Commandment, that ye love one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother as I have loved you.</hi> See <hi>John</hi> 15. 5, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O my Friends! Theſe are the ſweet and comfortable Sayings of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, our Prince of Life, Love, and Peace. Let them be duly weighed, faithfully regarded and followed by you all who profeſs to be his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> (that is) <hi>Learners of him;</hi> for as he ſaith, <hi>Without him we can do nothing,</hi> except we be joined to his <hi>gracious Spirit</hi> of Light, Life, and Peace, we cannot pleaſe God, but being joined to it, it worketh in us to will and to do that which is well pleaſing in the ſight of the Lord God. So we become
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65439:15"/> his workmanſhip in Chriſt, created in him unto thoſe good Works which God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained we ſhould walk in, that our Light may ſhine before men, that they may behold our good Converſation in Chriſt, conſtantly coupled with that godly fear, wherein there is not only a hating of, but alſo a coming out of, and preſervation from, <hi>Pride, Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy,</hi> and <hi>every evil way</hi>—O my Friends! This is that which is to be deſired, ſought of God, and diligently waited for; this is the <hi>durable Riches</hi> that far excels all that can be mentioned beſides it; this is the <hi>Treaſure</hi> that is to be laid up in Heaven, according to Chriſts Command, <hi>where neither Moth can corrupt, nor Thief break through and ſteal.</hi> Bleſſed are all they who diligently wait for the <hi>Increaſe</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, they ſhall never be forſaken of the Lord; he whoſe the Earth is, and the fulneſs of it, who feeds the Ravens, cloaths the Graſs, and takes care for Sparrows, will take care and provide for them. So all wait, that your Faith and Confidence may be preſerved, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and increaſed to his eternal honour, and your enduring Peace and Comfort; even ſo be it, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65439:15"/>
               <head>Concerning good Conſcience.</head>
               <p>MY <hi>dear Friends,</hi> ſomething lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to write to you in the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Bowels of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Prince of our Chriſtian Peace, Fellowſhip, and Unity. The matter before me is this: I find that there are ſome perſons profeſſing Truth amongſt us, (who not being faithful to the gracious Spirit and Light of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which they make profeſſion of) that are offended with the <hi>Method, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> and <hi>Form</hi> in which Friends Care of Gods Glory, and the good one of another, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; theſe perſons talk much of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience:</hi> To which I ſay, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> (rightly underſtood) hath ever ſince we were a People, been, and ſtill is owned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; but for any who profeſs to be <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Light, Members of the Church which is in God,</hi> to plead Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience for themſelves, without put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a difference betwixt <hi>good Conſcience</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> this is an Unſound and Unchriſtian Plea (for the Apoſtles of Chriſt diſtinguiſheth betwixt <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil Conſcience</hi>) yea, ſhews that they are ſeparated and divided the one from the other, for they proceed from <hi>contrary Cauſes.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>My</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:65439:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65439:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:65439:17"/> 
                  <hi>Conſcience beareth me witneſs in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rom. 9. 1. And again, <hi>I have lived in all good Conſcience unto this day: For our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing is this, the Teſtimony of our Conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly Wiſdom, but by the Grace of God, we have had our Converſation in the World, and more abundantly to you-wards.</hi> See 2 Cor. 1. 12. He who had believed and received the Holy Ghoſt, was made of a good Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by it, his Will and Affections alſo being purified from Corruption thereby, ſo that he did not only underſtand what was <hi>right</hi> and <hi>wrong,</hi> but he alſo willed and took pleaſure to act and do that which was and is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the ſight of the Lord: And this he was enabled to do by the Power of the Holy Ghoſt, or Spirit of Truth, which (according to the Promiſe of Chriſt) leads his faithful Subjects by Degrees from Glory to Glory, from one degree of Grace to another) into all Truth: And ſo are the faithful followers of Chriſt Jeſus led in this our day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> writing to <hi>Timothy</hi> ſaith, <hi>Now the end of the Commandment is charity out of a pure heart and of a good Conſcience, and of Faith unfeigned, from which ſome having ſwerved, have turned aſide unto vain jangling.</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 5, 6. Again ver. 18, 19. he chargeth. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> to <hi>hold Faith and a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me having put away,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65439:17"/> concerning Faith have made ſhipwrack.</hi> Again, <hi>Chap. 3. ver. 9. The Myſtery of Faith is held in a <hi>pure Conſcience.</hi>
                  </hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writes to the Believers thus, <hi>(viz.) Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> that whereas they ſpeak evil of you as of Evil-doers, they may be aſhamed that falſly accuſe your good Converſation in Chriſt.</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning evil Conſcience.</head>
               <p>THE Apoſtle writes thus: <hi>Now the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſpeaketh expreſly, that in the latter times ſome ſhall <hi>depart</hi> from the <hi>Faith,</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heed to the ſeducing Spirits and Doctrines of Devils, ſpeaking Lyes in Hypocriſie, having their Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron.</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 1, 2. Now the Prince that begets and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds this <hi>evil Conſcience,</hi> hardened and ſeared, is the Devil, who abode not in the truth, in whom there is no truth, <hi>he is that Prince of the power of the Air, who works in the hearts of the Children of Diſobedience,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith. This is he who leads into the <hi>fleſhly Liberty</hi> from the Croſs of Chriſt, into the <hi>fleſhly Luſts,</hi> which <hi>war againſt the Soul,</hi> and drowns ſuch men in predition, who become Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt. This <hi>Liberty</hi> is not to be given way unto, nor to be pleaded for by any <hi>true Chriſtian;</hi> this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65439:18"/> is <hi>not</hi> the <hi>Liberty of the Sons of God,</hi> which he hath promiſed to reſtore them into, who believe in Jeſus Chriſt, and take up their daily Croſs and follow him, giving and taking <hi>Liberty</hi> to this <hi>evil Conſcience</hi> brings into corruptible Bondage, yea, it vaſſalizeth the Creature, Soul and Body to Satan; and if <hi>this Liberty</hi> be continued in, it brings everlaſting deſtruction both upon Man and Woman.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> writ to <hi>Titus,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Unto them that are defiled and unbelieving is nothing pure, but even their Mind and Conſciences defiled; they profeſs that they know God, but in <hi>Works</hi> they <hi>deny</hi> him.</hi> See <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 15, 16. Again, the Apoſtle writing to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let us draw near with a true heart, in full aſſurance of Faith, having our hearts ſprinkled from an <hi>evil Conſcience,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let us hold faſt the Profeſſion of our Faith without wavering; for he is faithful that promiſed; and let us conſider one another to provoke unto Love and to good Works, <hi>not forſaking the Aſſembling our ſelves together as the manner of ſome is;</hi> but exhorting one another,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 22, 23, 24, 25.</p>
               <p>Oh my dear Friends! All tenderly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the great work of God in, and through Chriſt, is to put away this <hi>evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and to work in man a good one, yea, to redeem out of all corrupt, ſinful, fleſhly Liberty, which Liberty embondageth the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65439:18"/> Creature under Satans power, as I ſaid before. Now Chriſt the patient and innocent Lamb of God, was ſent by the Father to take away the Sins of the World, which <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> in his Eternal Light ſaw, and teſtified of, and in the ſame Divine Spirit and Light of Chriſt <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet ſaw, and teſtified of, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>He ſhall finiſh Sin and Tranſgreſſion, and ſhall bring in everlaſting Righteouſneſs:</hi> Bleſſed are all they who in Faith and Patience wait to ſee this great Work carried on, and finiſhed in the appointed ſeaſon of the Father.</p>
               <p>O my <hi>Friends!</hi> Seriouſly conſider how <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, apt,</hi> and <hi>prone.</hi> Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are (after they are come to ſome degree of the knowledge of God, and of Chriſt, and of the daily Croſs) to hearken to the Serpents voice, (who deceived <hi>Eve</hi>) who leads into this ungodly Liberty, who by his Transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations hath deceived ſome in our Age after they knew God and Chriſt, as aforeſaid; and he has <hi>promiſed them Liberty</hi> and <hi>great things,</hi> as he did <hi>Eve,</hi> and has brought them into <hi>miſery</hi> as he did <hi>her;</hi> and through this his accurſed work, a Root of Bitterneſs is ſprung up in ſome, which is in danger to defile many, <hi>which God through his tender Mercy put a ſtop unto, confound, and drive backward:</hi> This is the earneſt deſire of my Soul.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writes againſt the <hi>fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65439:19"/> Libertines,</hi> with which the Church was exerciſed in his day, which became matter of much Travel and Grief to the faithful Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; of them he thus writes, <hi>viz. Theſe are Wells without Water, Clouds that are carried with a Tempeſt, to whom the miſt of Darkneſs is reſerved for ever; for when they ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity, they allure through the Luſts of the Fleſh, through much Wantonneſs, thoſe that were <hi>clean eſcaped from them who live in errour: While they promiſe them Liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of Corruption;</hi> for of whom a man is overcome, of the ſame he is brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Bondage,</hi> &amp;c. See 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 16. to the end.</p>
               <p>Dear Friends, Something more is upon me to write concerning <hi>Conſcience.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle writing to the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the Idolatry of the Gentiles, <hi>(viz.) As concerning therefore the eating of thoſe things that are offered in ſacrifice unto Idols, we know that an Idol is nothing in the World; for though there be that are called Gods, whether in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or in Earth, (as there be gods many, and lords many) But to us there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things, and we in him, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things, and we by him; howbeit there is not in every man that knowledge; for ſome with <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the Idol unto this hour, eat it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65439:19"/> as a thing offered unto an Idol, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences being weak are defiled. But meat com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth us not to God; for neither if we eat are we the better, neither if we eat not are we the worſe. But take heed, leſt by any means <hi>this Liberty of yours become a ſtumbling block to them that are weak;</hi> for if any man ſee thee which haſt knowledge ſit at meat in the Idols Temple, ſhall not the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of him which is weak be emboldened to eat thoſe things which are ſacrificed to Idols?</hi> &amp;c. Read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 4. to the end of the <hi>chap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerve here, that ſome with Conſcience of the Idol did eat things ſacrificed unto it, and their Conſciences therein and thereby were defiled. The <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who knew there was no other God but one, were warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Apoſtle, that they ſhould not ſit in the Idols Temple at Meat, with thoſe who eat their meat unto the Idol, leſt their ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhould embolden thoſe ignorant Idolaters to perſiſt in their Ignorance and Idolatry; for though ſome might ſay, they did not eat it to the Idol as the Idolaters did, but for ſtrength and ſuſtenance to the outward man; yet this would not anſwer the Counſel of the Lord in the Apoſtle, nor the Light of Chriſt in their own Souls; but they were to abſtain from eating with them at ſuch Sacrifices, thereby to prevent emboldening them therein. And in <hi>chap. 10. ver.</hi> 20. take his Teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65439:20"/> this ſort of Idolatry in theſe words, <hi>viz But I ſay that the things which the</hi> Gentiles <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, they ſacrifice to Devils, and not to God.</hi> (See <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 28.) <hi>And I would not that ye ſhould have fellowſhip with Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Friends, theſe Teſtimonies I bring, not only to ſhew <hi>good Conſcience</hi> from <hi>evil Conſcience,</hi> and weak from ſtrong, but alſo to ſhew how careful the Apoſtle was, that thoſe believing Gentiles (who had received the knowledge of the one true God) ſhould walk in faithfulneſs to him, according to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which he had given them, that by their good converſation, in Chriſt as well as by their, preaching of the word and Doctrine of the Goſpel, thoſe Idolaters might be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from their dumb Idols to ſerve the living God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning them that are weak in the Faith.</head>
               <p>YET ſomething further concerning them that are weak in the Faith. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle writing to the believing <hi>Romans,</hi> writes thus, <hi>viz. Him that is weak in the Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you; But not to doubtful diſputations; for one believeth that he may eat all things, another who is <hi>weak</hi> eateth hearbs: Let not him that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65439:20"/> eateth deſpiſe him that eateth not, and let not him which eateth not judge him that eateth; for God hath received him.—One man eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth one day above another; another eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every day alike; Let every man be fully perſuaded in his own Mind,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1, 5, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>My Friends, ſome unruly, and ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful perſons of our time, who would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>ſtrong, faithful,</hi> and <hi>wiſe,</hi> under the Profeſſion of the Light of Chriſt Within, have endeavoured to ſtrain and wreſt this laſt cited Scripture, thereby to juſtifie and cover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in the practiſing of ſome things which are contrary to the Truth, as it is in Chriſt Jeſus; as alſo in the omitting and neglecting of ſome things, which the Light of Jeſus hath led the faithful into, not only the Elders or aged in Chriſt, but the younger alſo. In bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with weakneſs we are of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles mind and concerning eating of Hearbs, or any ſort of Food or Meat; we would have all who profeſs the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, to wait diligently in it, that by it their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings may be cleared, that they may ſee as the Apoſtle did, and be perſuaded as he and many more were, and are, that <hi>there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unclean of it ſelf;</hi> that ſo out of weakneſs they may grow ſtrong in the Lord. The ſame Apoſtle who took this care, that they might not judge one another about <hi>Meats,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65439:21"/> Drinks,</hi> and <hi>Days.</hi> Hear what he further ſaith concerning theſe things, when ſome among the Chriſtians would, or did command to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Meats, and would have it received as a Principle or Doctrine of Chriſt in his Church, then the Apoſtle judged it, and ranks it as one of the Doctrines of Devils. See <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p>Obſerve whilſt the abſtaining from Meats, in the before mentioned ſenſe, was practiſed as a <hi>Weakneſs</hi> (which it really was) through ſhortneſs of Underſtanding, he bore with it and exhorted others ſo to do, ſaying, <hi>We who are ſtrong ought to bear the Infirmities of the weak:</hi> Rom. 15. 1. But when ſome did account themſelves ſtrong and wiſe in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, (but were not ſo) would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined it as a Command, that he judged, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Days.</head>
               <p>AGain concerning Days hear what he ſaith, <hi>(viz.) Howbeit then, when ye knew not God, ye did ſervice to them which by nature are no Gods. But now after that ye have known God, or rather are known of God, how turn ye again to the weak and beggerly Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereunto ye deſire again to be in Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65439:21"/> Ye obſerve Days and Months, and Times, and Years; <hi>I am afraid of you, leſt I have beſtowed on you Labour in vain:</hi> Brethren, I beſeech you to be as I am.</hi> Gal. 4. 8, 9, 10, 11. Again hear what he ſaith, <hi>viz. Now the God of Patience and Conſolation grant that you be like minded one towards another, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt Jeſus, that you may with one Mind, and one Mouth glorifie God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Rom. 15. 5, 6.</p>
               <p>Again, hear what the Apoſtle ſaith concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things, writing to the believing <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> viz. <hi>Let no man therefore judge you in Meat or in Drink, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the New Moon, or of the Sabbath days, which are a ſhadow of things to come; But the body is of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. Col. 2. 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, That the Apoſtles and Primitive faithful <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who bore with the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of ſome, in their obſervation of Days, and limiting themſelves to eating of Hearbs, they were not to be judged in their eating or drinking, who eat and drank in the Faith and Counſel of God; neither were they to be judged, becauſe they did not obſerve the <hi>Jews <hi>Holy-days</hi>
                  </hi> (ſo called,) neither becauſe they did not obſerve the Jews <hi>New Moons,</hi> or <hi>Sabbath days,</hi> which are a ſhadow; for they were come to Chriſt, who is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs ſake, to every one that believes, as its written.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:65439:22"/>
               <p>Again, hear what Chriſt ſaith, And he called the Multitude together &amp; ſaid, <hi>Hear and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, Not that which goeth into the Mouth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth the Man, but that which cometh out of the Mouth defileth the Man. Do not you underſtand; that whatſoever entereth in at the Mouth goeth into the Belly and is caſt out into the Draught? but thoſe things that proceed out of the Mouth, cometh forth from the Heart, and they define the Man; For out of the heart proceed evil Thoughts, Murders, Adulteries, Fornications, Thefts, Falſe Witneſs, Blaſphemies, theſe are the things which defile a man.</hi> Matth. 15. 10, 11, 17, 18, 19, 20. And concerning the <hi>Jews Sabbath</hi> hear what Chriſt ſaith, And he ſaid unto them, <hi>The Sabbath was made for Man, and not man for the Sabbath; therefore the Son of Man is Lord alſo of the Sabbath,</hi> Mark 2. 27, 28.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, this he ſaid unto the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who judged his <hi>Diſciples</hi> for plucking the Ears of Corn on the Sabbath day, who ſaid unto him, <hi>Behold, why do they on the Sabbath day that which is not lawful?</hi> Upon which he brought them an Inſtance what <hi>David</hi> did, in eating the <hi>Shew-bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi> But Chriſt by offering up himſelf through the Eternal Spirit, hath ſince that put an end to theſe ſhadows; ſo that the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians were not to be judged for their refuſing to practiſe them when Chriſt had ended them. And
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65439:22"/> though the Apoſtles and Chriſtians did bear with the Practice of theſe things in ſome, after they came to make ſome profeſſion of Chriſt, yet they bore with it as weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which it was, which the ſtrong in Chriſt knew they would outgrow, as they diligently did follow on to know the Lord, through obeying him in what they did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready know; for that is the way for every one to know what is needful for them to know, which they yet know not, even <hi>to be obedient to God in what they do already know:</hi> For he is faithful who hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſaying, <hi>He that is faithful in a little, I will make him Ruler over much. The Path of the Juſt is as the ſhining light, which ſhines more and more unto the perfect day,</hi> as 'tis written. And again, <hi>The light of the Moon ſhall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun ſhall be ſevenfold, as the light of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven days,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now if thoſe weak ones, with whom the Primitive Chriſtians bore in theſe things, ſhould have called them <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> and <hi>Innova<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ors,</hi> and have called their Epiſtles, <hi>rotten Orders, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns Preſcriptions</hi> and <hi>Edicts,</hi> and have judged them in their <hi>Chriſtian freedom,</hi> becauſe they did not continue with them in <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> in <hi>Eating Herbs, Obſervation of Days, Years,</hi> and <hi>Times,</hi> and ſhould have cryed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65439:23"/> up their <hi>Jewiſh bondage</hi> to have been <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty,</hi> and themſelves to be <hi>ſtrong Chriſtians,</hi> and the others to be <hi>weak,</hi> or <hi>darkned</hi> and <hi>Apoſtatized; <hi>Would the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Primitive Chriſtians have owned them as Brethren in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and have had Fellowſhip with them in their ſo doing?</hi>
                  </hi> Yea or Nay? Let Gods faithful Witneſs in all that know it, anſwer this Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Oh! my Friends, I am grieved in Spirit, becauſe of the <hi>hardneſs, wilfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceitedneſs</hi> of ſome, whoſe work, at this day, is to unſettle the minds of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by drawing them from their diligent attendance unto the Spirit, Light, and Voice of God in their own hearts and ſouls, and in the mouths of his faithful Servants, (which Spirit, Light, and Voice in their hearts, and in the mouths of his Servants, is not contradictory to it ſelf in the one or the other) after them, into ungodly jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, evil ſurmiſes, thoughts and imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, words and actions, by which evil work ſeveral perſons, whom the Lord in mercy had gathered near to himſelf, have been drawn out from the ſimplicity, which is in Chriſt, into prejudice, evil jealouſies, and alſo into ſome practices, which are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Truth as it is in Chriſt Jeſus, divers of whom the Lord hath in mercy gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the ſenſe thereof, and through his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65439:23"/> Judgments upon the evil, hath reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them into Unity with himſelf and with his tender people, who in his tender bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els have travelled for their reſtauration, who now greatly rejoyce in their return. <hi>Glory, yea, Glory to his Eternal Name for the ſame, and that for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis my Faith, that God will diſintangle ſome who are yet held by the aforeſaid Snares, for whoſe return my Soul travels in Prayers and Supplications to God: Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful is that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 14. 22. Happy is he that condemneth not himſelf in the thing which he alloweth.</hi> Again he ſaith, <hi>Now I beſeech you, Brethren, by our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſion among you; but that you be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment: For it hath been declared unto me of you, my Brethren, by them which are of the Houſe of</hi> Cloe, <hi>that there are <hi>Contentions</hi> among you. Now this I ſay, that every one of you ſaith, that I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> and I of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and I of <hi>Cephas,</hi> and I of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Is <hi>Chriſt</hi> divided? Was <hi>Paul</hi> Crucified for you? Or were you Baptized in the name of <hi>Paul?</hi> Chriſt ſent me not to Baptize, but to Preach the Goſpel; not with wiſdom of Words, leſt the Croſs of Chriſt ſhould be made of none effect: For the Preaching of the Croſs is to them that periſh, fooliſhneſs; but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65439:24"/> unto us which are ſaved, it is the power of God: For it is written, <hi>I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he wisdom of the wiſe,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. <hi>We preach Chriſt crucified, unto the</hi> Jews <hi>a Stumbling Block, and unto the</hi> Greeks <hi>fooliſhneſs; but unto them which are called, both</hi> Jews <hi>and</hi> Greeks, <hi>Christ the power of God, and the wiſdom of God,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 1. 10, to 19.</p>
               <p>Oh! my <hi>dear Friends,</hi> and all you who profeſs the Divine Light of Chriſt to be your Teacher; ſeriouſly conſider of theſe things: My earneſt deſire for you all is, that you may all diligently wait in the Light of Chriſt, therein to receive a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thereof; for if you therein dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently wait, you will ſee that it was not the Apoſtles deſire or pleaſure, that they ſhould <hi>contend, or be in ſtrife for Apollo,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> or <hi>Him,</hi> or for them one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another; but that they ſhould all exalt and magnifie <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who died for them, and roſe again to govern and lead them in righteouſneſs, and to uphold and juſtifie them in the ſame: And alſo conſider, that he Preached not the Goſpel with the wiſdom of words, or the words which mans wiſdom teacheth, leſt the Croſs of Chriſt ſhould be made of none effect; but he Preached the Goſpel with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, in the words which it taught him; that their Faith, who heard
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65439:24"/> him might not ſtand in the wiſdom of thoſe words, which mans wiſdom teacheth; but in the power of God; for, as he ſaith in 1 <hi>Cor. 4. 19, 20. I will come to you ſhortly, if the Lord will; and will know, not the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h</hi>
                  </hi> (or words) <hi>of them which are puffed up, but the <hi>Power;</hi> for the Kingdom of God is not in <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> but in <hi>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r;</hi>
                  </hi> neither doth it ſtand in meats or drinks, but in <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> into which Kingdom God hath gathered and is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering them that have or yet do, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after may, in ſincerity Hunger and Thurſt after it.</p>
               <p>Again, conſider the Apoſtle took great Care in his Preaching, that the Croſs of Chriſt might <hi>Not</hi> be made of none Effect, that thoſe who were come to bear it, might <hi>Not</hi> be weary of it, and Caſt it off, becauſe of the offence taken by the wicked at them, for their Obedience thereunto (nor for any other cauſe); for it is true as he writ, <hi>the Preaching of the Croſs is to them that periſh fooliſhneſs, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us it is the power of God;</hi> and as it was then, ſo it is now, <hi>he that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the ſpirit; and they that live godlike</hi> (on in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>ſhall ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; but evil men and ſeducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:65439:25"/>
               <p>Again Conſider, oh my <hi>friends,</hi> and all you who profeſs the Light of Chriſt within to be your Teacher, Ruler, and Guide, what is the cauſe that ſome profeſſing the Light within make ſuch a Noyſe againſt that wholſome Method or Order which the God of Order hath brought forth amongſt us, in taking Care of his Glory, and the good one of another; that the profeſſors of the Goſpel and its Light may walk Orderly in the Light as becomes the ſame, that their Light might ſo ſhine before men, that they might ſee their good works, and glorifie their Father which is in Heaven, according to Chriſts Command. Is it not obvious and plain that their Noiſe and Clamour is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſeek a Liberty which Chriſt and the bearing of the Croſs Admits not, nor allowes of? Oh Conſider the ſayings of Chriſt, <hi>Strait is the Gate, and Narrow is the Way that Leads to life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and broad is the Gate, and wide is the Way that Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto deſtruction, and many there be that go in thereat, but Labour ye, To Enter in at the ſtrait gate.</hi> Many Ancient Faithful friends, who have kept their habitations in the Light, and their firſt Love therein to God (the fountain of it) and one to another, have not forgotten what <hi>Exerciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was gone through Twenty Years ago and upward, through the <hi>unſound Notions, Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65439:25"/> 
                  <hi>Practices</hi> of ſome, who not only <hi>profeſſed the Light within,</hi> but Largly <hi>talked</hi> and <hi>Preached in Commendation of it</hi> when they were out of it, and in their works Enemies to it: Oh how were ſome at <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awars</hi> beguiled through their <hi>fair words</hi> &amp; <hi>fine ſpeeches</hi> in their <hi>feigned Commendation of,</hi> and in words <hi>Magnifying the Light within!</hi> they told us in thoſe dayes, <hi>They were come to a greater Diſpenſation and Glory, then we were in,</hi> and they told us, <hi>that we were in the form without the power;</hi> and told us, <hi>God would break our form and ſcatter us;</hi> but they proved falſe Prophets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for God hath <hi>broken</hi> them, and <hi>ſcattered</hi> them, but <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reſerved</hi> and <hi>kept his People,</hi> who have been kept by his Mighty power through Faith in the <hi>true form of Godlineſs,</hi> while divers of them, with their high and vain pretentions, have not only been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged from the Life and Power of Godlyneſs, but alſo from the very form thereof, turning into the Liberty and Luſts of the fleſh, and ſo became Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, whoſe minds went downward, into the Earth and Earthly things, from the Heavenly; the Latter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of ſuch we have ſeen to be worſe than their beginning, though many that were ſo <hi>ſubt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly</hi> prevailed upon and hurt in thoſe days, came (through the tender Mercy of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65439:26"/> God) to ſee the ſnare in which they were taken, and came out of it; and as it was then, ſo will it be with reſpect to divers who through <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lty</hi> and at <hi>unawars</hi> (for want of watchfulneſs in the Holy fear of God) have been of late years, and yet are enſnared and entangled, as others were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; tho ſome whom Satan hath made uſe of to enſnare them, may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Lord by Repentance, but be cut off in his diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>And oh my friends, and all you that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Light within to be your Teacher, Conſider; doth not ſome at this time who profeſs the ſame Light within to be their Teacher, pay Tithes to a <hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rieſts,</hi> go to a <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to be <hi>married,</hi> or be <hi>married</hi> by him, uſe the <hi>unchriſtian Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>faſhons</hi> of the People of the Nation, in their unſound ſpeech and vain Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſome in their <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> and <hi>need<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>appar<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and ſome in <hi>ſwearing,</hi> and ſome in ſeeking to, and complying with, and truſting in the <hi>Arm of fleſh</hi> for their ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and do not theſe Cry, <hi>we muſt be left to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur Liberty in theſe things, We muſt hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Liberty of Concience? and</hi> have <hi>Not</hi> ſome of them preſumptuouſly ſaid, <hi>that the ſpirit or Light of God might allow them to do ſo?</hi> and to cover and juſtifie themſelves in this unchriſtian Liberty, have not ſome of them
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65439:26"/> ſought, to ſtrain and wreſt the afore ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſayings of the Apoſtles Concerning eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Herbs, Meats, and the Obſervation of days, and other parts of the Scripture of Truth? Would not ſome ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oreſt</hi> theſe Scriptures in our time to cover themſelves in the aforeſaid unchriſtian practices? let Gods faithful witneſs in their own hearts ſpeak in this Matter, and let the words that have falen from the Mouthes of ſome of the profeſſors of the Light within (made publick) of late, Witneſs againſt them in this matter.</p>
               <p>The Lord God ſaid by the mouth of his Prophet, <hi>Wo to the Rebellious Children, that take Councell, but not of me; and that Cover with a Covering, but not of my ſpirit, that they may add ſin unto ſin,</hi> Iſa. 30. 1. My tender de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are for all that profeſs the Light &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God withtin, that they may walk in it, &amp; be covered by it, that the woes of God they may Eſcape; but the unruly, looſe and diſorderly profeſſors of it, will not E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the woes and wrath of God, if they do not unfeignedly Repent, and amend their doings; and Ceaſe from their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian deeds, which they have done, and words, which they have ſpoken againſt the Lord God, Chriſt, and his tender faithful ſervants, who have Anciently and to this day do labour in the Word and Doctrine
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65439:27"/> of the Goſpel, in turning many from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Light, from the power of Satan unto God, and for their Preſervation, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation and Eſtabliſhment therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Something concerning <hi>Chriſtian Order,</hi> or, <hi>Order in the Church of Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Apoſtle writes thus, <hi>God is not the Author of <hi>Confuſion</hi> but of <hi>Peace,</hi> in all the Churches of the Saints.</hi> Again, he exhorts or commands, ſaying: <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 33, 40. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> writes thus, <hi>Who is a wiſe man, and endued with knowledge amongst you, let him ſhew, out of a good converſation, his works with meekneſs of wiſdom: But if ye have <hi>bitter Endyings</hi> and <hi>Strife</hi> in your Hearts, glory not, and <hi>lie not againſt the Truth:</hi> This wiſdom deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>not from above,</hi> but is Earthly, Senſual, Deviliſh; for where <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Strife</hi> is, there is <hi>Confuſion</hi> and every evil work; but the <hi>wisdom</hi> that is from above, is firſt <hi>pure,</hi> then <hi>peaceable, gentle,</hi> and <hi>eaſie to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated;</hi> full of <hi>Mercy</hi> and of <hi>good Fruits,</hi> without <hi>partiality,</hi> and without <hi>hypocriſie;</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65439:27"/> and the fruit of Righteouſneſs is ſown in <hi>peace</hi> of them that <hi>make peace,</hi>
                  </hi> James 3. 13. to the end.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be ye followers of me, even as I am of Chriſt: Now I praiſe you, Brethren, that ye remember me in all things, and keep the Ordinances as I delivered them unto you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the reſt will <hi>I ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> when I come,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 1, 2, 3, 4. And again, writing to <hi>Titus,</hi> he ſaith: <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in</hi> Crete, <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt <hi>ſet in order</hi> the things that are want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ordain Elders in every City, as I had appointed thee,</hi> Titus 1. 5. read it through. Again, the Apoſtle writing to the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſaith: <hi>Now concerning the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for the Saints, as I have given order to the Churches of</hi> Galatia, <hi>even ſo do ye,</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 1.</p>
               <p>Obſerve here, that all things were not <hi>ſet in order</hi> at once by the Apoſtles, amongſt the Believers and Profeſſors of Chriſt, but as the work of <hi>Faith, Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation</hi> was wrought in order by degrees, even ſo good outward <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> they grew into gradually, or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; ſo hath it been and is in our day, with thoſe who to the light of Chriſt are turned, who therein wait, and more and more follow on to know the Lord; ſuch do not build again the things which the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65439:28"/> Truth in them hath deſtroyed: They do not <hi>pay Tythes, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>eſt,</hi> or turn back into the <hi>ſinful cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>vain glory</hi> of the world; but they ſtand in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made them free, and hold faſt the Truth, which is their Crown, that no man take it from them, or them from it.</p>
               <p>Now all you that are young in Truth, and all others whom it concerns, take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that thoſe whom God firſt turned from darkneſs to light in this our Age, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came lovers and followers of it, they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by were led in the very morning or Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their knowledge of the Light, and the teachings of it, to <hi>deny being Married by a Hrieſt,</hi> and to <hi>deny paying of Tythes,</hi> and to <hi>deny Sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aring,</hi> to <hi>deny Envyings</hi> and <hi>Strife, Wars</hi> and <hi>Fighting,</hi> which are the fruits of the Fleſh, proceeding from the Luſts thereof, and to <hi>deny the vain cuſtoms, ſinful Lu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>glory of the world; to continue in the denyal of theſe, is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God:</hi> And as it was with the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the beginning, or breaking out of the Goſpel day amongſt us; ſo it is with the faithful now, as with reſpect to their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in the denial of theſe things; and God hath given great <hi>Increa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of his ſpiritual <hi>Treaſures, Riches,</hi> and <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> to thoſe that have continued faithful <hi>ſince that time;</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:65439:28"/> ſo that they are now nearer to the Lord, than they were in the morning of the day, and Infancy of their knowledge of him, <hi>Glory to his Name for the ſame.</hi> And thus it was with the Primitive Believers and Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Light, as the Scriptures of Truth declare.</p>
               <p>Now to ſuch as ſay, <hi>Things amongst us</hi> (who profeſs the Light of Chriſt to be our Teacher) <hi>are not as they were in the beginning;</hi> I ſay, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay,</hi> as with reſpect to <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Perſons profeſſing the Light,</hi> as aforeſaid; <hi>they are not,</hi> nor yet with reſpect to divers things practiſed by the profeſſors of the Light; for the Faithful have grown from one degree of Grace to another, and ſo from the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of <hi>ſome good thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> to the practice of <hi>more good things,</hi> having walked in the Light, <hi>they have held what they had, and gained more,</hi> according to Chriſts promiſe, who ſaid, <hi>He that is faithful in a little, I will make him Ruler over much:</hi> And there is to be a growing from <hi>ſtrength to ſtrength,</hi> and from <hi>Glory</hi> to <hi>Glory,</hi> from one degree of Grace to another, till there be an appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Sion</hi> in perfect beauty, till there be a coming to the meaſure of the Stature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, to a perfect man in Chriſt Jeſus. This is accordiog to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Doctrine: Who thus goes on gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually towards perfection, are <hi>no A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ates,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65439:29"/> Backſliders,</hi> or <hi>Drawers back to perdition; but preſſers forward for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Redemption of their Souls:</hi> So theſe are in a better condition than they were in the beginning of their profeſſion of the Spirit, Truth, and Light of Chriſt within; As he ſaith, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>very Scribe that is taught or inſtructed unto the Kingdom of God, is like unto a Man that is an Houſholder, which bringeth out of his Treaſure things new and old.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All that come to this State, walking in the light, as aforeſaid, they increaſe in good Order in the Power of God.</p>
               <p>And again, Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Take heed what you hear,</hi> &amp;c. And he ſaid, <hi>Whereunto ſhall we liken the Kingdom of God? Or with what compariſon ſhall we compare it? It is like a Grain of Muſtard-ſeed, which when it is ſown in the Earth, is leſs than all the ſeeds that be in the Earth: but when it is ſown, it groweth up, and becometh greater than all Herbs, and ſhooteth out great Branches,</hi> ſee Mark 4. v. 24. to 32.</p>
               <p>Oſerve here the Parables that Chriſt ſpoke concerning the Kingdom of God, and the Increaſe of it: Now as the Grain of Muſtardſeed is ſmall, but being ſown in the Earth groweth gradually, and in due ſeaſon brings forth great increaſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65439:29"/> of its own Nature and Kind, even ſo the Heavenly <hi>ſpark</hi> or <hi>ſeed of life,</hi> being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in by man, it takes root in his heart, and grows gradually, and in the Appointed ſeaſon of the Father brings forth fruit, firſt a little, and afterwards <hi>more;</hi> for Chriſt the living Vine ſaid, <hi>In this is my Father gloryfied, that you bring forth much fruit: I am the true vine, my father is the husbandman. Every branch that bringeth not forth fruit (<hi>in me</hi>) he taketh away; and every branch that beareth fruit, he purgeth, that it may bring forth more fruit,</hi> Joh. 15. And again, he ſaid, <hi>So is the Kingdom of God, as if a man ſhould caſt ſeed into the ground, and the ſeed ſhould ſpring and grow up,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for the earth bringeth forth fruit of her ſelf, firſt the <hi>blade,</hi> then the <hi>ear,</hi> then the <hi>full corn</hi> in the <hi>ear,</hi> Mark. 4. v.</hi> 26. to 32.</p>
               <p>Again, the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Propheſying of Chriſts Government and Kingdom, writes thus, <hi>For unto us a Child is born, unto us a Son is given, the Government ſhall be on his ſhoulder, and his name ſhall be called <hi>wonderful Counſellor,</hi>
                  </hi> the <hi>mighty God,</hi> the <hi>everlaſting Father,</hi> the <hi>Prince of Peace; <hi>of the increaſe of his Government and Peace, there ſhall be no end; upon the Throne of</hi>
                  </hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>and upon his Kingdom to Order it, and to <hi>Eſtabliſh it with Judgment,</hi> and with <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:65439:30"/> from henceforth even for ever: The zeal of the Lord of Hoſts will perform this,</hi> ſee Iſa. 9. 6, 7.</p>
               <p>Obſerve here the Parable of the Grain of Wheat caſt into the Earth, it <hi>firſt</hi> ſprings to the <hi>Blade; ſecondly</hi> to the <hi>Ear; thirdly</hi> to the <hi>full</hi> or <hi>ripe <hi>Corn</hi>
                  </hi> in the <hi>Ear.</hi> Now it may be truly ſaid, that when the Grain of Wheat is ſprung up to the <hi>Ear,</hi> it is not as it was in the beginning of its growth into the <hi>Blade,</hi> as with reſpect to the ſtature and growth of it; for the <hi>ſecond</hi> is greater than the <hi>firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, it may be ſaid, when it is grown to <hi>full ripe Corn</hi> in the <hi>Ear,</hi> it is not as it was in the beginning of its growth into the <hi>Blade,</hi> nor as it was when it was grown to the Ear, but not ripe, full, or perfect Corn; for the third degree of its <hi>growth</hi> was greater than the <hi>firſt</hi> or <hi>ſecond,</hi> though they proceeded of <hi>one ſeed</hi> and were of <hi>one kind,</hi> and all <hi>good</hi> and beautiful in the order of their growth. Now this Grain of Wheat, and the fruit and product of it, in the ſeveral <hi>degrees</hi> of the <hi>growth</hi> thereof to its <hi>perfection,</hi> being made by Chriſt a Parable of the <hi>Heavenly Seed</hi> of God in the Hearts of his People, and of the ſeveral degrees of its work and appearance in them, and of <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir ſeveral degrees</hi> of growth in it from their <hi>Infancy</hi> therein, to their
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65439:30"/> 
                  <hi>compleatneſs</hi> or <hi>ripe Age in Chriſt.</hi> All you that profeſs to be the Generation or Off-ſpring of this <hi>Heavenly Seed, Try and prove your ſelves</hi> in this matter, be retired in the Spirit of your minds, and with the Light (you make profeſſion of) <hi>take a view of your States</hi> and <hi>Conditions,</hi> and ſee whether your growth and proſperity in the Truth doth anſwer this parable, Yea or Nay.</p>
               <p>And obſerve what <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Propheſied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſts <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> He ſaith, <hi>Of the Increaſe of His Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Peace there ſhal be no End.</hi> Now they, who under the profeſſion of the Light within, are againſt this pure <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of Chriſt, and the increaſe of it, in the particuler, and in his <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>generall, <hi>who are for bringing in and Practiſing a corrupt fleſhly Liberty, Contrary to Chriſt, theſe are the Apoſtates and Innova<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ors,</hi>
                  </hi> with ſuch the Faithful <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Apoſtles and Elders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were <hi>Exerciſed</hi> and <hi>gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ved</hi> in the Primitive times, as the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> of <hi>Paul, Peter, John, Jude,</hi> &amp;c. do ſhew.</p>
               <p>Hear what <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith Concerning this matter, <hi>viz. The Lord knoweth how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Godly out of Temptations, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the unjuſt unto the day of Judgment, to be <hi>puniſht;</hi> but Chiefly them that walk af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65439:31"/> the <hi>fleſh</hi> in the <hi>Laſt</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, and diſpiſe Government; preſumtuous are they, ſelf-willed,</hi>—having Eyes full of Adultery, and that cannot ceaſe from Sin, <hi>beguiling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Souls</hi>—Theſe are wells without Water, Clouds that are Carryed with a Tempeſt, to whom the miſt of Darkneſs is reſerved for ever; for when they ſpeake great <hi>ſwelling words of vanity,</hi> they alure through the Luſt of the fleſh, through much wantonneſs, thoſe that were <hi>Clean Eſcaped</hi> from them <hi>who live in Errour:</hi> while they promiſe them <hi>Liberty,</hi> they themſelves are the <hi>Servants of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> for of whom a man is overcome, of the ſame he is brought into bondage,</hi> 2 Peter 2. 9, 10, 14, 17, 18. 19. read the Chapter through.</p>
               <p>And as it was in their dayes, <hi>ſo is it in ours; ſome fell away</hi> then from the faith and Obedience to the Croſs of Chriſt, who had been Enlightened, and taſted of the Heavenly Gift, and of the power of the World to Come; who while they therein abode, were as Stars in the Firmament of the power of God, and as the Clouds that are filled with rain, and as the Trees of the Lords Planting, which brought forth ſome fruit to him; but when they fell away from Chriſt, <hi>the root, ſeed, Light and fountain of life, then their fruit withered, and ſo they came
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65439:31"/> to be without fruit,</hi> as <hi>Jude</hi> writeth; <hi>Trees twice dead, pluckt up by the Roots,</hi> &amp;c. and could not grow any more.</p>
               <p>Now obſerve, <hi>it is not with theſe</hi> as it was in the <hi>beginning,</hi> when they were firſt turned to the Light of Chriſt, by which they come to ſee their Sins, and to be led to Repent of them, and to forſake them; <hi>the latter End of theſe is, and will be, worſe than their beginning,</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writes concerning ſuch; for ſaith he, <hi>It had been <hi>better</hi> for them not to have known the way of Righteouſneſs, than after they have known it, to <hi>turn from</hi> the Holy Commandment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to them; but it is come to paſs according to the true Proverb, <hi>the dog is returned to his own vomit again, and the ſow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the Mire,</hi> 2 Peter 21. 22. <hi>ſuch,</hi>
                  </hi> in former time, <hi>became the <hi>Agents of Sathan to ſeduce and draw others from the Faith and Obedience of the Croſs of Chriſt; ſome ſuch have been and are in our day.</hi>
                  </hi> All you that Love the Light of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which makes Manifeſt all things as they are, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves that which is Evil, wait dilligently in the Light, that therein you may ſee all the <hi>Myſterious</hi> workings of <hi>Sathan</hi> and his <hi>Agents,</hi> that therein waiting and a biding ſtedfaſt, you may Eſcape all their Snares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:65439:32"/>
               <head>Something more Concerning the order of the works of God in Heaven and Earth, and particularly in his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</head>
               <p>THE great God, who made Heaven and Earth; and the fountains of Water, who made all things good in the beginning, he is the <hi>great God of Order,</hi> he works his works in <hi>Order.</hi> In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining God Created the Heaven and the Earth, and the Earth was without <hi>form</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> and Darkneſs was upon the face of the Deep, and the ſpirit of God Moved upon the Face of the Waters, and God ſaid, let there be <note n="*" place="margin">Note, God Commanded the Light to be and appear the firſt day.</note> 
                  <hi>Light,</hi> and there was <hi>Light,</hi> and God ſaw the <hi>Light</hi> that it was Good, and God divided the <hi>Light</hi> from the <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> and God called the <hi>Light Day,</hi> and the <hi>Darkneſs</hi> he called <hi>Night,</hi> and the Evening and the morning were the firſt day: and God ſaid let there be a Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament in the midſt of the Waters, and let it divide the Waters from the Waters, and God made the Firmament, and divided the Waters which were under the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65439:32"/> from the Waters which were above the Firmament, and it was <hi>ſo,</hi> and God called the Firmament <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the Evening and the Morning were the ſecond day; and God ſaid let the waters under the Heaven be gathered together unto one place, and let the dry Land appear, and it was ſo; and God called the dry Land <hi>earth,</hi> and the gathering together of the waters called he <hi>ſeas,</hi> and God ſaw that it was good; and God ſaid, Let the Earth bring forth graſs, the Herb yeilding ſeed, and the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree yeilding fruit after his kind, <hi>whoſe ſeed is in it ſelf</hi> upon the Earth, and it was ſo, and the Earth brought forth graſs, and Herb yeilding ſeed, after his kind, and the tree yeilding fruit, whoſe ſeed was in it ſelf after his kind, and God ſaw that it was good, and the Evening and the morning were the Third day: and God ſaid, let there be Lights in the Firmament of the Heaven to divide the Day from the Night, and let them be for <hi>Signes</hi> and for <hi>Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ous,</hi> and for <hi>Dayes</hi> and <hi>Years,</hi> and let them be for Lights in the Firmament of Heaven, to give Light upon the Earth, and it was ſo, and God made two great Lights, the greater Light to Rule the day, and the leſſer Light to Rule the Night, he made the Stars alſo, and God ſet them in the Firmament of the Heaven, to give Light upon the Earth, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65439:33"/> to Rule over the Day, and over the Night, and to divide the Light from the Darkneſs, and God ſaw that it was good, and the Evening and the Morning were the Fourth day: and God ſaid, let the waters bring forth aboundantly the moving Creature that hath life, and Foul that may fly above the Earth in the open Firmament of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and God Created great Whales, and every living Creature that moveth, which the waters brought forth aboundantly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their kind, and every winged Foul af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his kind, and God ſaw that it was good, and God bleſſed them, ſaying, <hi>be fruitful and Multiply, and fill the waters in the Seas, and let Foul Multiply, in the Earth,</hi> and the Evening and the Morning were the Fifth day: and God ſaid, let the Earth bring forth the Living Creature after his kind, Cattle and Creeping thing, and Beaſt of the Earth, after his kind, and it was ſo, and God made the Beaſt of the Earth after his kind, and Cattle after their kind, and every thing that Creepeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth after his kind, and God ſaw that it was good; and God ſaid, <hi>let us make Man in our own Image,</hi> after our Likeneſs, and let them have Dominion over the Fiſh of the Sea, and over the Foul of the Air, and over the Cattle, and over all the Earth, and over every Creeping thing that Creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65439:33"/> upon the Earth; ſo God Created Man in his own Image, in the Image of God Created he him, Male and Female Created he them; and God bleſſed them; and God ſaid unto them, <hi>be fruitful, and multiply, and repleniſh the Earth, and ſubdue it, and have <hi>Dominion</hi> over the Fiſh of the Sea, and over the Foul</hi> of the Air, and over every Living thing that moveth upon the Earth; and God ſaid, behold I have Given you every Herb, bearing ſeed, which is upon the face of all the Earth, and every Tree in the which is the fruit of a tree yeilding ſeed, to you it ſhall be for ever, and to every beaſt of the Earth, and to every Foul of the Air, and to every thing that Creepeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth wherein there is life, I have given every green herb for meat, and it was ſo, and God ſaw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good, &amp; the Evening and the Morning were the Sixth day. Thus the Heaven and the Earth were finiſhed, and all the hoſt of them, and on the Seventh day God ended his work which he had made, and he reſted on the Seventh day from all his work which he had made, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are the generations of the Heavens and of the Earth when they were Created. Read the whole firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and the beginning of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:65439:34"/>
               <p>Obſerve here the Beautiful and Lowly <hi>order</hi> of the work of the great <hi>God of Order,</hi> in bringing forth his Beauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul Creation of Heaven and Earth, and all things in them; behold he did not make Heaven and Earth and all things that are in them at once, or in one day; you may here Read what he made the <hi>Firſt day,</hi> and what he made the <hi>Second day,</hi> and what he made the <hi>Third day,</hi> and what he made the <hi>Fourth day,</hi> and what he made the <hi>Fifth day,</hi> and what he made the <hi>Sixth day,</hi> and that he finiſhed and ended his work on the <hi>Seventh day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reader, here thou mayeſt ſee how the works of God were Carried on by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, to their Compleatneſs; Likewiſe thou mayeſt obſerve the Ignorance of ſome in our day, who ſay, <hi>Things among us</hi> (who profeſs to be Taught and led by the Light of Chriſt within) <hi>are not as they were in the beginning, when we were firſt turned to the Light, but here is new Order or Orders ſet up amongſt us, ſeveral Meetings and Practices, which we are afraid, will bring in Apoſtacy.</hi> Such Ignorant, Dark talk as this have I heard from ſome who account themſelves <hi>Children of Light, Ancient in Truth, Grown, Wiſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Obſerve from what God has ſpoken by the Mouth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as aforeſaid, that from
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65439:34"/> the <hi>Firſt day</hi> to the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> in which God ended his work, he brought forth <hi>New things every day,</hi> This glorious work he Carried on by <hi>degrees,</hi> till he had <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated it</hi> according to the Counſell of his own will.</p>
               <p>Again, obſerve, Man, who was at the firſt made in the likeneſs of his Maker, <hi>holy, Juſt, and good,</hi> being ſeduced, deceived by the Serpent, who abode not in the Truth, in whom there is no Truth, he is become a degenerate plant of a ſtrange Vine unto God, by <hi>taking, eating,</hi> and <hi>doing,</hi> that which the great God from the firſt hath forbidden, he died the Death according to the word of the Lord, and in this dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate fallen State is dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, his <hi>Spirit, mind, will,</hi> and <hi>affections,</hi> dead from God, from Purity, from Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Righteouſneſs and Innocency, in this State of Death he doth not <hi>Rightly</hi> ſeek after the Living God, in this State he is not <hi>rightly</hi> affected towards him, he doth not behold his goodneſs, his glory and Mighty power, he doth not Reverence and fear him as he ought, neither doth he hunger and thirſt after him and his Righteouſneſs, Purity, Juſtice, Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, his dead mind, will, and affections, all dead from God, are <hi>Imployed</hi> and <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed</hi> by Satan in that which is Evil,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65439:35"/> and that continually, as the Lord hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the mouth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> viz. <hi>And God ſaw that the wickedneſs of man was great in the Earth, and that every Imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only Evil continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and it repented the Lord that he had made man on the Earth, and it grieved him,</hi> &amp;c. Geneſis 6. 5, 6.</p>
               <p>Obſerve the great and merciful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and God of the whole Earth, hath promiſed the <hi>Redemption</hi> of his Creature <hi>Man,</hi> yea, both the Male and Female out of the Bondage of Corruption, into the glorious Liberty of the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God; this he hath ſpoken by the mouths of his Servants, as it is written in the Scriptures of Truth, when God gave his juſt and righteous Sentence of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the Serpent, for his Curſed work of deceiving the Man and the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he ſaid unto the Serpent, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt done this, thou art Curſed above all Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and above every Beaſt of the Field, upon thy Belly ſhalt thou go, and Duſt ſhalt thou eat all the days of thy Life; and I will put Enmity between thee and the Woman, and between thy Seed and her Seed, and it ſhall bruiſe thy Head,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Geneſis</hi> 3. 14, 15. The Apoſtle writing concerning this Seed, ſaith, <hi>Now to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his Seed were the promiſes made; he ſaith not, and to Seeds,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65439:35"/> as of many, but as of one, and to thy Seed, which is Chriſt,</hi> Gala. 3. 16. This Seed Chriſt was Glorified with the Father before the World began; as he ſaid, <hi>Glorifie thou me with thine own ſelf, with the Glory that I had with thee before the World began,</hi> Joh. 17. he is that Eternal Divine Word, by whom all things were made, who lighteth every that cometh into the World, who, in the days of his Fleſh, commanded man, ſaying, <hi>Believe in the Light, walk in the Light,</hi> &amp;c. The Apoſtle writing of him to the Saints, ſaid, He was Ordained from of old, but manifeſt for you in the laſt time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> made of the Seed of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> according to the Fleſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be the Son of God with Power, by the Reſurrection from the Dead; he was made in due time of a Woman under the Law, to Redeem them that were under the Law; he went up and down doing good, healing all manner of Diſeaſes, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies and Sickneſſes; yea, he raiſed the Dead unto life; after which he offered up himſelf through the Eternal Spirit, as a Lamb without ſpot and blemiſh, an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Sacrifice to God for the remiſſion of the ſins of the Tranſgreſſors, (who believe in him, and come to the obedience of the Faith,) he roſe from the Dead the Third Day, and appeared to his Diſciples, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65439:36"/> gave them many things in Charge, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to feed his Lambs and Sheep, (and to love one another, and love Enemies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) after which he aſcended according to the Scriptures, and is on the right-hand of the Majeſty on High, from whence <hi>be</hi> ſhall proceed to Judg the World in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, the man <hi>Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> this is he who was with the Church in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the ſpiritual Rock; for ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>He was with the Church in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs;</hi> for ſaith he, <hi>They all eat the ſame ſpiritual meat; they all drink the ſame ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al drink; they eat and drank of the Rock that followed them, and that Rock was Chriſt;</hi> this is h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of whom <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations</hi> teſtifies, ſaying, <hi>He rides upon a White Horſe, his Veſture is dipt in blood, his Name is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the Armies which are in Heaven follow him.</hi> This is he that was dead and is alive, and lives for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, who hath the Keys of Hell and of Death, who ſlays the Dragon that plays in the Sea, who deſtroys Death, and him that hath the Power of Death, which is the Devil; this is he who is the Reſurrection of the Dead, and the Life of the Living; this is he who ſaid, <hi>He that believeth on me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he live;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>he that liveth and believeth, ſhall never dye; <hi>Martha,</hi> believeſt thou this?</hi> this is he of whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65439:36"/> writ to the Saints, ſaying, <hi>Ye, that ſome time were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, hath he quickened; by Grace ye are ſaved through Faith, and that not of your ſelves; for it is the gift of God.</hi> Again, this is he of whom the Apoſtle writ, ſaying, <hi>We have all been gone aſtray, as Sheep without a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd; but now we are returned to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of our Salvation, and Biſhop of our Souls:</hi> this is he of whom tis written, <hi>That there is no Name given under Heaven, by which man can be ſaved, but by the name of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> it is alſo written of him, <hi>That there is not Salvation in any other;</hi> he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath ſaid, <hi>I am the way to the Father; no man can come to the Father but by me; I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life; I am the Door, he that enters in by me the Door, ſhall go in and find Paſture; I am the good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd; I lay down my Life for my Sheep; all that came before me, they are Thieves and Robbers.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8. 9. they who Preach the Words of God, ſpoken by his Spirit, in, and by his Son, or in &amp; by his Prophets or Apoſtles, without the Spirit of God and Chriſt, they ſteal, the Lord is againſt them, ſee <hi>Jer. 23. Ezekel</hi> 13, 1. to the end. 1 <hi>Cor. 2. 10, 11. 1 Pet. 1. 11. 1 Cor.</hi> 12. 3.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:65439:37"/>
               <p>Obſerve, This is he by whom God brings forth his <hi>New Creation in man,</hi> who was fallen dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he is a New Creature; old things are paſſed away, behold all things are become New; and all things are of God;</hi> and he writ to the Saints, ſaying, <hi>We are Gods workmanſhip, Created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good Works, which God before Ordained that we ſhould walk in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerve, This is he that burns up the <hi>old Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>old Earth,</hi> which Satan hath filled with Sin and Wickedneſs; this is he that Baptizeth with the Holy Ghoſt, and with Fire, who burns up all the <hi>falſe Joy, falſe Pleaſure,</hi> which is as a <hi>falſe Heaven;</hi> for as the <hi>Kingdom of God the true Heaven,</hi> conſiſts in true Joy and Peace, ſo Satan transforms himſelf in his dark King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in fallen man, which he has filled with ſin, and gives him, for a ſhort time, a <hi>falſe Joy</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> in <hi>Evil doing;</hi> this is <hi>that Joy</hi> that muſt be turned into <hi>Sorrow;</hi> this is <hi>that Peace</hi> which is not <hi>the Peace of God,</hi> therefore God will deſtroy it. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and all things, were good in the beginning, and man was good, yea very good, his Spirit, Soul and Body; but being fallen from God, degenerated into a Plant of a ſtrange Vine, his Heart, Mind, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65439:37"/> Will and Affections, all Corrupted, Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, Slain, Dead, from God, he is now become as the corrupt Earth, which brings forth Bryers and Thorns, whoſe end is to be burned. Mankind in the fall is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by the Prophet as a <hi>Foreſt</hi> or <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> overgrown with <hi>Bryers</hi> and <hi>Thorns,</hi> and he Propheſies of the day of the Lord that ſhall come upon this <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, Bryers</hi> and <hi>Thorns, Sin</hi> and <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,</hi> and ſhall burn them up. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the Prophet of the Lord ſaith, <hi>The day of the Lord ſhall come, which ſhall burn as an Oven, and the Proud, and <hi>all</hi> that do wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble, and it ſhall burn them up, and leave them neither Root nor <hi>Branch.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>All have ſinned and come ſhort of the glory of God; Sin brought Death and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from God; God ſaith by the Prophet, <hi>Your Sins ſeparate betwixt you and your God, your ſins with-hold good things from you; waſh you, make you clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine Eyes, and then draw near, and let us reaſon together; though your ſins were as Crimſon, I will make them as Snow, though they were as blood, I will make them as Wool; I will carry them into a Land of forgetfulneſs, and Will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them as far from you, as the</hi> Eaſt <hi>is from the</hi> Weſt. Again, God commands
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65439:38"/> by the Apoſtle, ſaying, <hi>Cleanſe your hands you ſinners, purifie your hearts ye double mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, be afflicted and mourn, let your laughter be turned into heavineſs, and your joy into mourning; humble your ſelves under the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand of God, and he ſhall exalt you in due time.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the Dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee Light,</hi> Epheſ. 5. 14.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, That all the fallen dead ſons and daughters of <hi>Adam,</hi> who come to be made alive to God, to become a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him, to bring forth fruit to his Glory, <hi>they muſt</hi> come to be <hi>Awakened</hi> by the Spirit and Voice of God, ſounding an alarum in their own Hearts and Souls, to have their ears opened to his voice, the eyes of their unberſtandings opened to ſee him a God nigh at hand, they muſt know the Revelation of the Righteous Judgments of God upon the head of the Serpent in their own Hearts, Minds, Wills, and Affections, and through his Righteous Judgments to know the old man with his deeds which are Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, according to the deceitful Luſts of the fleſh put off, and ſo to know the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Apoſtles words, who ſaid, <hi>They that are Chriſts have Crucified the fleſh, with the Affections and Luſts; He that is in Chriſt is a New Creature.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:65439:38"/>
               <p>Again, obſerve, this work of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Creature</hi> out of the bondage of Corruption, into the glorious Liberty of the ſons and daughters of God, is a work that is carried on by Degrees, as Chriſt hath ſhewed and ſet it forth in many Parables, ſhewing the ſmalneſs of its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, as to the ſence and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Creature in whom it is begun; The Kingdom of God in the unregenerate is Compared to a grain of <hi>Wheat</hi> caſt into the Earth, which firſt <hi>ſuffers,</hi> or <hi>dyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> but in its ſuffering or dying brings forth the fruit of its own kind, firſt the <hi>blade,</hi> then the <hi>ear,</hi> then the <hi>full,</hi> or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ipe Corn,</hi> in the <hi>Ear,</hi> It is alſo Compared to a grain of <hi>Muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ard Seed</hi> caſt into the Earth, which being ſmall, yet in the Appointed ſeaſon of him that gives the increaſe, brings forth fruit plentifully: Again, it is Compared to <hi>Leaven</hi> put in three meaſures of Meal, till the whole was Levened: Again, it is Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a <hi>Net caſt into the Sea,</hi> which gather good and bad to the ſhore, and gathers the good into Veſſels, but caſts the bad away.</p>
               <p>Obſerve ſtill, here is a glorious <hi>Order</hi> in the work of mans Regeneration and Reſtoration to God; Man, who is turned from Darkneſs to Light, from Sathans po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to God, with the Light he is come to ſee his ſin: Now he is to wait to know
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65439:39"/> God, (who is a Conſuming fire to ſin and wickedneſs,) to appear in him, to burn up and Conſume his Sins, to Slay that Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon or Serpent in him, who has led him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sin, and hath kept him in it, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to take pleaſure in the ſame. Now he is to wait to know the Mighty, Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Dreadful God, to appear in him as a <hi>refiners fire,</hi> and as <hi>Fullers ſoap;</hi> Now he is patiently to bear the Indignation of the Lord, becauſe he hath ſinned, untill he hath Mercy on him; for he will not Contend forever with the Repenting, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Penitent ones, becauſe he delights in Mercy. Now he that thus believes, waits, and ſubmits to the Chaſtiſing hand of the Lord, doth not always Continue under his rebukes, Chaſtiſement or Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in the mideſt of Judgment he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers Mercy to ſuch; under Judgment he ſupports the Spirits of theſe Contrite ones; he ſtrengthens them in this <hi>Winter ſeaſon,</hi> and he Leads them through it, as a man of God hath written, <hi>Behold the Winter is over and gone, the time of Rejoycing is come, and the voice of the Turtle is heard in our Land.</hi> Thus they that have ſet their faces <hi>Sion</hi>-wards; and are travelling with their faces thither-wards, go on and grow from glory to glory, from ſtrength to ſtrength, from one degree in the grace of Chriſt Jeſus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65439:39"/> another, untill they appear in <hi>Sion</hi> in perfect beauty; ſo theſe are not like a <hi>Dwarff,</hi> that doth not grow; for a <hi>Dwarff</hi> was by the Law of God <hi>forbiden</hi> to be a Prieſt, and ſo was a <hi>Lepor;</hi> but ſuch who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, wait, and grow, as aforeſaid, are not as the <hi>Dwarff</hi> or <hi>Lepor,</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſed,</hi> who are all Corrupt, from the Crown of the Head to the Sole of the Foot, and who hath <hi>no Health in them</hi> as they ſay; but theſe are come to Chriſt the Phyſician of Value, yea the ſaving Health of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as its written of him; though theſe can do nothing of themſelves, yet they can do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengthens them, which the Apoſtle knew and writ of; Theſe have put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; Theſe make no proviſion for the fleſh, to fulfill the Luſt thereof; theſe are ſtrengthened by Chriſt (who is Gods glorious power and wiſdom) in their Inward man, as its written; theſe grow ſtrong in the Lord; by degrees, theſe put on the whole Armor of God, by which they are defended from all the fiery Darts of the Devil, theſe are made Conquerors in Chriſt, who Deſtroys the Devil, and his works in them; To theſe is given the <hi>Spirit of Praiſe</hi> inſtead of that of <hi>heavineſs;</hi> theſe are returned to <hi>Sion</hi> with ſongs of diliverance, and Everlaſting joy; amongſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65439:40"/> theſe God reigns, in and through them he ſhines, to enlighten the dark World, which lyes in wickedneſs; Thus its writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Out of</hi> Sion, <hi>the perfection of beauty, God hath ſhined.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle writing of the <hi>Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Order</hi> of the work of God in Heaven &amp; Earth, ſaith, <hi>There is one Glory of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and another Glory of the <hi>Moon,</hi> and another Glory of the <hi>Stars,</hi> for one Star differeth from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Star in Glory, ſo alſo is the Reſurrection of the dead,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 41, 42.</p>
               <p>Obſerve here, what the Apoſtle hath written concerning the Different <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> in Heaven, &amp; ſaith, <hi>ſo is the Reſurrection of the dead;</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſeveral States and Conditions of thoſe whom Chriſt hath Quickened or raiſed in ſome degree from death to life, do alſo differ in their ſeveral degrees of growth in Life, Stature, and Strength, and accordingly do differ in their gifts and places, and glory and beauty, in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from Death to Life.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſaid to them whom he had Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened, <hi>I am come that you might have life, and that you may have it more abundantly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, The Pſalmiſt, who was Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God and his appointment, both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and King, writ thus, <hi>Praiſe ye the Lord; Praiſe the Lord from the Heavens; Praiſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65439:40"/> him in the heights; Praiſe ye him all ye his Angels; Praiſe ye him, all ye his hoſts; Praiſe ye him, Sun and Moon; Praiſe ye him all ye Stars of Light; Praiſe him, ye Heavens of Heavens, and ye Waters, that be above the Heavens, Let them praiſe the Name of Lord; for he commanded, and they were Created; he hath alſo Eſtabliſhed them forever and ever, he hath made a decree which ſhall not paſs; Praiſe the Lord from the Earth ye Dragons and all deeps, Fire, and Haile, Snow and Vapour, Stormy Wind, fulfilling his word, Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and all Hills, fruitfull trees and all Cedars, Beaſts and all Cattle, Creeping things and flying Fouls, Kings of the Earth and all People, Princes and all Judges of the Earth, both young Men and Maidens, old Men and Children, let them Praiſe the Name of the Lord; for his name alone is Excellent, his Glory is above the Earth and Heaven, &amp;c.</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al. 148. read it through.</p>
               <p>Here again Obſerve, the great <hi>God of Order,</hi> who in the beginning Created all things <hi>in Order,</hi> and placed them in <hi>their Order</hi> in Heaven and Earth, all which was very good; he calls of them in <hi>Order,</hi> by the mouth of his Prophet, to praiſe, Magnifie and Glorifie him, for whoſe glory and honour they all were Created good in the beginning; <hi>Oh vain Man!</hi> who under the Dark power of Satan, has been
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65439:41"/> bred up in thy Tranſgreſſion as a Wild Aſſes Colt, or as a Wild Bullock unaccuſtomed to the yoke, <hi>(or thou that haſt known the yoke of Chriſt and caſt it off)</hi> wouldeſt thou in thy folly limit the Holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the beginning, Carrying on and Compleating of his <hi>Creating anew</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus, the fallen degenerated and dead Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam</hi> who have believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his divine Spirit and Light, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in waits upon him in it, <hi>he will not be Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by thee,</hi> but will rebuke and Judge thee for thy preſumptuous attempt: behold the beautiful Creation, the works of God in Heaven and Earth, and the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> thereof, and <hi>theſe will Teach thee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> it is true what the Apoſtle hath writ, <hi>The wrath of God is revealed from Heaven againſt all unrighteouſneſs and ungodlineſs of men, becauſe that which may be known of God, is manifeſt in them; for God hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it unto them, for the <hi>Inviſible things of</hi> the Creation are clearly ſoon, by the things that are made, even his Eternal power and Godhead, ſo that they are <hi>with out excuſe</hi>
                  </hi> Rom. 1. 18, 19, 20, ſee the 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, to the end of the Chapter.</p>
               <p>Obſerve here, Gods Creation, Heaven and Earth, and the things therein <hi>are as a book,</hi> wherein man and woman may read the wonderful works of God, and the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65439:41"/> 
                  <hi>Glorious Order and Beauty</hi> of them, all People being enlightened by Chriſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine word, by whom God the Father made them all, they believing in the Light of him, in it they may ſee his wonderful po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and wiſdom in the bringing forth, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding and beautiful <hi>Order</hi> thereof, God having enlightened all by his Word and Spirit, which are one, <hi>Calls all the Ends of the Earth to Look unto him;</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Look unto me O all ye ends of the Earth and be ye ſaved; for I am God, and there is None Elſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mighty God and a Saviour:</hi> they who believe in his Light, and therein wait, they come therein to ſee and have Unity with his glorious works in Heaven and in Earth, and in their own Hearts and Souls, and therein come to be made ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of his bounty and kindneſs unto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in the Creating of them, and ſetting them in their <hi>Beautiful Order,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding them in the ſame, and in the deep ſence of theſe things, Mans Heart becomes tender, broken, and humble within him, and in this tender ſubjected humble frame of heart and mind, he returns the <hi>Praiſe, Honour, Glory, Dominion,</hi> and <hi>Thanks</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, the great God and Creator, of all things, who is worthy <hi>of Glory, Honour, Obedience</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> over all Heaven and Earth, now and forever more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:65439:42"/>
               <head>Something more particularly concerning the Order of Chriſt in his Church.</head>
               <p>THE Apoſtle writing to the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> writes thus, <hi>viz. ye are the body of Chriſt, and Members in particular: and God hath ſet <hi>ſome</hi> in the Church;</hi> firſt, <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>Prophets;</hi> thirdly, <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Are all Apoſtles? are all Prophets? are all Teachers?</hi> &amp;c. ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 27, 28, 29. Again, he writes to the Church at <hi>Epheſus</hi> thus, <hi>viz. And he gave <hi>ſome</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and <hi>ſome</hi> Prophets, and <hi>ſome</hi> Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and <hi>ſome</hi> Paſtors and Teachers, for the <hi>perfecting</hi> of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the Edifying of the body of Chriſt, till <hi>we all</hi> come in the Unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a <hi>perfect man,</hi> unto the Meaſure of the <hi>ſtature</hi> of the fulneſs of Chriſt,</hi> Epheſs. 4. 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>Obſerve here, the Apoſtle ſhews the <hi>order</hi> particularly of the ſeveral gifts of God to the ſeveral Members of his Church, which he gave them by the one Spirit, in which gifts the <hi>ſeveral</hi> Members were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſerve him, and <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch other,</hi> and as they <hi>all</hi> kept in their proper Gifts, they
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65439:42"/> did <hi>therein</hi> ſerve him and each other, and the <hi>weakeſt</hi> Members of the Church alſo, for whoſe ſervice they received their Gifts, (The weak had and have the moſt need of the help and ſervice of theſe gifts) and as they all kept in the Exerciſe of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral gifts <hi>in the motion, leading and guidance of Gods holy Spirit, the root and fountain of them all,</hi> they had all Unity therein one with another, although their gifts did <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,</hi> both in the manner of their working, and in the <hi>meaſure</hi> or <hi>greatneſs</hi> of them, ſo that there was an Harmony and Unity amongſt them, though they were many Members, yet were but one body, all in Subjection unto Chriſt the <hi>one</hi> head.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Obſerve the Apoſtles queſtion, <hi>are all Apoſtles? are all Prophets? are all Teachers?</hi> &amp;c. He doth not ſay, <hi>they are;</hi> the contrary is manifeſt; neither are all the Members in the Church of Chriſt in this Age called, appointed, or ordained (<hi>In their preſant State</hi>) to be Prophets, Apoſtles, or Teachers; for theſe are peculiar or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per gifts, given by the Lord God, as, and when, he pleaſeth, according to the Counſel of his own will.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Obſerve, that by what I have ſaid in this matter, I <hi>only</hi> intend all the Members of the Church of Chriſt in their preſent State, are <hi>not</hi> ſent forth publickly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65439:43"/> with a meſſage of Salvation to Preach to the Nations, <hi>nor to</hi> Propheſie or Preach pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly in words the Doctrine of the Truth or Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>nor</hi> are they all appointed of God to Propheſie and foretel things to come, <hi>nor</hi> are they all made Teachers in a publick Miniſtry in Doctrine, or Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; for theſe are peculiar or proper gifts, given according to the Heavenly will and Counſell of God (in his own time and ſeaſon) as I ſaid before.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Obſerve that though all the Members of the Body of Chriſt, have not all or <hi>ſome</hi> of the aforeſaid places in the body, yet <hi>ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry</hi> Member hath a <hi>place</hi> in the body, <hi>and it is a precious and bleſſed thing,</hi> for every Member to know its place, and <hi>keep in it,</hi> in its proper ſervice, whereto its cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God; but when any Member goes out of the Counſel of God, and <hi>looks</hi> at anothers <hi>gift,</hi> and <hi>goes out of his own</hi> proper place from his gift and ſervice in the body, ſtriving in a wrong mind or zeal after others gifts; <hi>Immitating</hi> them in words, <hi>voice, or ſound,</hi> or other <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Motion</hi> or <hi>Action</hi> of the <hi>Creature,</hi> or through a <hi>zeal without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> or by any other means whatſoever, then ſuch a Member <hi>hurts it ſelf,</hi> and grieves or offends the other more diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Members of the body, <hi>who ſees and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65439:43"/> feels</hi> the out-going of the ſaid Member.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Obſerve, it is the place and duty of the diſcerning Members of the body, who ſee ſuch out-goings, tenderly in the Love and wiſdom of God, to ſpeak to ſuch, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to bring them to a ſence of their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going, and to reſtore them into their place again (if poſſible) and to watch over them in Love, for their preſervation in it.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Obſerve, it is the duty of ſuch who have been miſtaken, and gone out of their place, as aforeſaid, to hear and receive Counſell of thoſe who freely tender it to them, in the Love of God, ſeveral ſuch in our day, have had Counſell ſo given to them, who have received it in the ſame Love, which have tended greatly to their profit, even to their ſettlement and Eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment with God, and Unity with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, praiſed be the Lord God for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Obſerve, that ſome who have had a place in the Church of Chriſt, through want of watchfulneſs in the holy fear of God, have been <hi>drawn out of it,</hi> by the ſubtill Adverſary of their Souls; and when ſome of the Members of the body, (who kept their habitation in the Light, in which they have <hi>a right</hi> ſence, ſight, ſavour and <hi>diſcerning of Spirits, words and Actions</hi>) have ſpoken to them, in the Wiſdom and Love of God, in <hi>Order to have Reſtored
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:65439:44"/> them,</hi> into their places, that they might therein have been preſerved in Unity with God and his People, they have <hi>not</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Love, <hi>that which in Love was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to them, for</hi> the good End aforeſaid; but on the <hi>Contrary</hi> have rejected the ſame, and have let up <hi>prejudice, hard thoughts and evil will againſt their friends,</hi> who ſought their good, and ſo theſe <hi>evils</hi> given way to <hi>by them, have eaten out the Love, gantineſs tenderneſs, Meakneſs, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that once in ſome Meaſure appeared in them, and a raging ſcornful, bitter, reviling Spirit, hath entered ſome,</hi> as alſo from the ſame root, <hi>faigned Humiliy,</hi> faigned words and <hi>flattery</hi> hath appeared in <hi>ſome,</hi> theſe latter mentioned fruits proceeding from the <hi>Evil root, is more Dangerous</hi> to deceive than the <hi>former,</hi> therefore all you who Love your own Souls, be warned to fly from the Spirit of diſſimulation and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, as alſo from the rude, railing, boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous, quarelſome, perverſe, Crooked, ſelf-revengful and ſcornful, Stubborne, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willful, and ſelf-Exalting Spirit.</p>
               <p>Eightly, Obſerve, that the ſame God, who by his Spirit, and in his own Order ſet ſome in the Church; Firſt, Apoſtles. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Prophets. Thirdly, Teachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the ſame Spirit, he gives proper or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar gifts to ſome, that are not Apoſtles,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65439:44"/> Prophets, or publick Teachers, according to the aforeſaid difinition of them, <hi>viz.</hi> he ſets ſome in the Church, helpers in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which laſt mentioned Members are of great ſervice in their places, in the body of Chriſt, they being kept by him in true Humility.</p>
               <p>[<hi>O friends, all keep low in your Minds, let nothing be done amongſt you in highmindedneſs or vain glory, for that God Accepts not; but the Meek he Guides in Judgment, but the Proud are an abomination to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is the Teſtamony of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to you,</hi> viz. <hi>The more Perſons grow in Chriſt, the Root, Foundation, and Head of his Church, the more Meek, Humble, and Patient they grow.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Ninthly, Obſerve, that though all the Members of the body have not <hi>all</hi> or <hi>any</hi> of the before mentioned ſervices in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet have they <hi>all</hi> a place in the Body, as I ſaid before, and they are <hi>bleſſed</hi> who know their place <hi>and keep in it,</hi> though it be the place of <hi>one</hi> of the leaſt of the Members of the Body; for that is to be deſired, which the good man made choyce of in his days, <hi>who ſaid, <hi>I had rather be a door-keeper in the houſe of the Lord, than to dwell in the Tents of wickedneſs, for the Lord God is a Sun and a Shield, the Lord will give grace, no good thing will he withhold, from them that walk uprightly,</hi>
                  </hi> Pſalm 84. 10, 11.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:65439:45"/>
               <p>Tenthly, Obſerve, that as every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber hath a place in the Body, ſo it hath <hi>a ſervice therein,</hi> though not the place of an Apoſtle, or Propher, or helper in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yet all they who are properly and truly of the body, <hi>do Preach, witneſs and teſtitie of God and Chriſt, his Kingdom and Glory,</hi> (and againſt the Kingdom of Satan, Sin, Wickedneſs, and the vain Glory and Luſts that are in the World,) <hi>In their Chriſtian Lives and Converſations;</hi> and every Nember that abides in its place and ſervice, in the fear of the Lord, and true Humility, hath Peace and Comfort with the Lord, and Unity with all their fellow-Members, who keep in their places and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices; and all who keep their places and ſervices, as aforeſaid, therein, are in a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paredneſs</hi> for whatſoever the Lord God pleaſeth to call them <hi>further unto,</hi> and when any is called to further or <hi>other</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, than what God hath already called them unto, their Peace with God and Unity with his People, will be continued in their <hi>obedience</hi> to God that calls them.</p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle writeth thus of Chriſt, <hi>viz. he that deſcended is the ſame alſo that aſcended up far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things, and he gave ſome Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:65439:45"/> of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the Edifying of the body of Chriſt, till we all come in the Unity of the faith and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the Stature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, that we henceforth be no more Children, toſſed to and fro, and Carried about with every wind of Doctrine by the ſlight of men and <hi>cunning Craftyneſs, whereby they lye in waite to deceive,</hi> but ſpeaking the Truth in Love, may grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Chriſt, from whom the whole body <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ly Joyned together and compacted,</hi> by that which every <hi>Joynt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth</hi> according to the Effectual working <hi>in the meaſure of every part,</hi> maketh Increaſe of the body unto the Edifying of it ſelf <hi>in Love,</hi>
                  </hi> Epheſs. 4. 10, 11. to the 17.</p>
               <p>Firſt Obſerve, that the gifts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Prophets, Teachers, Evangeliſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were not given <hi>only</hi> to convince People of the Truth and way of Righteouſneſs, <hi>but alſo</hi> to build them up in it gradually from ſtrength to ſtrength, to <hi>a R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe Age</hi> in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly Obſerve, that thoſe who were turned to the Light and Spirit of Truth <hi>by thoſe</hi> whom God ſent to turn them to it, could not in the Light and Spirit <hi>gainſay</hi> or <hi>oppoſe</hi> them who therein Laboured in their writing and ſpeaking to them to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:65439:46"/> build them up in it; from ſtrength to ſtrength, for the Light is <hi>not Contradictory to it ſelf in the Preacher or the Nearer, or in any of the Children of it,</hi> for that which the Light or Spirit of Truth <hi>ſpeaks</hi> or <hi>dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates</hi> to <hi>write in one</hi> of <hi>its Children</hi> it doth <hi>nor reject, oppoſe or gainſay in any other of its Children;</hi> for if it could do ſo, <hi>then</hi> ſhould it be the Author of Confuſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s</hi> Children, which is moſt falſe and blaſphemous to ſay; for God by this Spirit and Light is <hi>not</hi> the Author of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, but of good, profitable, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable <hi>order</hi> and <hi>peace in all</hi> the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the <hi>Saints.</hi> The Apoſtle in this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light ſaw, and by Experience knew that which he writ concerning it, <hi>viz. God is Light, in him is no Darkneſs at all, if we ſay we have fellowſhip with him, and walk in Darkneſs <hi>we lie,</hi> and do not the Truth; <hi>but</hi> if we walk in the Light, as he is in the Light, <hi>then</hi> have we <hi>fellowſhip</hi> one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his ſon Cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 John 1. 5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Obſerve, that they who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Light of Chriſt within, whether they be <hi>old</hi> or <hi>young</hi> profeſſors of it, <hi>that gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, oppoſe, reject, ſlight and contemn that which the Light or Spirit of Truth hath ſpoken and dictated to write</hi> in its ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Children for the Profit, Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:65439:46"/> Confirmation, Eſtabliſhment, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Body, (which Thouſands being Children of the Light, have gladly received, and finds the great comfort and profit of) Theſe are <hi>not</hi> the <hi>Lights</hi> Children, theſe do <hi>not</hi> walk in it, though they talk of it, and though ſome of them may be full of ſelf-confidence, that they walk in it, and that they are diſcerning Perſons, Wiſe, Strong, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet this is <hi>their great miſtake,</hi> herein they ſhew their ſpiritual <hi>darkneſs,</hi> blindneſs, nakedneſs, miſerableneſs, <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dician</hi> like.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Again Obſerve, That the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles who had turned the people to the Light and Spirit of Truth within, who were thereby gathered into Congregations or Churches, <hi>did</hi> afterward write the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Epiſtles to the ſeveral Churches, and therein gave to them <hi>Commands,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Inſtructions, Exhortations, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, and <hi>ſometimes</hi> ſharp <hi>Reproofs,</hi> and <hi>Rebukes,</hi> as the Lord by his Light and Spirit moved in them, according to the ſeveral States and Conditions of thoſe they writ to; the Apoſtle Exhorts <hi>Timothy,</hi> viz. <hi>them that ſin, rebuke before <hi>all,</hi> that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo may fear,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 20. Again, <hi>Reprove, Rebuke, Exhort with all long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi> and Doctrine, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. Again,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:65439:47"/> he writ to <hi>Titus,</hi> viz. <hi>Theſe things ſpeak, and exhort, <hi>and rebuke,</hi> with all Authority, let no man diſpiſe thee,</hi> Titus 2. 15. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Wherefore <hi>rebuke them ſharply,</hi> that they may be <hi>ſound</hi> in the Faith,</hi> it is render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the <hi>Greek,</hi> in the Margent, <hi>Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,</hi> touching to the quick, <hi>Titus</hi> 1. 13. Here take notice, that Reproofs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes are commanded of the Lord, and <hi>profitable</hi> in their ſeaſon, though it <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times</hi> comes to paſs, that thoſe who are ſeaſonably reprooved and rebuked, <hi>do not</hi> ſeaſonably and rightly receive the ſame, but turns againſt it, in Self-juſtification, and into <hi>Enmity</hi> againſt thoſe, who in the Councel of God, give it unto them <hi>for their good,</hi> in <hi>ſome</hi> ſuch is that Proverb ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, <hi>Reprove a fool, and he will hate thee; but a wiſe man, and he will love thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, Obſerve, <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were Overſeers, made ſo by the Holy Ghoſt, Spirit and Light, therein to watch over the Saints for their good, to Miniſter to them from time to time, whether by <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> what was needful and profitable for them; we do not read in the Scripture of Truth, nor believe that theſe two Overſeers did reject <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, written to them, or call them <hi>Man's</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:65439:47"/> 
                  <hi>Man's</hi> Decrees, Preſcriptions, or put any ſuch contemptable <hi>names</hi> upon them; but on the <hi>contrary,</hi> we believe they received them in Love, and obeyed the good Counſel, <hi>Charge</hi> and Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therein given them; we do not read, nor believe, that theſe two Miniſters of Chriſt did <hi>plead</hi> their Place and Office in the Body and Church of Chriſt, to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude</hi> and Reject <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles to them, which he gave forth in the Light and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>we do not</hi> read, <hi>nor</hi> believe, that they ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi> we <hi>deny thy Forms, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Preſcriptions,</hi> &amp;c. we are Miniſters of the Goſpel as well as thee; thy Epiſtles are of no uſe or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to us, why doſt thou ſeek to impoſe them upon us? the Holy Ghoſt, and Light within, by which we are made Overſeers, is ſufficient for us, away with thy Orders. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writ thus to <hi>Timothy,</hi> viz. <hi>Theſe things write I unto thee, being to come to thee ſhortly, but if I carry long, that thou mayeſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelf in the Houſe of God, which is the Church of the Living God, the Pillar and Ground of Truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 14, 15.</p>
               <p>Behold here <hi>Paul</hi> in this Epiſtle <hi>Inſtructs <hi>Timothy,</hi>
                  </hi> (who was an Overſeer in the Church) <hi>how to</hi> behave himſelf <hi>in it;</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:65439:48"/> we do not read, nor believe, that this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeer in the Church did Reject <hi>Paul's</hi> Inſtruction <hi>herein;</hi> or that he pleaded the Sufficiency of the Light within, <hi>in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to <hi>Paul's</hi> Advice and Inſtruction, but we do believe that he ſaw <hi>in the Light,</hi> the Inſtruction given to be good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for him, and therefore gladly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now if theſe Overſeers in the Holy Ghoſt could ſee a Service to them in <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, <hi>which certainly they did,</hi> then there <hi>certainly was</hi> a Service in his other Epiſtles to the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> who in the Light and Holy Ghoſt, taught the Elders by his Epiſtles to them; he alſo taught the Younger by his other Epiſtles, though both of them knew and obeyed the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; in it they ſaw the good uſe, profit and comfort of them, and therefore did <hi>not</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt them, <hi>but</hi> chearfully received them, and obeyed the Councel of the Lord therein given.</note> or <hi>young Schollars,</hi> weak in the Faith, feeble <hi>minded,</hi> &amp;c. Upon all which, Obſerve, That <hi>neither</hi> theſe ſtrong <hi>men,</hi> Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, <hi>nor</hi> the <hi>younger, who walked in the Light of Chriſt, did plead their</hi> being
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65439:48"/> taught by the Light of Chriſt, or Holy Ghoſt within, <hi>in oppoſition to their being Taught, Exhorted, and Inſtructed, by the Inſtrumental helps of thoſe Epiſtles</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> and other of the Apoſtles writ to them as they were moved by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. I do Adviſe and Exhort thoſe profeſſors of the Light within, who are <hi>offended</hi> at ſome profitable and wholſome Epiſtles, given forth by ſome of the moſt ancient and faithful of the Children of Light in this Age, (concerning good <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> in the Church of Chriſt,) to read the two Epiſtles to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and that to <hi>Titus,</hi> and <hi>Peter's</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to the Elders (or Overſeers) to <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed</hi> the Flock of God, <hi>over</hi> which the Holy Ghoſt had made them Overſeers, which take as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Elders which are among you I Exhort, who am alſo an Elder and a Witneſs of the ſufferings of Chriſt, and alſo partaker of the Glory that ſhall be revealed; feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy Lucre, but of a ready mind, neither as being Lords over God's Heritage, but being <hi>Examples to the Flock,</hi> and when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away; likewiſe ye
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:65439:49"/> Younger <hi>ſubm't</hi> your ſelves unto the <hi>Elder,</hi> yea all of you be ſubject one to another, and be cloathed with Humility; for God reſiſteth the Proud, and giveth grace to the Humble; humble your ſelves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may Exalt you in due time, caſting all your care upon him, for he careth for you. Be ſober, be <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>;</hi>
                  </hi> (or <hi>watchful,) <hi>becauſe your Adverſary the</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, <hi>walketh about, ſeeking whom he may devour. Whom reſiſt</hi> ſtedfaſt in the Faith, <hi>knowing that the ſame afflictions are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in your Brethren that are in the World. But the God of all Grace, who hath called us into his Eternal Glory by Chriſt Jeſus, after that ye have ſuffered a while, make you</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſtabtiſh, ſtrengthen ſettle <hi>you. To him be Glory, for ever and ever. Amen.</hi>
                  </hi> 1 Pet. 5. 1, to the 12. Again, hear his ſweet Exhortation, <hi>Finally, be all of <hi>one mind,</hi> having compaſſion one of another; <hi>love as Brethren,</hi> be pitiful, be courteous: <hi>not rendering evil for evil, or railing for railing,</hi>—For he that will love life, and <hi>ſee good oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> let him <hi>refrain his tongue</hi> from evil, and his lips that they ſpeak no <hi>Guile.</hi> Let <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m</hi> eſchew, or fly from Evil, and <hi>do good,</hi> let him ſeek <hi>peace,</hi> and enſue it, (<hi>that is follow it</hi>) for the Eyes of the Lord are over the Righteous, and his Ears
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65439:49"/> are <hi>open</hi> unto their <hi>prayers,</hi> but the <hi>face</hi> of the Lord is <hi>againſt them</hi> that do evil.</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 8, to the 13.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Obſerve here <hi>Peter</hi> that faithful Apoſtle of Chriſt, in his general Epiſtle, Exhorts the Elders who were among the Churches, to feed the Flock; <hi>we do not read nor believe,</hi> that thoſe Elders took it <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of <hi>Peter</hi> that he ſo Exhorted them; we neither read, <hi>nor</hi> believe, that they <hi>pleaded</hi> their Gifts and Places in the Church, or <hi>their</hi> being led by the Light, or Holy Ghoſt, within, <hi>in oppoſition</hi> to his Chriſtian Councel and Exhortation in the ſame Holy Ghoſt, Light and Spirit, given them by his Epiſtle; but on the <hi>contrary,</hi> we believe that in the Light they ſaw the ſame to be good and profitable for them, and therein gladly received and obeyed the ſame, and alſo we believe, that the <hi>younger</hi> who walked in the Light, <hi>did ſubmit</hi> themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto the Elder <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> and that they who obeyed the Light were thereby led into Humility and Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and therein to ſubmit themſelves one to another, in the Fear and Councel of God.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> writ thus, viz. <hi>And when this Epiſtle is <hi>read</hi> amongſt you, cauſe that it be read in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65439:50"/> the Church of the</hi> Laodicians—<hi>And ſay to</hi> Archippus, <hi>take heed to the Miniſtry, which thou haſt received in the Lord, that thou ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerve two things in the foregoing words, firſt, that he did <hi>not</hi> only charge or enjoin them to <hi>read</hi> his Epiſtle amongſt them, but alſo to take care, that it was <hi>read</hi> to the <hi>Laodicearis.</hi> Secondly, He writ to them, to ſay to <hi>Archippus,</hi> take heed to thy Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We do not read, or believe, that the believing <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> did <hi>reject</hi> this Epiſtle of <hi>Paul's,</hi> or <hi>neglect</hi> their duty in <hi>reading</hi> it, and cauſing it to be read according to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, or that they <hi>pleaded</hi> the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the Light within, <hi>in oppoſition to his E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtles,</hi> and councel therein given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them, but that in the light, they had Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with it, and therefore gladly received it, and had benefit by it, neither do we read or believe, that <hi>Archippus</hi> was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with what <hi>Paul</hi> writ concerning him, <hi>nor</hi> that he pleaded his Gift and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and the Light within, againſt <hi>Paul's</hi> councel, in the matter relating to him, but that he had Unity therewith in the Light.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Paul</hi> writ to <hi>Timothy</hi> thus, viz. <hi>I <hi>charge</hi> thee before God, and our Lord Jeſus
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:65439:50"/> Chriſt, who ſhall <hi>Judg the quick and dead,</hi> at his appearing, and his Kingdom, Preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebuke; exhort, with all long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and doctrine, for the time will come, when <hi>they will not endure ſound Doctrine,</hi> but after their own <hi>Luſts,</hi> ſhall they <hi>heap</hi> to themſelves Teachers, having <hi>itching Ears,</hi> and they ſhall <hi>turn away their Ears</hi> from the Truth, and ſhall be <hi>turned</hi> unto <hi>Favles;</hi> but watch thou in all things, endure afflistions, do the work of an Evangaliſt, make full proof of thy Miniſtry,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 1, to the <hi>6th.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerve, Have not ſome profeſſors of the Light within now, itching Ears which cannot endure ſound Doctrine, and are not ſome ſuch for ſetting up Teachers, which with unſound Doctrine, for a wrong Liberty, againſt the Croſs of Chriſt, can, or do pleaſe their itching Ears.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>we ſpeak not as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing men, but God, who tryeth our hearts, 1 Theſs.</hi> 2. 4. Again, to the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians</hi> he writ, ſaying, <hi>For do I now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men, or God? or do I ſeek to pleaſe men? for if I yet pleaſed men, I ſhould not be the Servant of Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 1. 9, 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> charges <hi>Timothy</hi> before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to Preach the Word,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:65439:51"/> to Reprove, Rebuke, Exhort, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to make full proof of his Miniſtry; we do <hi>not</hi> read, nor believe, that <hi>Timothy</hi> was offended with this Fatherly Charge, or Exhortation in this matter; or that he <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt, or oppoſed</hi> this Charge, or <hi>pleaded</hi> his Gift or Place in the Church, or the Holy Ghoſt, or Light of Chriſt, <hi>in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> to it, or that he ſaid, he had no need of it, or that it was of <hi>no</hi> uſe or ſervice to him, but on the contrary, we believe that this faithful young man, whom <hi>Paul</hi> had begotten to God, (through the power of the Goſpel) did gladly receive; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>prove,</hi> the Charge, Exhortation and Councel of <hi>Paul</hi> the Aged, his Elder in the Truth.</p>
               <p>Again, Chriſt <hi>after he was riſen from the dead,</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Simon Peter, Loveſt thou me, more then theſe? he ſaith unto him, Yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I love thee. He ſaith unto him, Feed my Lambs. He ſaith to him again the Second time,</hi> Simon <hi>Son of</hi> Jonas, <hi>Loveſt thou me? he ſaith unto him, Yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I love thee. He ſaith unto him, Feed my Sheep. He ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the Third time,</hi> Simon <hi>Son of</hi> Jonas? <hi>Loveſt thou me?—And he ſaid unto him, Lord, thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:65439:51"/> that I love thee. He ſaith unto him, Feed my ſheep,</hi> John 21. 15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Obſerve, How Chriſt put the Queſtion before Recited, upon <hi>Peter</hi> Three times, <hi>deſigning</hi> thereby to ſettle, and <hi>revet or faſten,</hi> the ſence and care of this great Duty, of feeding his Lambs and Sheep, <hi>upon him,</hi> which command of his Maſters he faithfully performed, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the other Elders to perform <hi>their duty</hi> in this matter, of ſo great <hi>weight,</hi> as is ſhewed before. The like did <hi>Paul, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and the reſt of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Apoſtles and Elders.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Obſerve, How theſe Holy men of God did <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed</hi> the Lambs and Sheep of Chriſt, in Preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdom of God unto them, which they Preached in the Power of the Holy Ghoſt, ſent down from Heaven.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Obſerve, We do not read in the Scriptures of Truth, <hi>nor believe,</hi> that theſe Lambs or Sheep of Chriſt, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Teachings of the Light within, <hi>in oppoſition <hi>to its teaching of them through theſe Apoſtles and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Note, <hi>The Light of Chriſt within, is not contradictory to it ſelf, in any of the Children of it, nor in any others.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:65439:52"/> 
                  <hi>and empower'd from Heaven to <hi>feed</hi> them, they did not plead</hi> the ſufficiency of the Light of Chriſt within <hi>themſelves,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt its Teaching them in theſe Apoſtles, for as I ſaid before, the Light <hi>in him,</hi> that is Taught, <hi>cannot oppoſe</hi> the Light <hi>in him</hi> that Teacheth, <hi>neither is</hi> the Light <hi>contradictory</hi> to it <hi>ſelf in any of its Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> but walking in it therein is their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip one with another.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Obſerve, Chriſt calls thoſe that were to be fed, Lambs and Sheep, <hi>which ſignifies,</hi> they were not of a Woolf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh or Dogiſh <hi>Nature</hi> or Spirit, that is, Bitter, Cruel and Ravenous, but as Lambs and Sheep, they were <hi>meek and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et;</hi> Oh that all the profeſſors of the Light of Chriſt within, <hi>were</hi> ſuch, then would not <hi>ſome</hi> of them cauſe ſuch diſhonour to the Lord as they do, neither would they cauſe ſuch grief and travel to the faithful Labourers in the Goſpel of Peace, as they do.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Paul</hi> writ to <hi>Timothy</hi> thus, <hi>viz. take heed unto thy ſelf and unto thy Doctrine, continue in them, for in doeing this thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelf and them that hear thee,</hi> 1 Tim. 16. <hi>read the</hi> Chapter throughout.</p>
               <p>The ſame Apoſtle to the Church of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> writ thus, <hi>viz. Now we
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65439:52"/> 
                     <hi>Command</hi> you Bretheren in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every Brother that walketh <hi>diſorderly,</hi>
                  </hi> and not after the <hi>Tradition</hi> which ye received of <hi>us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi> 2 Theſſ. 3. 6.</p>
               <p>Again, he writ thus, <hi>viz. We Exhort you Brethren, warn them that are <hi>unruly</hi> (or diſorderly) Comfort the feeble minded, ſupport the weak, be patient towards all men, I <hi>Charge</hi> you by the Lord that this Epiſtle be read unto all the holy Brethren, the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you all</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; 1 Theſſ. 5. 14, to the end, And to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> again, he ſaith in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Epiſtle, <hi>viz. for we hear that there are ſome among you which walk <hi>Diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> working not at all, but are buſi-bodies, Now them that are <hi>ſuch we Command and Exhort by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that with Quietneſs they Work and Eat their own Bread,</hi> but ye Brethren be not Weary in well Doing; <hi>and if any man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not our word</hi>
                  </hi> by this Epiſtle, <hi>Note that <hi>man and have</hi> no <hi>Company with him that he may be aſhamed; yet count him not as an Enemy, but</hi> Admoniſh <hi>him as a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Now the Lord of Peace, himſelf give you peace always, by all meanes, the Lord be with you all,</hi>
                  </hi> 2 Theſſ. 3. 11, to the End.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:65439:53"/>
               <p>Obſerve here if any of theſe to whom <hi>Paul</hi> wrote, and to whom he Charges his Epiſtle to be Read, ſhould have called his Epiſtle his rotten Orders, his Edicts, mans Preſcriptions, Impoſition upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Innovations or Apoſtacy, and ſuch like; could he or any other of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Chriſt Jeſus have owned ſuch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be Brethren in the Unity and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Goſpel, or could he or they have owned ſuch words and ſayings a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe to be the fruit of the Divine Light and Spirit of Chriſt within, <hi>as applyed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the faithful in Chriſt Jeſus</hi>) Oh Certainly Nay.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:65439:53"/>
               <head>Concerning the form of the Apoſtles Doctrine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Apoſtle writ thus to the beleiving Obedient Romans, <hi>viz. But God be thanked ye have obeyed from the heart that forme of Doctrine, which was delivered unto you; <hi>Note here,</hi>
                  </hi> that it was the Apoſtles <hi>Joy</hi> that they obeyed that forme of ſound Doctrine which was delivered to <hi>them,</hi> for this he thanked God, he was <hi>not</hi> of the mind of ſome who, formerly as alſo ſome of late were and have been, who under the profeſſion of the Light within, and its teaching, have ſpoken, preached, or written, that the way of Gods People muſt, or ought, or may be as the way of a <hi>Serpent</hi> upon a rock, or as the way of a <hi>ſhip</hi> on the Sea, which leaves <hi>noe form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or Impreſſion behind them, this <hi>neither was nor</hi> is the way of Gods People <hi>either</hi> under <hi>his Law</hi> or <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but the way of an Adulterous woman as it is written, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 19, 20. And further obſerve, Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs of the true Chriſtians in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Doctrine, <hi>viz. And they Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Stedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and fellowſhip,</hi> Acts 2. 42. <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God, and the holy Prophets, Chriſt and his holy Apoſtles left good forms of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65439:54"/> Doctrine <hi>in ſound words</hi> behind them, under the <hi>ſeveral Diſpenſations</hi> of God, in which they Lived, which is <hi>contained</hi> in the holy Scriptures of Truth, which form of ſound Words and Doctrines are both Comfortable and Profitable to the man of God in this day, and will be to the People of God in Ages to come, and it is groſs Darkneſs and Spiritual <hi>Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> that is come upon them who have ſpoken, Preach or believe that the way of Gods People muſt be as the way of a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> on a Rock, or as the way of a <hi>Ship</hi> in the <hi>Sea,</hi> which leaves <hi>now</hi> Impreſion or <hi>form</hi> behind it, It were to be <hi>deſired</hi> ineed that the <hi>Devil and Wicked men</hi> might leave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> form or Impreſſion of their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs behind them, ſeeing their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>formes</hi> others are Apt to follow them in to their own hurt and danger of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ruine, God Almighty in his own Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time will root out and deſtroy all the wicked formes of Imaging, ſpeaking, and Acting wickedly, which the Devil, in whom there is no Truth, hath led men and women into, by which he hath led them to deſtroy themſelves and each other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:65439:54"/>
               <head>Concerning the Commands of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h they gave not of Themſelves, or by their own Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but by and in His Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Strength, and Authority; for they were His Ambaſſadors, over them He Reigned, in them He ſpake, and gave Commands; who is Head of His Church, and One in the Male and Female.</head>
               <p>THe Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> writing to the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> concerning the Things that were <hi>Not in good Order</hi> amongſt them, writing of many things in his <hi>Firſt Epiſtle</hi> to them, in the 14 Chapter, concludes thus: <hi>If any Man thinks himſelf to be a Prophet, or Spiritual, let him know, that the things <hi>That I write</hi> unto you, are the <hi>Commandments of the Lord.</hi> Let all Things be done Honeſtly, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and in Order;</hi>
                  </hi> verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. and 40.</p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle writing to the Church of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> writ thus, viz. <hi>We beſeech you, Brethren, and exhort you by the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that as you have <hi>Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:65439:55"/> of us, how you ought to walk, and pleaſe God;</hi> ſo you would abound more and more; for you know what <hi>Commandments we gave you by the Lord Jeſus:</hi> for this is the Will of God, even your Sanctification—That every one of you ſhould know how to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs his Veſſel in Sanctification and Honour, <hi>Not <hi>in the Lusts of Concupiſcence, as other</hi>
                  </hi> Gentiles, <hi>that know not God; that <hi>No Man go beyond, and defraud his Brother in any matter;</hi> becauſe the Lord is the Avenger of ſuch, as we have forewarned and teſtified: for God hath not called us unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, but unto Holineſs; <hi>He therefore who deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, deſpiſeth not Man, but God,</hi> who hath alſo given unto us his holy Spirit;</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 1. to the <hi>9th.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writes thus to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> viz. <hi>We have Confidence in the Lord, touching</hi> you, <hi>that you both do, and will do the things which we <hi>Command</hi>
                  </hi> you. <hi>Now we Command you Brethren, that you withdraw your ſelves from every Brother, that walketh <hi>Diſorderly;</hi> and not after the <hi>Traditions,</hi> or Ordinances, which ye received of us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Therefore Brethren, ſtand faſt, and hold the Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which ye have been taught, whether <hi>By Word,</hi> or our <hi>Epiſtles,</hi>
                  </hi> 2 Theſſ. 2. 15. See 2 Theſſ. 3. 4, 5.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:65439:55"/>
               <p>Again, he writes to <hi>Timothy</hi> thus; <hi>Theſe things <hi>Command,</hi> and teach; let no Man diſpiſe thy Youth, but be thou an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> of the Believers in Word, in <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> in <hi>Charity,</hi> in <hi>Spirit,</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> in <hi>Purity:</hi>
                  </hi> See 1 Tim. 4. 11, 12. read the Chapter through.</p>
               <p>Again, hear what the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith unto the Saints in Light, viz. <hi>This Second Epiſtle, Beloved, I now write unto you; in both which, I ſtir up your pure minds, by way of Remembrance, that ye may be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the <hi>Words,</hi> which were ſpoken before by the holy Prophets, and of the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of us,</hi> the Apostles of our Lord and Saviour; knowing this firſt, that there ſhall come in the <hi>Laſt days Scoffers,</hi> walking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own <hi>Luſts,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Again,—<hi>Ye therefore, Beloved, ſeeing ye know theſe things before, beware leſt ye alſo being led away with the <hi>Errour</hi> of the Wicked, fall from your own <hi>Stedfaſtneſs;</hi> but grow in Grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt: To Him be Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, both now and forever, Amen.</hi> 2 Peter 3. 1, 2, 3, and 17, 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reader,</hi> who ever thou art, this I ſay to thee, in the Preſence of Almighty <hi>God,</hi> the Searcher of all Hearts, before whom all things are naked and bare, who judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth righteouſly, That I do <hi>Not</hi> bring
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:65439:56"/> the Commands, Ordinances, or Doctrines given and ſpoken by the Apoſtles of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with <hi>Any Deſign to wrong, ſtrein, or wreſt them, or any of them;</hi> to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lt any Friend, Brother or Brethren, Siſter or Siſters, above or out of their Place, in which <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the one Head, hath ſet them in his Body, his <hi>Church,</hi> or in anywiſe to exalt them, or any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of them, as Lords, over <hi>Gods</hi> Peoples Faith, which our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the Author and Finiſher of; by which Faith they live to <hi>God,</hi> and pleaſe Him. But my deſign there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is to Exalt <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Head,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n them <hi>All,</hi> and over them <hi>All,</hi> who is <hi>One</hi> in the <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female:</hi> He hath given us a Command, to <hi>Learn of Him,</hi> ſaying, <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n of me, <hi>I am meek, and Low in hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, and ye ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ll find reſt to your Souls: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f him we have learned Humility, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of Mind; in this we have found abundance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Peace, Joy, Comfort,</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>Reſt</hi> to our <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ls.</hi> This to us is of much more value, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n all the Riches and Glory of this World: <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere</hi> is the Pleaſant and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Dwelling Place, here we deſire to dwell forever.</hi> The Humble <hi>God</hi> doth teach; he guides the Meek in Judgment, and cloaths them with Salvation: Eternal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lory be given to Him for the ſame. My Deſign in bringing theſe things to thy
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65439:56"/> 
                  <hi>View,</hi> is, to ſhew that the Apoſtles, who preach't the Goſpel with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven (as it's written), did in the <hi>Movings</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the ſame, give forth thoſe Commands, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and Doctrines unto the Believers, in the ſame Holy Ghoſt, Spirit, or Light; by which Light they ſaw and underſtood the Truth, Soundneſs, and Serviceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them: and by the ſame were they led; <hi>Not to Oppoſe them, and ſpeak Evil of them,</hi> but to <hi>Obey,</hi> and practiſe them. Now, thoſe that profeſs to be governed by the ſame Holy Ghoſt, Spirit, or Light within, if they poſſeſs what they profeſs therein, they will ſee, that the ſame Holy Ghoſt is, <hi>In ſome meaſure,</hi> given to ſome in our Day; and that by it, <hi>Some</hi> are made <hi>Able</hi> Miniſters, and thereby have been <hi>Moved</hi> to give out <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Commands, <hi>Not</hi> in their own Name, but in the <hi>Name</hi> of the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the chief Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, and Biſhop of our Souls: and ſuch Profeſſors of the Light, who <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſs</hi> what they <hi>Profeſs,</hi> and dilligently attend upon God in the ſame, they will herein <hi>See,</hi> and thereby be <hi>Led to Obey,</hi> and practiſe thoſe things, <hi>Not</hi> as the Precepts, Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Doctrines of Men; <hi>But</hi> as the <hi>Commands, Precepts,</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which he gives, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65439:57"/> ſpeaks by the Mouths of his Servants; which anſwers that Light of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the Conſciences of his People. And ſuch who reject them, they therein reject <hi>God,</hi> and Chriſt. Theſe things ſo Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are <hi>Not</hi> contrary to the Commands of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, recorded in the Scriptures of Truth; but <hi>Agreeable</hi> to them, in the <hi>fulfilling</hi> the precious <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> of God, ſpoken by the Mouths of his Holy Prophets; who ſaid, <hi>I will pour forth my Spirit upon all Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>When they ſhall lead you, and deliver you up, take no thought before hand what you ſhall ſpeak, neither do you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditate; but whatſoever ſhall be given you in that hour, that ſpeak ye: For it is <hi>Not you that ſpeak,</hi> but the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> Mark 31. 11.</p>
               <p>In the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, obſerve the Holy Ghoſt that ſpake to the Magiſtrates and Rulers, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted them; the ſame ſpake in them to the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and gave forth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, Precepts, Ordinances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Believers, unto whom they wrote, having a meaſure of the ſame Holy Ghoſt, were thereby given to underſtand the ſame, and thereby led to the Obedience thereof.</p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid unto the Saints, <hi>You know how we Exhorted, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and <hi>Charged</hi> every one of you (as a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:65439:57"/> Father doth his Children) that you would walk worthy <hi>Of God,</hi> who hath called you unto his Kingdom and Glory; for this Cauſe, alſo, thank we God, without ceaſing; becauſe, when ye received the Word of God, which ye heard of us, ye received it <hi>Not</hi> as the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> but as it is in Truth the <hi>Word</hi> of God, which effectually worketh alſo in you that believe;</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2. 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>Obſerve here, the Apoſtle commends the Saints for receiving the Word, or Teſtimony of <hi>God</hi> by him and others, not as the <hi>Word</hi> of Man, or Men; but as it was indeed the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which <hi>wrought Effectually in them,</hi> as he ſaith: And as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was then, ſo is it now; <hi>God</hi> having given (by his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants) his Word, his Commands, and Doctrines; he hath by his powerful, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning Spirit of Life, opened many to receive the ſame, <hi>Not</hi> as the Word, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Precepts, Decrees, Edicts, or Orders of <hi>One Man, Many Men,</hi> or <hi>Any Men;</hi> but as the <hi>Word, Commands,</hi> and <hi>Precepts,</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the Great God, and our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Glory, yea glory to the Lord God, and the Lamb, for the ſame.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Objection</hi> that ſome make concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the practice of ſome things in the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65439:58"/> Church of Chriſt, at this day, <hi>is,</hi> becauſe they were not practiſed when we were firſt turned to the <hi>Light,</hi> and came into the belief and profeſſion of it.</p>
               <p>This Objection is fully anſwered before in this Epiſtle, where the divers growths and ſtatures of Gods people are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>great Objection</hi> that is uſed by ſome at this day, is, That they <note place="margin">An Objection anſwered.</note> do <hi>not ſee</hi> thoſe things requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them, or believe them to be their duty; and becauſe they do not ſee the practice of thoſe things to be their duty, or required of them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they oppoſe (Friends) in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of them. What theſe things are, theſe <hi>Oppoſers</hi> know; and the Faithful who are <hi>oppoſed by them</hi> therein, know them alſo. They are not things which are evil or ſcandalous, or of evil ſame or report amongſt ſerious ſober perſons; we are not afraid to bring them to the Light; they are practiſed by many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in <hi>Unity,</hi> to their comfort, and tends to preſerve both young and old, ſweet and <hi>orderly</hi> in their <hi>Marriages,</hi> and in the reſt of their <hi>Converſations,</hi> and is for the Relief of the Poor, Widows, and Fatherleſs Children. Some have done
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65439:58"/> 
                  <hi>hurt</hi> in their <hi>ſelfiſh</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> ſtriving <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> theſe things; and when they have done the <hi>hurt,</hi> they would lay the blame upon the <hi>things</hi> which they ſtrive againſt: and the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> who have and do incourage thoſe <hi>things.</hi> And thus they judge unrighteouſly the Innocent, and juſtifying themſelves who are guilty.</p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle exhorted, ſaying, <hi>Brethren, whatſoever things are true, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; If there be any Vertue, and if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe things. Theſe things which you have both learned, and received, and heard, and ſeen in me, do, and the God of peace ſhall be with you,</hi> Philip. 4. 8, 9.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, that Meeting together in the Love &amp; Fear of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> to take care of <hi>his glory,</hi> in providing for the Poor, Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and Fatherleſs Children, and others who have need of help &amp; aſſiſtance among us in their bodily Weakneſs, Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Trials, and Exerciſes; <hi>is good, is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, is Juſt, is lovely, is of good report, and is worthy of praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things are done in our Meetings, both by Male and Female. Such Meetings have the <hi>vertuous</hi> Preſence of the <hi>Lord God,</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:65439:59"/> them: Such Meetings God doth gather, own, uphold, and juſtifie by his powerful preſence in the midſt of them. Again, In thoſe Meetings care is taken, that ſuch who profeſs the truth, as it is in Chriſt Jeſus, (and walk amongſt us) do proceed in their Marriages ſweetly, in good order, according to the example of holy men and women of God, in former time (and in our days) thoſe proceedings are brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though plainly touched at in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures of Truth. Again, In thoſe Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings care is taken, that thoſe whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in relation to Marriage, are not as they ought to be, that ſuch be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that they may come into a right ſenſe of the diſhonour they bring to God thereby, that they may repent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the ſame, and give glory to God therein, that they may obtain forgiveneſs at his hand; and that his People whom they have grieved by their unfaithfulneſs therein, may be comforted in ſeeing this good Work of God wrought in them. Again, In theſe Meetings care is taken, that thoſe who profeſs the Truth as it is in Chriſt Jeſus, (and walk amongſt us) do in their Converſations walk orderly, as becomes the Goſpel, that no Profeſſor thereof wrong another, or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whomſoever, in any matter or thing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:65439:59"/> whatſoever. This is endeavoured by the faithful Children of God, Children of Light, both Male and Female, in their particular and diſtinct, and alſo in their more general Meeting, as much as in them lieth. And where any profeſſing the Truth amongſt us, do or have done the contrary, care hath been and is to labour with them in the love of God, and Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Patience, which Chriſt Jeſus, the meek and lowly Lamb of God, hath taught us, to bring them into a right ſenſe of the diſhonour, they have brought to God by their evil doings; and that they might repent of, and ſenſually judge themſelves for the ſame; that ſo through unfeigned Repentance, and forſaking the ſame, they might obtain Forgiveneſs of their ſins at the hand of God: for the Lord God who is merciful, delighteth not in the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſinner, but rather that he ſhould repent, and turn from the evil of his ways, and live, and ſo come into unity with his tender People. Again, In theſe Meetings the faithful in Chriſt Jeſus do watch one over another in Love, to be helpful one to another in their Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Tryals, and Afflictions, labouring to build up each other in the holy Faith, (which works by Love, as the Apoſtle ſaith) herein they manifeſt their love one
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:65439:60"/> to another, according to Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: Their love is without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; by which they are known to be the Diſciples of Chriſt, in fulfilling the Royal Law of Love in his Divine Light, according the Scriptures of Truth.</p>
               <p>Again, in thoſe Meetings care is taken, that the Profeſſors of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Teachings of his Divine Light within, do walk in the Light which they make profeſſion of that according to Chriſts command, their Light may ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee their good works in Chriſt Jeſus, and glorifie our Father which is in Heaven; that as the Salt of the Earth, we may always keep that heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>avour which God in Chriſt hath given us, and that we may grow in it more and more, that therein we may be a good ſavour both in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh, even as the Apoſtle exhorted.</p>
               <p>All the before mentioned things are true, honeſt, juſt, good, virtuous, lovely, and of good report, worthy of praiſe. Hereby God is honoured, and his children profited, benefited, comforted, edified, and built up in unfeigned Love, Peace, and ſweet Unity, to his praiſe and glory, who is over all Heaven and Earth, worthy of Honour, Glory, Dominion, and Praiſe,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:65439:60"/> now and for ever more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerve, that which oppoſeth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orneth the faithful in Chriſt Jeſus, in theſe their ſervices and labour of love, is neither true, juſt, honeſt, lovely, virtuous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good report; neither is it worthy of praiſe, but the contrary: Therefore all you who profeſs to be led and guided by the Light of Chriſt within; you in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, I tell you, that his Light in you, will not lead any of you to oppoſe any of the good things before mentioned. And where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon profeſſing to be led by the Light of Chriſt within, do oppoſe any of the before-mentioned Meetings, or the aforeſaid good ſervices in them, it is Darkneſs, and not the Light of Chriſt, which ſo leads and perſwades them: He that was a Liar from the beginning, hath deceived ſuch. Oh that they might ſee his Snare, and come out of it! this is our ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der deſire for them for their eternal good. The Lord God, who is Light, in whom there is no Darkneſs at all, ſaid by the mouth of his holy Prophet, <hi>Wo unto them that call evil good, and good evil; that put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs! Wo unto them that are wiſe in their own eyes!</hi> Iſai. 5. 20, 21. Chriſt ſaid, <hi>If the light that is in thee be darkneſs, how great is that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:65439:61"/> darkneſs?</hi> See <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 22, 23. See <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 34, 35, 36. See <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 35.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, it is <hi>No Proof,</hi> that theſe good things are <hi>not <hi>their duty,</hi>
                  </hi> becauſe <hi>they</hi> do <hi>not</hi> ſee <hi>them</hi> to be ſo: for it is <hi>undeniable, that</hi> it is the <hi>duty</hi> of all Men &amp; Women to believe in the <hi>one</hi> Eternal God; but ſome were of old, and now are ſo <hi>blinded</hi> by the <hi>God</hi> of this world, their minds <hi>ſo</hi> darkned, and they ſo <hi>hardened</hi> in the <hi>practice and love of ſin,</hi> that they <hi>did not, nor</hi> do <hi>ſee or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> that there is a <hi>God;</hi> as it's written, <hi>The <hi>Fool</hi> hath ſaid in his <hi>heart,</hi> there is no God:</hi> And again, Chriſt ſaid to the great profeſſing Jews, High Prieſts, Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites, who were as the whited Walls, Graves, and painted Sepulchres, (but within were full of rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs, hypocriſie and deceit) <hi>Ye neither <hi>know Me, nor my Father;</hi> ye neither <hi>know the Scriptures, nor the Power of God.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, it is the <hi>duty</hi> of every man and woman to believe in the true Light of Chriſt, that lighteneth every man that cometh into the World; but it's <hi>known by lamentable Experience, that even</hi> many of the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, are <hi>far</hi> from believing <hi>in it;</hi> who on the <hi>contrary</hi> are Blaſpheming againſt it, Mocking and Scoffing at it, perſecuting and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Children of it, and oppoſing the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:65439:61"/> Teſtimony of it. Now, if theſe do ſay, We do <hi>Not ſee</hi> or believe it to be our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to believe in and obey the Light; it doth <hi>Not</hi> therefore follow, that it is not their Duty: and if they ſay, We ſee &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it is our <hi>Duty</hi> to ſpeak and write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Light, and to puniſh you who profeſs and obey it; <hi>Their</hi> ſo ſaying will <hi>Not</hi> prove that theſe their. <hi>Evil</hi> Works are their Duty to God and Chriſt, no not at all, but the <hi>Contrary.</hi> But to come cloſer to the Profeſſors of the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, hear what Chriſt and the Prophet ſaith, <hi>viz.</hi> This Peoples <hi>Heart is waxed groſs, and their Ears are dull of hearing, and their Eyes they have cloſed, leſt at any Time they ſhould ſee with their Eyes, and hear with their Ears, and ſhould underſtand with their Heart, and ſhould be converted, and I ſhould heal them.</hi> See <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 14, 15. <hi>Acts</hi> 28. 26, 27. The Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> writ thus concerning Chriſt, viz. <hi>And he became the Author of Eternal Salvation to all them that obey him, called of</hi> God <hi>an high Prieſt, after the Order of</hi> Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck, <hi>of whom we have</hi> many things to ſay, and hard to be uttered; ſeeing <hi>Ye</hi> are <hi>Dull of hearing,</hi> or as it is rendered in the Margin out of the Greek, <hi>Hath no Experience;</hi> for when for the <hi>Time</hi> ye ought to be Teachers, <hi>Ye</hi> have <hi>Need</hi> that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:65439:62"/> one teach you again, which be the firſt Principles of the Word or Oracles of God. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>Again, Chriſt ſpeaking a Parable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kingdom of God, ſaith, <hi>For unto every one that hath ſhall be given, and he ſhall have abundance; but from him that hath not, ſhall be taken away even that which he hath; and caſt ye the unprofitable Servant into utter darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Math.</hi> 25. 29, 30.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, the ſloathful Servant who had not improved his Lords Talent, was and is to be caſt into utter darkneſs, his <hi>Talent</hi> being taken from him: <hi>Such an one</hi> in Darkneſs may talk of Light, as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>Death and Deſtruction ſaith, We have heard of the fame of Wiſdom;</hi> ſuch an one may talk of the Light, who in his dark Works <hi>Denies it,</hi> and oppoſeth it, and contends againſt the Children of it, in their pure Obedience to it, and <hi>Such an one</hi> may ſay to the Children of the Light, I do not ſee that to be my Duty which you practiſe: <hi>I ſay,</hi> how ſhould he ſee who is ſhut up in utter darkneſs, whoſe wilful diſobedience has brought him to be like the deaf Adder, which ſtoppeth his Ears, which will not hear, as it's written.</p>
               <p>Again, Jeſus ſaid unto them, <hi>Yet a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while is the Light with you, walk while ye have the Light, lest Darkneſs come upon you;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:65439:62"/> for he that walketh in darkneſs knoweth not whither he goeth; while ye have the Light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Light, that you may be the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light,</hi> John 12. 35, 36.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, They who believe in the Light, as Chriſt commands, and obey it in its firſt and ſmalleſt Manifeſtations, they in that Light <hi>Cannot oppoſe</hi> what the Light brings forth <hi>In others;</hi> for though <hi>Some</hi> who are turned to the Light, and have believed in it, and in ſome meaſure obeyed it, <hi>Do not</hi> ſee ſo <hi>Much</hi> or ſo <hi>Far</hi> into the things of God, as ſome others who are more grown and Eſtabliſhed, and have received a greater Meaſure of Divine Wiſdom; yet <hi>Cannot</hi> theſe <hi>Weak</hi> or <hi>Young ones,</hi> by the motion or teaching of the Light, contradict, oppoſe, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt what the ſame Light brings forth in others of the Children of it; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if this <hi>Could be,</hi> then God (whoſe gift to Man and Woman, the Light is) would thereby be the Author of Confuſion, and not of Peace, in the Churches of the Saints, as is obſerved before in this Epiſtle; but God <hi>Is not</hi> the Author of Confuſion, but of Peace in all the Churches of the Saints, as the Apoſtle hath writ, which is obſerved before. It is true as the Prophet writ, <hi>O Lord in thy Light we ſhall ſee more Light,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Path of the Juſt is as the ſhining Light,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:65439:63"/> which ſhines more &amp; more unto the perfect day.</hi> It is certainly true, that we find it harder in this Age to perſwade ſome people, to keep and walk in the Light, than it was to turn them to it; and ſome like <hi>Balaam</hi> having been opened by it, to ſee the bleſſed end of the Righteous, do ſtill retain a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it (though they rebel againſt it) and deſire to die the death of the Righteous, as <hi>Balaam</hi> did; but refuſeth to live that Self-denying Chriſtian life, which leads to that good End. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Loe I come, and my reward is with me, to give unto every one according as his works ſhall be.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Such as every one ſows, ſuch ſhall he reap: he that ſows to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap Corruption; but he that ſows to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap Life everlaſting. If ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall die; but if ye through the ſpirit mortifie the deeds of the body (or fleſh) then ſhall ye live.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writ thus to the Children of the Light, <hi>Let us therefore as many as be perfect, be thus minded: and if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded,</hi> God <hi>ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal even this unto you. Nevertheleſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame thing. Brethren, be followers together of me, and mark them which walk ſo, as ye have us for an enſample.</hi> See <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. 15, 16, 17.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:65439:63"/>
               <p>Obſerve here, It was the Apoſtles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, that if any among the Believers in the Light, were of another mind than he was, in any thing that he in the Light practiſed, God would reveal the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them alſo, they abiding ſtedfaſt with the Light to which they were turn'd; and as <hi>he</hi> believed, ſo do <hi>we</hi> believe in this matter. 'Tis poſſible, that ſome perſons, who are turned to the Light of Chriſt within, who have believed, and in ſome meaſure obeyed the ſame, who in many <hi>things have Unity</hi> with the moſt antient grown and eſtabliſh'd of the Children of the Light, yet in ſome things, may not be ſo opened and clear in their Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, as to ſee them, and joyn in Faith in the practice of them. <hi>We believe,</hi> and therefore <hi>ſay,</hi> That if ſuch abide in the Light, faithful to what they know, God will reveal theſe things unto them. And we believe, and therefore ſay, They kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the Light, it will keep them <hi>from contending againſt or oppoſing</hi> others, in the practice of that which God has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to them, and required of them. What is not of Faith is ſin, as ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>Such</hi> therefore that are <hi>weak</hi> in the Faith, we ought <hi>not to reject,</hi> but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, though not to doubtful Diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but <hi>to hear their</hi> infirmities or weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:65439:64"/> to be good Examples to them, and to make interceſſion to God for them, and to hold forth Truth to them in ſound Doctrine, that they may be <hi>ſtrengthened</hi> with his glorious power in their Inward man; and that he may increaſe their Faith, and more and more fill them with that Wiſdom and Knowledge, which is pure and peaceable from above.</p>
               <p>But obſerve, where perſons have been <hi>long</hi> convinced, and are become <hi>Teachers</hi> of others, and by their ſo doing would be <hi>look'd</hi> upon to be Elders, wiſe and ſtrong, ſhall under the profeſſion of the Light <hi>oppoſe,</hi> and teach others to oppoſe the faithful Followers of Chriſt, in things which they practiſe in the Faith of Chriſt, accompanied with his Power and a good Underſtanding, <hi>This Caſe is greatly dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from</hi> the before-mentioned: For theſe will not grant, that their refuſing the practice of ſome things, and the oppoſing the Practiſers thereof, <hi>proceeds</hi> from <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or ſhort-ſightedneſs</hi> through their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy in the knowledge of the Truth; <hi>Much leſs</hi> that it proceeds from <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and Rebellion, the latter of which is true upon ſome in our Age; but theſe give out reviling Speeches againſt the Faithful, calling them Apoſtates, and many other evil names, which I here omit to mention,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:65439:64"/> having no pleaſure to repeat them.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, we are of the Apoſtles Faith and Judgment, who writ thus to the Church at <hi>Galatia; Brethren, if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſs, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted: Bear ye one anothers burthens, and ſo fulfil the Law of Chriſt.</hi> See <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1, 2. read the Chapter through. Chriſt, our Souls Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, hath taught us how to ſeek to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thoſe that commit Offences againſt him and his People; and ſeveral hath been ſo ſought, and recovered out of the Snare, in which they were taken; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>ſo</hi> ſought, have not been gained, but have perſiſted in their evil doing, until God has ceaſed any longer to ſtrive with them <hi>through</hi> his Servants, and then <hi>his Servants</hi> have witneſſed againſt them, and declared their diſunion with them, according to Chriſts command; and ſome ſuch being declared againſt, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, have appeared in great wrath againſt us, like the raging Waves of the Sea, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out their own ſhame; but we pity them, and ſhould greatly rejoyce on their behalf, if they could yet find a place of repentance and return: for 'tis true which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Joy ſhall be in heaven over one ſinner that repenteth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:65439:65"/>
               <p>Again, it is true which the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> writ, <hi>Brethren, if any of you do erre from the truth, and one convert him, let him know, that he which converteth the ſinner from the errour of his way, ſhall ſave a ſoul from death, and cover a multitude of ſins,</hi> Jam. 5. 19, 20.</p>
               <p>Again, to them that ſay, <hi>they do not ſee,</hi> as aforeſaid, hear what Chriſt ſaith by his Angel to the Church in <hi>Laodicea,</hi> viz. <hi>Becauſe thou ſayeſt, I am rich and increaſed in goods, and have need of nothing, <hi>and knoweſt not that thou art wretched and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked:</hi> I counſel thee to buy of me gold tryed in the fire, that thou mayeſt be rich, and white rayment that thou mayeſt be cloathed, and that the ſhame of thy <hi>nakedneſs do not appear; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint thine eyes with eye-ſalve,</hi> that thou mayeſt ſee: as many as I love, I rebuke &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten. Be zealous therefore and repent: behold I ſtand at the door and knock, <hi>If any man hear my voice, and open the door, I will come in to him,</hi> and will ſup with him, and he with me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith unto the Churches,</hi> Rev. 3. 14. to the end.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſerve, this Church or Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was gathered into the Profeſſion of Chriſt and his Light within.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:65439:65"/>2. <hi>Obſerve how greatly they were miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning their own ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> a moſt groſs and lamentable <hi>Errour were they in,</hi> as the before-cited words of Chriſt do plainly ſhew, <hi>They were puffed up with Self-conceit, that they wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> when in reality and truth, they <hi>Wanted all things,</hi> that ſhould have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them to be that which they profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be; Namely, ſuch who were Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the Head of His Church; who is the fulneſs; who Cloaths his Members with the Robes of his own Righteouſneſs, and fills them with the bright Beams of his Divine Light, ſo that they ſee clearly; and he fills their Hearts with the Riches of his Grace, in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of which, their Hearts and Souls pour forth Praiſes and Thankſgiving to the <hi>Lord <hi>God,</hi>
                  </hi> and the Lamb who is Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy for evermore.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Obſerve, Though their State was ſo miſerable; yet in his tender Mercy, he calls them to Repentance. Oh, conſider this, thou Back-ſlider, whoever thou art, and let the ſence thereof ſeize upon thee, and break thy Heart. Repent, and Turn to the Lord, with whom is forgiveneſs!</p>
               <p n="4">4. Obſerve, How <hi>Chriſt</hi> charges this Congregation to be blind, and being blind they could not ſee their State as it was;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:65439:66"/> but in their blind Self-conceit, ſaid, It was <hi>What it was not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Obſerve, That theſe blind Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited ones, while they remained ſuch, could not ſee that to be their Duty, which the Children of Light ſaw to be theirs.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Obſerve, That we do not here read, that theſe blind ſelf-conceited <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceans,</hi> did ſo oppoſe the Children of Light, in their Faithful Obedience to it; as ſome do oppoſe in our day we do not read they called them <hi>Apoſtates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Obſerve, That ſome blind Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited ones in our Age, have appeared worſe than they, who are not contented with that ungodly fleſhly Liberty, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Looſneſs in which they are; but therein do oppoſe, &amp; War againſt the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Light, becauſe they will not joyn and walk, and have Unity with them, in their dark Words &amp; Works: But in the Councel of <hi>God,</hi> Witneſs againſt the ſame.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Obſerve, If theſe blind Self-conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones do not take <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Councel, <hi>viz. <hi>Anoynt their Eyes</hi> with Eye-Salve, that they may ſee and repent;</hi> then their Latter End will be Miſerable, much worſe than their Beginning was. Oh, that ſuch might yet ſeek, and find a Place of Repentance! This would be matter of great rejoycing to the Children of Light, who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:65439:66"/> reviled, oppoſed, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed by them.</p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writ to the Saints in Light, <hi>viz. Giving all Diligence, Add to your Faith Vertue, and to Vertue Knowledge, and to Knowledge Temperance, and to Temperance Patience, and to Patience Godlineſs, and to Godlineſs brotherly Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Charity; for if theſe things be in you, and abound, they make you that you ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be barrennor unfruitful in the Knowledge of our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>but he that lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe Things is blind, and cannot ſee far off; and hath forgotten, that he was purged from his old Sins. Wherefore the rather, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, give <hi>All diligence to make your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election ſure; for if you do theſe things, ye ſhall never fall,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5. to the 11. Read the Chapter through.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſerve, All you that profeſs the Light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> within, what things you are to be found in, <hi>Which will render you,</hi> that you are not barren, nor unfruitful in the Knowledge of our Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſerve, That he that profeſſes to be plentiful in the Knowledge of our Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>And is not</hi>
                  </hi> found in the Poſſeſſion and Practice of thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned <hi>Chriſtian fruits, he is blind,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>and too like
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:65439:67"/> the ſelf-conceited</hi> blind <hi>Laodiceans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Obſerve, That there are ſome at this day, who do profeſs themſelves to be followers of the Light of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>Who do lack theſe</hi> before-mentioned good Things; and ſo, according to the Apoſtles ſaying, <hi>Theſe are blind,</hi> and the blind cannot ſee till their Eyes be opened; <hi>So they cannot ſee their Duty,</hi> nor the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Children of Light,</hi> till their Eyes <hi>be open'd.</hi> Such of them, who <hi>Have not yet ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out the Day of Gods Uiſitation,</hi> to them I <hi>Exhort and warn to retire,</hi> out of the Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceit, and vain Imaginations, to the pure Divine Light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> within, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto diligently attend, that thereby the Eyes of their Underſtandings may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed and opened, that therein they may ſee their Duty, and by vertue of the ſame, be led into it, and kept in it; and alſo may ſee the Duty of the Children of Light, and have Unity with them therein.</p>
               <p>Again, Hear what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith concerning Blindneſs, viz. <hi>But if our Goſpel be hid, <hi>It is hid in them that are loſt, in whom the God of this World hath blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the minds of them which believe not,</hi> leſt the Light of the Glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of</hi> God, <hi>ſhould ſhine unto them; for we Preach not our ſelves, but</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>the Lord, and our ſelves your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:65439:67"/> for</hi> Jeſus <hi>ſake; for</hi> God, <hi>who command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined in our hearts, to give the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of</hi> God, <hi>in the face of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>but we have this Treaſure in the Earthen Veſſels, that the Excellency of the Power, may be of</hi> God, <hi>and not of us,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 3. <hi>to</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſerve, That it is the <hi>God</hi> of the World, who blinds the Minds of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, deſigning thereby to hinder them of the Benefit of the Light; that ſo they might be kept blind, and in Blindneſs, <hi>Conceit themſelves</hi> to be wiſe and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Things of <hi>God,</hi> and Goſpel of his Kingdom, and in their Blindneſs to oppoſe and contend againſt thoſe, whom <hi>God</hi> hath made <hi>Wiſe unto Salvation,</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their Chriſtian Counſel, Advice, and Converſation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſerve, That the Apoſtles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not Preach Themſelves, but <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the Lord, and Themſelves their Servants for <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſake; and ſo doth the faithful Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in this day, praiſEd be the Lord for the ſame; and the Excellency of the <hi>Power</hi> by which they are enabled to ſerve <hi>God,</hi> and each other, is of <hi>God,</hi> and not of Themſelves. Therefore the Glory belongs to him forever.</p>
               <p>Again, Hear what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:65439:68"/> ſaith concerning the darkened and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, viz. <hi>For the Wrath of</hi> God <hi>is revealed from Heaven <hi>Againſt all Ungodlyneſs and Unrighteouſneſs of Men,</hi> who hold the Truth in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs; becauſe that which may be known of</hi> God, <hi>Is Manifeſt in them; <hi>for</hi>
                  </hi> God <hi>hath ſhewed it unto them,—<hi>Becauſe that when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were they thankful; but became vain in their Imaginations, and their fooliſh Heart was darkned; profeſſing themſelves to be Wiſe, they became Fools,</hi>
                  </hi> Rom. 1. 18, 19, to 23.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſerve, That the Wrath of <hi>God</hi> is revealed from Heaven, againſt all <hi>Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs</hi> and <hi>Unrighteouſneſs</hi> of Men, for holding the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs; <hi>That is,</hi> holding a Profeſſion of it <hi>Without Subjection and Obedience to it,</hi> becauſe they do not obey the Truth, in forſaking that which it ſhews them to be evil, &amp; chuſing &amp; doing that which it ſhews them to be good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſerve, That when they through their <hi>Negligence and Slothfulneſs, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and multiplied Diſobedience and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, are come to be darkned, and made Spiritually blind;</hi> ſo that they neither ſee, know, or deſire to <hi>Know their Duty, or to do it;</hi> yet this their Darkneſs and Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>doth not</hi> render them <hi>Excuſable,</hi> or uncondemnable either in the ſight of God,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:65439:68"/> or his Faithful People; but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Inexcuſable</hi> and condemnable in the ſight of God, and alſo in the ſight of his Faithful People..</p>
               <p n="3">3. Obſerve, The cauſe why they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo darkned and blinded was, that when they knew <hi>God,</hi> they glorified Him not as <hi>God,</hi> neither were thankful; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they became <hi>Vain in their Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and their fooliſh Hearts were dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; profeſſing themſelvee to be <hi>Wiſe,</hi> they became <hi>Fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Obſerve, What it is to <hi>Glorifie God</hi> as <hi>God,</hi> when Man knows Him; for there are ſeveral Degrees of the <hi>Knowledge of God,</hi> all proceeding from one Cauſe, and are of one kind, though <hi>Not all of One Quantity or Largeneſs.</hi> Certain it is, that to <hi>Glorifie God as God,</hi> is not only to believe that He is a Mighty, Powerful, Juſt, and Holy <hi>God;</hi> but alſo to <hi>Reverence, fear, and ſtand in awe of Him, and to obey Him,</hi> according to that Knowledge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of him. His Bleſſing is upon, &amp; will continue and increaſe upon all thoſe, who do ſo <hi>Glorifie Him;</hi> for <hi>He</hi> hath promiſed, who cannot lie, That he that is Faithful in a little, ſhall be made Ruler over much, and ſhall enter into the Joy of his Lord.</p>
               <p>Again, The ſame Apoſtle writ to the believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> viz. <hi>This I
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:65439:69"/> ſay therefore, and teſtifie in the Lord, That ye henceforth walk not as other</hi> Gentiles <hi>walk, in the Vanity of their Minds, having the <hi>Underſtanding darkened, being alienated from the Life of</hi>
                  </hi> God, <hi>through the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that is in them, becauſe of the Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Heart, who being paſt feeling, have given themſelves over to Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to work all Uncleanneſs with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 17, 18, 19.</p>
               <p>Obſerve here, the woful and miſerable Effects of Diſobedience to <hi>God;</hi> what Darkneſs, Spiritual Blindneſs, <hi>Benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medneſs,</hi> and Inſenſibility it brings them into, who are given up thereto, alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating them from the Life, Power, and Spirit of <hi>God;</hi> yet this Blindneſs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility, <hi>Doth not</hi> render them excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in the Sight of the Lord <hi>God,</hi> who hath ſent his Son, a true Light, who <hi>lights every Man that comes into the World;</hi> who therefore ſaith, <hi>Look unto Me all, O ye Ends of the Earth, and be ye ſaved; for I am</hi> God, <hi>and there is none elſe; a mighty</hi> God, <hi>and a Saviour,</hi> Iſa. 45. 22.</p>
               <p>And again, The Apoſtle in his Light, Spirit, and Power ſaw, and therefore ſaid, God's <hi>Will is, that all Men ſhould know the Truth, <hi>and he Saved,</hi> 1 Tim.</hi> 2. 4. They therefore who believe in the Divine Light of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and walk in and obey the ſame,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:65439:69"/> are therein ſaved, preſerved, and juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but they that know this Light, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and talk of it, <hi>but do not obey, and walk in it,</hi> they are juſtly by the Lord God condemned, and their Diſobedience juſtly <hi>Witneſſed againſt</hi> by his Faithful People, who walk in his Light, and bring forth the pure peaceable Fruits of it; and if ſuch diſobedient, unfaithful Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Light do not unfeignedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of their Evil Sayings and Doings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>People,</hi> and walk in Obedience to the Light they make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of; then will the Wrath of God fall heavy upon them in the End.</p>
               <p>Again, Hear what the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith to the Faithful Children of Light, viz. <hi>But ye are a choſen Generation, an holy Nation, a peculiar People, that ye ſhould ſhew forth the Praiſe of him, that hath called you <hi>Out of Darkneſs</hi> into his Marvellous Light. Dearly Beloved, I beſeech you, as Strangers and Pilgrims, <hi>Abſtain from Fleſhly Luſt, which War againſt the Soul,</hi> having your Converſations <hi>Honeſt</hi> amongſt the Gentiles; that whereas they ſpeak againſt you as Evil Doers, they may <hi>By your Good Works, which they ſhall behold,</hi> glorify</hi> God <hi>in the day of Viſitation.</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 9, to the 13.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, This Doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, is according to the Command of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:65439:70"/> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his Diſciples. He ſaid, <hi>Let your Light ſo ſhine before Men, that they may ſee your good Works, and Glorify your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven,</hi> Math. 5. 16.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Christ</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Light of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is the Eye, <hi>If therefore thine Eye be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, thy whole Body ſhall be full of Light; but if thine Eye be Evil, thy whole Body ſhall be full of Darkneſs;</hi> If therefore the Light that is in thee be Darkneſs, how great is that Darkneſs? See</hi> Math. 6. 22, 23.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Out of the <hi>Heart pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth an Evil Eye,</hi> Mark. 7. 22. Luke</hi> 11. 34.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſerve, That the Children of Light are a <hi>Royal Prieſthood, a Holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> a Peculiar People, called out of Darkneſs into Gods marvellous Light; They walking therein are as Lights in the World, their <hi>Light ſo ſhines before Men in the good Works,</hi> or good Converſation in <hi>Chriſt, this brings Glory to God the Father, which is in Heaven;</hi> they neither <hi>Need</hi> nor <hi>Do</hi> plead Ignorance, of their duty to <hi>God,</hi> or Man; or of the Commands of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> For they do both know, obey and do their Duty to <hi>God</hi> and Man, praiſed be the Lord <hi>God</hi> for the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſerve, That <hi>Christ</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Light of the Body, is the Eye; wherefore if thine Eye be ſingle, thy whole Body is full of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:65439:70"/> Light; but when thine Eye is Evil, thy whole body alſo is full of darkneſs. <hi>Here are 'two Eyes ſpoken of; the good one and the evil one,</hi>
                  </hi> he that hath the <hi>good Eye</hi> open in him, with it <note place="margin">Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If the blind lead the blind, both ſhall fall into the Ditch,</hi> Mat. 15. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>ſees right, ſees good things,</hi> and is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected therewith, embraceth and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth faſt the ſame; <hi>he ſees</hi> his duty to <hi>God</hi> and Man, and by <hi>Gods help</hi> doth the ſame, and therein is bleſſed; but he that hath the <hi>Evil Eye open in him</hi> (which Eye proceeds out of the Heart, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, with this his Evil Eye he ſeeketh and watcheth for Evil, and therewith ſees Evil things, and hath pleaſure in them, and therefore embraces them, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeth them, pleads for them, and holds them faſt. This is the Man, whoſe <hi>Good Eye</hi> is blinded, <hi>and his evil one open;</hi> therefore he calls <hi>Good Evil,</hi> and <hi>Evil Good.</hi> Here Darkneſs and its fruits, are put for Light and its fruits, and Light and its fruits, are put for Darkneſs and its fruits. The Perſon that doth this, hath <hi>changed the Truth</hi> of <hi>God for a Lie.</hi> Oh, this is a miſerable State, which ſome fell into in Ages paſt, and ſome are fallen into in our Age! Out of which, <hi>God</hi> Almighty preſerve all, who to his Light are turned, who believe in,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:65439:71"/> and love the ſame! And the Lord be merciful unto all, who, though they be Darkned and Intangled in the Snares of their Souls Enemy, through want of Watchfulneſs in the pure Light of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and holy fear of <hi>God;</hi> yet have not ſinned out the day of his tender Viſitation to them. Oh that they may ſeek and find a place of unfeigned Repentance, and ſo return unto the Lord <hi>God,</hi> before the <hi>Harveſt,</hi> or Gathering, or Reſtoring time, <hi>to them be ended.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the Honour which God gives unto his People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe fear of the Lord is the Inſtruction of Wiſdom, and before Honour is Humility,</hi> Proverbs 15. 33. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If any man <hi>honour</hi> me, him will my Father <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi>
                  </hi> John 12. 26. And the Apoſtle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> Exhorted the Saints, ſaying, <hi>Honour <hi>all men, love the Brotherhood,</hi> fear God,</hi> &amp;c. 1. Pet. 2. 17. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> Exhorted the believing Romans <hi>to be kindly Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onated one towards another with brotherly Love in <hi>Honour</hi> preferring one another,</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:65439:71"/> Rom. 12. 10. Again he writ to them, viz. <hi>But Glory, <hi>Honour,</hi> and Peace, to every man <hi>that worketh good,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. Rom. 2. 10. Again, hear what the Lord ſaith by the mouth of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet, <hi>viz. Them that <hi>honour</hi> me, I <hi>will honour,</hi> and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteem'd,</hi> 1 Sam. 2. 30. And again, <hi>Paul</hi> writing to <hi>Timothy</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let the Elders that Rule well be counted worthy of double <hi>honour,</hi> eſpecially they who labour in the Word and Doctrine,</hi> 1 Tim 5. 17.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, All the Children of God who are taught by his gracious Spirit of Life, Light, Love and Peace, who walk therein, they Glorifie and Honour him, with their Spirits and Bodies, which are his, and with his good Creatures, which he hath made them Stewards over, <hi>which is their reaſonable Service,</hi> and all ſuch he honours, with the honour that is <hi>from above,</hi> which comes from himſelf, and all theſe do honour each other, and prefer each other, according to the <hi>Order</hi> of the Work of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them in their ſeveral Gifts and Services in the Body of Chriſt, his Church; All keeping to, and walking in the Divine Light of Chriſt, all will be kept in <hi>Humility (and in Unity)</hi> yea
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:65439:72"/> cloathed with it according to the Apoſtles Exhortation, and according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Example of Chriſt the Chief Shepherd and Biſhop of our Souls, who ſaid, <hi>Learn of me, I am meek and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Heart, and ye ſhall find reſt to your Souls.</hi> A Remnant hath learned Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of him in this Age, and he hath given us reſt to our Souls, which to us far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels all the Riches and Glory of this World, Praiſes to the Lord God and the Lamb for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed are all they that walk in his Light, they find the fruit of it in them, to be unfeigned Love to Friends, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to Enemies, and Meekneſs, Patience, Gentleneſs, Juſtice, Equity, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs towards all Men, and a good Underſtanding, and holy right Zeal for the honour of the Lord, and the good of his People; who walks here <hi>will not be puffed up with ſelf conceit,</hi> or ſelf wilfulneſs, or be filled with Wrath, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Strife, nor ſtrive to Honour or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt themſelves, as Lords over Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſuch <hi>are not</hi> Lords over that Faith which God hath wrought in his People, but in the Love of God, Meekneſs and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of Chriſt Jeſus, theſe build up one another in their moſt Holy Faith, and are
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:65439:72"/> Fellow helpers of one anothers Joy in the Lord, as the Apoſtle hath writ and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted. And as the Primitive true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians practiſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Rule and Government in the Church of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>CHriſt Jeſus after he aroſe from the Dead ſpake unto his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>All power is given unto me in Heaven and in Earth, go ye therefore and teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Baptizing them into the Name</hi> (for ſo the Greek renders it) <hi>of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have comanded you, and lo I am with you always,</hi> &amp;c. Matt. 28. 18, 19, 20.</p>
               <p>Firſt Obſerve, Chriſt who was always ſpiritually preſent with thoſe whom he ſent to preach the Goſpel, gave them many things in Charge to teach the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to <hi>obſerve;</hi> thoſe who believed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and obeyed the Goſpel preach'd by the Apoſtles, <hi>did obey</hi> the Commands and Doctrines of Chriſt given by, or
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:65439:73"/> through the Apoſtles, who were his Embaſſadors, thoſe who did continue ſtedfaſt unto the end, were (<hi>by degrees</hi>) Taught and inabled by the powerful Spirit and Light of Chriſt <hi>in the Apoſtles and in their own hearts,</hi> to obſerve &amp; do all things that Chriſt commanded them.</p>
               <p>2. Obſerve, Chriſt in and by the Apoſtles did command and teach thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and received the Goſpel, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Light of it, and thoſe who did believe and obey thoſe Commands and Doctrines, were not (therein) ſubject or obedient to the Traditions, Doctrines, or Commandments of men (who were without the Spiritual Preſence and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Chriſt.) But they were obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent unto the Commandements and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Chriſt, delivered in and by the Faithful Apoſtles, thoſe holy Men of God.</p>
               <p>3. Obſerve, <hi>Here is Order and Rule</hi> in the Work of God, they that are No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices or young Scholars in the Faith and Doctrine of Chriſtianity, are Learners, others Elders or Teachers; theſe are to be <hi>Taught</hi> and watch'd over, by thoſe to whom God hath given an overſight of them in <hi>his power and wiſdom</hi> for the Salvation, Preſervation, and everlaſting good of their Souls; theſe Stewards of
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:65439:73"/> God, who labour for, and watch over Souls for the good end aforeſaid God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires them to be faithful in this great Charge which he hath laid upon them; for they muſt give an account to him of their ſtewardſhip, and bleſſed are all thoſe who have believed the Goſpel, who obey and walk in the Light of the ſame, receiving and obeying the Commands, Doctrines, and Precepts of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto them by his Light and Spirit in his Stewards and Embaſſadors, which they ſee and receive in the ſame Light &amp; Spirit of Chriſt in their own Hearts and Souls. An account will be given of them with joy, unto Chriſt the chief Shepherd and great Overſeer of Souls.</p>
               <p>4. Obſerve, They who after they have believed in the Spirit and Light of God, and Chriſt within, and have partaken of the vertue and power thereof, fall away when Temptations and Tryals come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them for Chriſt and the Goſpel's ſake; theſe become like the ſtony ground, which Chriſt ſpeaks of in the Parables of the Kingdom, that young and tender Blade, which appeared, in them being withered; an account cannot be given of theſe with joy, but with ſorrow, though they who have laboured faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:65439:74"/> with them for their good are clear of their Fall and Miſery.</p>
               <p>5. Obſerve, Thoſe who have come to a farther growth and knowledg of the Truth than thoſe laſt mentioned, who have come not only to know the Truth, but alſo further to obey it and ſuffer for it, yet they after they have thus done and ſuffered, have fallen away from their firſt love and obedience to the Croſs of Chriſt, by rejecting and ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Counſel of God by his Light and Spirit in their own hearts, and in the hearts and mouths of his Servants; and theſe having <hi>caſt off the Yoke of Chriſt,</hi> are become as Sons of <hi>Belial <hi>without Yoke;</hi>
                  </hi> gone into the World, into the <hi>Cumberſom Cares of it,</hi> and the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs</hi> of the Riches, Luſts, and Glory of it, <hi>ſuch has made ill uſe</hi> of the grace or favour of God given unto them, ſuch in their works (whatever their Words be) deny the only true God and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; ſuch are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of the Government of Chriſt in his Church, who though they <hi>retain</hi> yet ſomething of the Chriſtian form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, yet are out of the life and power thereof, and Enemies to it, <hi>as by their Evil Works and Words do and will appear.</hi>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:65439:74"/> The Stewards and Embaſſadors of Chriſt cannot give a joyous account of theſe, though having faithfully laboured with them for their preſervation and well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are therefore cleer of their blood, or of being in any wiſe guilty of their Fall and Ruin.</p>
               <p>Obſerve further what the Apoſtle ſaith concerning Rule and Government in the Church of Chriſt, he writing to the believing <hi>Hebrews,</hi> writes thus, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them which have the Rule over you, who hath ſpoken unto you the Word of God, whoſe Faith follow, conſidering the end of their Converſation, obey them that hath the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give an account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you:—Salute all them that have the Rule over you, and all the Saints; they of</hi> Italy <hi>ſalute you, Grace be with you all Amen.</hi> Heb. 13. 7, 17, 24, 25.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, Though the many ſorts of falſe Teachers have and do falſly pretend to watch for the Soul; who watch only for their own corrupt earthly Ends, as by their Fruits have and doth appear; yet God did of old and now doth ſend faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Labourers into his Vineyard, who
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:65439:75"/> have and do labour and watch for the Salvation of the Souls of the Sons and Daughters of Men, glory be given to him for the ſame: Theſe faithful Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are known by their Fruits, they covet no Mans Gold, Silver, or Apparel; they do not watch for Earthly gain; they do not take the overſight of the Flock for filthy Lucre, but of a ready mind; they are not Lords over Gods Heritage, but good Examples to the Flock; they are not Lords over the Faith of the People of God. But they are Fellow-helpers of their Joy, Peace, Comfort, and Eſtabliſhment in the way of Righteouſneſs. They Preach and give freely, according to Chriſts Command, they walk in Love to Friends and Enemies, witneſſing againſt that which is Evil, in all, without Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and without Hypocriſie, and the Fruits of Righteouſneſs is ſown by them in peace; they have peace with God, and live in Love and Peace one with another. They have learned of Chriſt Jeſus, true Humility, true Lowlineſs of Mind and Heart, in which they Preach in their good Example as well as Doctrine, to the honour of God and the good of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; they labour in the Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel, and in a good
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:65439:75"/> Converſation (in Chriſt) that he may be Exalted in all, both Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, to Rule in all, whoſe Right it is. Theſe do not ſeek their own glory, or exalt themſelves; but in humility they glorifie God with their Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which are his, and faithfully and unweariedly ſerve God and his People in patience, poſſeſſing their Souls in all their Tryals and Afflictions. Again <hi>Paul</hi> writ to <hi>Timothy,</hi> ſaying, <hi>An Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer or Biſhop</hi> in the Church of God, <hi>muſt not be an Novice</hi> (that is a young Scholar, one lately begotten to the Faith of Chriſt, or one that is Raw and unskilful in the word of Righteouſneſs) <hi>leſt being lifted up with pride, he falls into the Condemnation of the Devil;</hi> ſee 1 Tim. 3. 6. Again he writ to him, <hi>viz. Let the Elders that Rule well, be counted worthy of double honour, eſpecially they who labour in the Word and Doctrine,</hi> Chap. 5. v. 17. Again, he writ to the believing <hi>Romans,</hi> thus: viz. <hi>For I ſay through the Grace given unto me, to every man that is among you, <hi>not to think of himſelf more highly than he ought to think, but to think ſoberly,</hi> according as God hath de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t to every man the meaſure of Faith; for as we have many Members in one Body, and all Members
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:65439:76"/> have not the ſame Office, ſo we being many are one Body in Chriſt, and every one Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers one of another; having then Gifts <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,</hi> according to the Grace that is given to us, whether Propheſie, let us Propheſie according to the proportion of Faith, or <hi>Miniſtry</hi> let us wait on our Miniſtrying, or he that Teacheth on Teaching, or he that <hi>Exhorteth</hi> on Exhortation; he that giveth let him do it with <hi>Simplicity,</hi> he that <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth</hi> with diligence, he that ſheweth <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> with cheerfulneſs; let Love be <hi>without Diſſimulation, abhor</hi> that which is evil, <hi>cleave</hi> to that which is good, be kindly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionated one to another, with <hi>Brotherly love in</hi> Honour, preferring one another,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 12. 3. to 11.</p>
               <p>My Friends, all you that Profeſs to be Members of the Church of Chriſt, and taught by his Spirit and Light within you; by what is here written (given forth by the Apoſtle as he was moved by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt) you may underſtand that there is a Rule and Government in the Church of God, in his Power, Wiſdom and Strength, for his Glory, who is the Head of it: And you may alſo underſtand hereby, that Chriſt the Head, hath given Gifts differing by the ſame Spirit, for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, Edification, and well Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:65439:76"/> and Governing his Church, and every one is to attend on his Gift in the Church, and to improve the ſame, which being done, is to the Increaſe of the Body, for the Edification of it in Love: Moreover by what is before writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, you may underſtand that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle through the Grace of God given to him, did warn every Man amongſt the believing <hi>Romans,</hi> not to think of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more highly than he ought to think, but to think ſoberly according as God had dealt to every man the meaſure of Faith.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, If every one which profeſs the Light and Spirit of Chriſt within to be their Guide and Teacher, did obey and walk in it, it would teach them all not to think too highly of themſelves, or of their States and Conditions in the Truth (which ſome do) and if ſuch of the aforeſaid Profeſſors were ſo Taught, then would they not think nor ſpeak ſo highly of themſelves or of their Sights, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and Growth in the Truth as they do (far beyond what they really are) then would they not be ſo puffed up, ſelf-conceited and unruly as they are; then would they live quietly, peaceably, and harmleſly among the People of God
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:65439:77"/> to his Glory, and the Comfort of his People, and their own peace and reſt, which ſome do not, but are contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, unruly and diſorderly, ſelf conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, fretful, and clamorous with Tongues and Pens. Oh that they could ſeek and find a place of unfeigned Repentance, it would much rejoyce my Soul to ſee it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the Living Faith, with its fruits and works.</head>
               <p>COncerning Faith, the Apoſtle thus writ (viz.) <hi>Now the juſt ſhall live by Faith; but if any Man draw back, my Soul ſhall have no pleaſure in him</hi> (ſaith the Lord God) <hi>but we are not of them who draw back unto perdition, but of them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to the ſaving of the Soul.—By Faith the Elders obtained a good report.—Through Faith we underſtand the World was framed by the Word of God—By Faith</hi> Abel <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto God a more excellent Sacrifice than</hi> Cain.—<hi>By Faith</hi> Enoch <hi>was Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death;—but without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:65439:77"/> for he that cometh to God, muſt believe that he is, and that he is a Rewarder of all them that diligently ſeek him. By Faith</hi> Noah <hi>was warned of God of things not ſeen as yet, moved with fear prepared an Ark.—By Faith</hi> Abraham <hi>when he was tried offered up</hi> Iſaac.—<hi>By Faith</hi> Moſes <hi>when he was come to years, refuſed to be called the Son of</hi> Pharaohs <hi>Daughter, chuſing rather to ſuffer Affliction with the People of God, than to enjoy the pleaſure of ſin for a ſeaſon, eſteeming the Reproaches of Chriſt greater Riches than the Treaſures in</hi> Egypt; <hi>for he had reſpect unto the Recompence of Reward; by Faith he kept the Paſſover,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I may ſay with this faithful Author, <hi>What ſhall I more ſay? for the time would fail me to tell of</hi> Gideon, <hi>and of</hi> Baruck, <hi>and of</hi> Sampſon, <hi>of</hi> Jephtha, <hi>and of</hi> David <hi>alſo, and of</hi> Samuel, <hi>and of the Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 38, 39. Read the 11 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter through: <hi>Habbakkuk 2. 4. Rom.</hi> 1. 17.</p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writ to the Saints concerning Faith, <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z. Who are kept by the power of God through Faith unto Salvation,</hi> ſee 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5. Again, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let us hold faſt the Profeſſion of our Faith, without wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> Heb. 10. 23. Now the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:65439:78"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:65439:78"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:65439:79"/> who writ of this Faith, writ alſo of the works and fruits of it (which the reſt alſo did) hear what he ſaith in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>viz. What doth it pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fit, my Brethren, though a Man ſay he hath Faith? can Faith ſave him? If a Brother or Siſter be naked and deſtitute of dayly Food, and one of you ſay unto them, Depart in peace, be you warmed and filled; notwithſtanding ye give them not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe things which are needful to the Body; what doth it profit? Even ſo Faith, if it hath not works is dead being alone,</hi> yea <hi>a man may ſay, Thou haſt Faith, and I have works, ſhew me thy Faith without thy works, and I will ſhew thee my Fath by my works. Thou believeſt there is one God,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>But wilt thou know, oh vain man, that Faith without works is dead. Was not</hi> Abraham <hi>our Father juſtified by Works.—ſeeſt thou how Faith wrought with his Works and by works was Faith made perfect, and the Scripture was fulfilled which ſaith</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>believed God, and was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs, and he was called the friend of God; ye ſee then how that by <hi>works</hi> a Man is juſtified and not by Faith <hi>only</hi>—for as the <hi>Body</hi> without the Spirit is <hi>dead,</hi> ſo Faith without Works <hi>is dead alſo,</hi>
                  </hi> James 2. 14 to the end.</p>
               <p>Again the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> writ to the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:65439:79"/> Children of Light concerning this Faith <hi>viz. For whatſoever is born of God, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the World, and this is the Victory that overcometh the World, even our Faith,</hi> 1 John 5. 4. Again <hi>Peter</hi> Exhorts thoſe who were come to ſome degree of this Faith, ſaying, <hi>Give all diligence; add to your Faith Vertue, and to Vertue Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and to Knowledg Temperance, and to Temperance Patience, and to Patience Godlineſs, and to Godlineſs Brotherly Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to Brotherly Kindneſs, Charity; for if theſe things be in you and abound, they make you that you ſhall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the Knowledg of our Lord Jeſus Christ; but he that la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>keth theſe things, is blind,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wherefore the rather, Brethren, give <hi>diligence to make your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election ſure;</hi> for if you do theſe things, you ſhall <hi>never fall,</hi>
                  </hi> 2 Pet. 1. 4, 11.</p>
               <p>Again, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the believing <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> ſaid unto them, <hi>We are bound to thank God always for you, Brethren, as it is meet, becauſe that your Faith groweth exceedingly, and the Charity of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of you all towards each other abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1. 3.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Paul</hi> writ to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> viz. <hi>Knowing that a Man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the Faith of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:65439:80"/> Jeſus Chriſt; even we have believed in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the Faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the Law; for by the works of the Law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified; <hi>but if while we ſeek to be juſtified by Chriſt, we our ſelves are found ſinners; is Chriſt therefore the Miniſter of ſin? God forbid;</hi> for if I build again the things which I deſtroyed, I make my ſelf a Tranſgreſſor; for I through the Law am dead to the Law, that I might live unto God; <hi>I am Crucified with Chriſt, nevertheleſs I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me; and the life which I now live in the fleſh; I live by the Faith of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on of God,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</p>
               <p>Again, he writ thus to the believing <hi>Epheſians,</hi> viz. <hi>We are <hi>Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>kman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> Created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good Works, which God hath before ordained we ſhould walk in them,</hi> Epheſians 2. 10.</p>
               <p>The ſame Apoſtle writing to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Philipians,</hi> writ thus, <hi>viz. For it is God which <hi>worketh in you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>th to will and to do,</hi> of his own good pleaſure; do all things without murmuring and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that you may be <hi>blameleſs and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Sons of God; without rebuke,</hi> in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:65439:80"/> among whom <hi>ye ſhine</hi> as Lights in the World,</hi> Philip. 2. 13, 14, 15.</p>
               <p>Again, he writ to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> thus <hi>(viz.) Unto him that is able to do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think, according to the power that worketh in us, unto him be Glory, in the Church throughout all Ages, world without end,</hi> Amen. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 20, 21.</p>
               <p>Again, the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> writing to them, ſaith, <hi>viz. Now the God of Peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant, <hi>make you perfect in every good work to do his will; working in you that which is well-pleaſing</hi> in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory for; ever and ever; Amen.</hi> Heb. 13. 20, 21.</p>
               <p>O all you who profeſs your ſelves to be Chriſtians, and to be led and guided by the Spirit and Light of Chriſt within; ſeriouſly conſider of the faithful ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of theſe faithful Apoſtles and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt, concerning Faith in God, and Chriſt, and the Goſpel, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian works, which God in Chriſt works in all thoſe who comes to the <hi>Baptized by Chriſt with the Holy Ghoſt and Fire,</hi> which burns up the works of Satan, to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:65439:81"/> with, Sin, who deſtroys the old man with his deeds, which are corrupt, and which renews and reſtores man again into the likneſs or image of God who created him. All who come to drink into the one Spirit, and be Baptized by it into the <hi>one Body,</hi> come thereby to be made of <hi>one Heart</hi> and Soul, and to Worſhip and Serve God with <hi>one conſent;</hi> theſe have not Faith without Works, which is dead; but they have the living Faith which God hath wrought in them, which by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is called the Faith of the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Work of God, and with this <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith</hi> they have the <hi>living Works</hi> and Fruits, which Faith and Works, <hi>prove them to be the generation and living off-ſpring of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further obſerve, How ſweetly all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned Apoſtles in their ſayings, are in <hi>Harmony and Unity,</hi> concerning this living Faith and its living Works or Fruits.</p>
               <p>Again obſerve, Where <hi>many Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Faith and Chriſtianity have been groſly miſtaken</hi> concerning Faith and Works. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in ſome of his Epiſtles, writing much againſt the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of the <hi>ſhadowy works</hi> of the Law, after Chriſt had ended them by his
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:65439:81"/> one offering, many Profeſſors of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity of latter times have been <hi>willing to exclude all works,</hi> as with reſpect to Salvation or Acceptance with God, under the Goſpel diſpenſation; though the holy Apoſtle Exhorted the Believers in Chriſt, to work out their Salvation with fear and trembling, ſaying, It is God that worketh in you to will and to do of his own good pleaſure. Now the Words which I have here brought out of <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, with much more of the like nature that may be found in them (which for brevity I here omit) doth and will plainly ſhew that he did <hi>never intend</hi> in his writing againſt the ſhadowy works of the Law, <hi>to exclude, deny, or make void the ſubſtantial,</hi> good and living Works of God in Chriſt, in his People, under the Goſpel diſpenſation; ſo that he was of the ſame mind concerning Faith and Works with <hi>James, Peter</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> ſo here are four faithful and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Witneſſes linked together, in Teſtimony to the living Faith which God works in his People, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Works and Fruits which accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, Glory to the Lord God for the ſame: and thoſe Four faithful Witneſſes to the living Faith, its Fruits and Works
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:65439:82"/> as aforeſaid, are alſo faithful Witneſſes againſt the dead Faith and dead Works of the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity in our Age, who notwithſtanding their high Notions and talk of Faith, Election, Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Salvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are yet dead in their Treſpaſſes and in their Sins. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>John</hi> writ to the Saints, ſaying, <hi>This is the Victory over the World, even your Faith.</hi> And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If you have Faith as a grain of Muſtard Seed, <hi>if you ſhall ſay unto this Mountain be thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and to this Hill be thou caſt into the Sea, they ſhall obey you.</hi>
                  </hi>—But they that are yet (dead) in their Treſpaſſes and Sins, pleading they muſt continue <hi>therein all</hi> their days upon Earth. <hi>Their dead Faith hath not given them Victory over the World, neither can it;</hi> for as they are taught by the <hi>Serpent</hi> to believe, that they muſt live in ſin all their days, according to this <hi>ungodly belief,</hi> they ſubmit themſelves to him, and he leads them into ſin, and they multiply their ſin daily, as they ſay; and ſuch <hi>are not in the ſtrait and narrow way</hi> they talk of, but in the broad way, that leads to deſtruction. Oh! that they would turn in their minds to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, and believe in it, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:65439:82"/> ſeek a place of Repentance; that they might find it, and ſo return to God from Satan and their Sins, which while they abide in ſubjection to, holds them in a <hi>Separation from God,</hi> from peace and reſt with him, and from Unity with his choſen; whatſoever they do or may imagine or ſay to the contrary, they will find this true at laſt.</p>
               <p>Again, theſe in their <hi>dead Faith</hi> and works of Sin <hi>have not known Gods</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous and <hi>miraculous</hi> works yet wrought in them, to throw down the Hills and Mountains of Sin and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which the Devil, who abode not in the Truth, in whom there is no Truth, hath <hi>raiſed up in them,</hi> to wit, Pride, ſelf-Exaltation, vain, freſhly, earthly Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>All that's in the World, <hi>the luſt of the fleſh, and the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father,</hi> but is of this World, and this World paſſeth away, and the Luſts thereof; but he that doth the Will of God abideth for ever; except a man be regenerate and born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God, <hi>and the blind who doth never ſee it, is never like to inherit it.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>all you who do not only</hi> profeſs
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:65439:83"/> Chriſt as the before-mentioned Profeſſors do, <hi>but alſo</hi> profeſs his Spirit and Light within to be your Teacher (<hi>which they do not</hi>) who profeſs according to <hi>John</hi> Baptiſts Teſtimony, and the Teſtimony of <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet, that Chriſt the Lamb of God, is the ſent One of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and is come to take <hi>away the ſins of the World,</hi> to put an end to <hi>ſin, to finiſh tranſgreſſion, to bring in everlaſting Righteouſneſs; <hi>all be retired in the ſpirit of your Minds,</hi>
                  </hi> to the Divine Light of Chriſt Jeſus, wherewith you are lighted, and therein wait to <hi>receive and keep a right ſenſe</hi> of your Conditions; ſee how you have taken up your Croſs, and how you bear it, and what the fruits and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of your bearing of it are; ſee that the hills and mountains <hi>of ſin</hi> be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned <hi>in you,</hi> and the rough places made ſmooth <hi>in you,</hi> and the Valley exalted in you; for who have not known theſe <hi>wonderful</hi> works of God, wrought in them, they are yet <hi>ſhort of the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or ſitting down in the Inheritance of the Kingdom of God and of his Chriſt, which conſiſts or ſtands in Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> for through the Righteous <hi>and Fiery</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God <hi>inwardly</hi> muſt <hi>ſinful Man</hi>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:65439:83"/> come, before he can draw neer to God, ſee his Kingdom, or have a place in it; <hi>this fiery Baptiſm</hi> they muſt come through wherewith Chriſt Jeſus the power and wiſdom of God <hi>Baptizeth all</hi> who believe in him, and in his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light patiently and conſtantly wait to be made new Creatures by him. It is true what the Apoſtle hath writ, <hi>If any Man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature, <hi>old things are done away, and all things are become new, and all things are</hi>
                  </hi> of God; for as he alſo ſaith, <hi>They that are Chriſts, have Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified the fleſh with the Affections and Luſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again obſerve, That if any perſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing to be led and guided by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light of Chriſt within, and that he or ſhe believes the before-mentioned Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies concerning Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That he is come to put an end to ſin, and bring in everlaſting Righteouſneſs, to enable his People to perfect Holineſs in his Fear, according to what God hath promiſed, and his Servants have writ and ſpoken, <hi>if ſuch perſon or perſons</hi> ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, continue in a <hi>looſe and ſinful Converſation,</hi> whether they be called <hi>Quakers,</hi> or by what other name ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:65439:84"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:65439:84"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:65439:85"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:65439:85"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:65439:86"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:65439:86"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:65439:87"/> their Sin is <hi>not leſs but much more grievous</hi> to Almighty God, than the ſins of the before-mentioned, who have not yet come to be <hi>opened ſo far</hi> as to underſtand what the Light of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is: Therefore do not make profeſſion to be taught and guided by it: but thoſe looſe and ſinful Profeſſors of the Light of Chriſt within, <hi>if they did ever</hi> really come to the Light they make profeſſion of, and in any meaſure obey it, then were their hearts opened thereby to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and know ſin, and the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God againſt it <hi>more</hi> than the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned; and ſo the Judgment of God will fall more heavy on them (if they repent not, and come not to walk orderly, as becomes the Goſpel) than upon others who have not known ſo much as they have known, and therefore are not guilty of the ſin of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, ſo much as they are; for <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion is as the ſin of Witcheraft,</hi> as 'tis writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: <hi>And he that knows his Maſters will, and doth it not, he ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes,</hi> as 'tis alſo written.</p>
               <p>Again obſerve, ſuch looſe Profeſſors of the Light of Chriſt within, may boaſt and talk of their Faith in God, and Chriſt, and the Divine Light within, of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:65439:87"/> without Sin, of Perfection, or of perfecting Holineſs in Gods Fear, yet being out of the Light and Life of Chriſt in Death and Darkneſs, and the Works and Fruits thereof, <hi>It is but Death and Darkneſs in them, which talks of Light, and Life, and Faith, Holineſs, Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> &amp;c. Their talk of theſe good things with their Mouths, is an Abomination to God Almighty, while their hearts are far away from him, while they are not in the Love and Obedience to God and Chriſt, and his Divine Light they make profeſſion of; ſuch profeſſion without Subjection and Obedience, God doth reject, it is loathſome to him, neither can his tender people whom he hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by his Spirit of Judgment and Burning, have unity with theſe <hi>dead talkers, nor their dead words and works for Light</hi> hath no communion with Darkneſs, though Darkneſs talk of Light.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Something concerning Self Separation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DE</hi> the Servant of Chriſt writ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Self-Separated ones, thus, <hi>viz.</hi> they are the <hi>RAging Waves of the Sea, foaming out their own ſhame, to whom
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:65439:88"/> is reſerved the miſt of Darkneſs for ever,</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> alſo the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of thoſe, ſaying, <hi>Behold the Lord c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>meth in Ten thouſands of his Saints</hi> (mark ſo it is rendred from the Greek, and is ſo in ſome Engliſh Tranſlations) <hi>to execute Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly amongſt them, of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodlily committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlily they have ſpoken againſt him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>theſe be they who ſeparate themſelves, <hi>ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, having not the Spirit.</hi>—But ye, Beloved, building up your ſelves in your moſt holy Faith, <hi>praying in the Holy Ghoſt, keep your ſelves in the Love of God,</hi> looking for the Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto Eternal Life, <hi>and of ſome have compaſſion, making a difference, and</hi> others ſave with fear, hating even the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpotted by the Fleſh. Now unto him that is able to keep you from falling, before the preſence of his Glory, with exceeding Joy, to the only wiſe God our Saviour, be Glory and Majeſty, Dominion and Power, now and ever, Amen.</hi> Jude 13 and 19 to the end, ſee alſo 1 <hi>Tim. 4. 1. 2 Tim. 3. 1. 2 Pet</hi> 3. 3.</p>
               <p>Oh my dear Friends, ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that as in the Primitive Goſpel days, there were ſuch <hi>Self-ſeparated ones,</hi>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:65439:88"/> makers of Sects or Parties, which cauſed great grief and deep Exerciſe to the Faithful in Chriſt Jeſus; ſome ſuch like have been in our Age, and ſome ſuch like yet are, who having been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the Truth, have come amongſt us under the Chriſtian Profeſſion of the Spirit and Light of Chriſt within, <hi>who for ſome time did in ſome meaſure follow and obey the Teachings of it,</hi> but have ſince turned from it, yet keep in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it; theſe are they who ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelves <hi>without it, <hi>in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to it, and the Children of it,</hi> bleſſed be God that their number is but ſmall; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! they are too many, for we have received the mind of God, and Chriſt (and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) whoſe will was, and is, that all Men might know the Truth, and not only know it, but obey it, that ſo they might be ſaved; but alas! <hi>a few reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> ſpirited Inſtruments of Satan, who under the pretence of the Spirit and Light of Chriſt, make War againſt the God of Peace, againſt Chriſt the Prince of Peace, and againſt the Subjects of his Peaceable Kingdom; theſe are in <hi>danger to deceive</hi> others, and bring them to be <hi>reſtleſs</hi> like themſelves; the Lord in Mercy ſtop theſe evil Works and Workers.
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:65439:89"/> Oh that there might be a place of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance yet found by them! Oh that they could yet ſee from whence they are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and Repent, and come into that ſimplicity and loving and peaceable frame of mind, into which the Truth had once in ſome meaſure drawn them Oh! this would be matter of great joy to thoſe whom they in their darkneſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count their Enemies; as ſome <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>loting dark Notioniſts</hi> did the faithful Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> for his faithful and ſtedfaſt Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt their <hi>Looſeneſs, Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Diſorder.</hi> It is my ſtedfaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in God, that he will not long ſuffer this Evil Work to go on to the grief of his People, and the indangering the loſs of Souls, but he will plead with theſe Evil Workers, theſe Serpentine wiſe and ſelf-conceited, he will ſtop and drive them backward, and woe will be to them if they cannot find a place of Repentance, which will be hard for ſome of them to find; they have ſo highly magnified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt God, his Tabernacle, and them that dwell in Heaven; but as <hi>Jude</hi> the Servant of Chriſt, well obſerved in his Epiſtle, that there was a difference to be put betwixt them who were ſo gone out into diſorder, looſneſs, or confuſion in
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:65439:89"/> his time; ſome no doubt of thoſe, were <hi>unwarily,</hi> through the ſubtilty of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans Agents, drawn from the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, honeſt mindedneſs, and good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which the Spirit of Truth had wrought in them, <hi>into ungodly Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies and a wrong liberty from their obedience to the Croſs of Chriſt. <hi>Jude</hi>
                  </hi> ſaw there was a <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to ſuch, and therefore <hi>wiſely</hi> in the Wiſdom of God put the Churches <hi>in mind of it,</hi> and we are ſenſible ſuch there hath been in our day, who hath been <hi>betrayed</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon by Satan and his Agents, as aforeſaid; theſe have been ſought in the Love of God and Bowels of Jeſus Chriſt, their Advocate with the Father, travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for them in his Faithful ones, who hath kept their Habitation in God, and we have ſeen the travels and deſires of our Souls anſwered, in their returning into Unity with God and his People, through their unfeigned <hi>Repentance and Condemnation</hi> upon the Spirit of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (which led them from God) and upon the evil Words and Works it led them into, and we believe that there are divers that yet remain in the ſame Snare, for whoſe return to God we travelin Spir it, and Hope that we ſhall ſee the Fruit of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:65439:90"/> the Travel of our Souls in the Love and Power of God, for their good, and ſhall have cauſe to rejoyce and praiſe God for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, oh my dear and well beloved Friends, who are exerciſed by theſe ſorts of Evil Agents, and their Evil Works, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſpacious profeſſion of the Light, Grace, and Spirit of Chriſt, and the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of it, <hi>All keep in the love of God, and in the patience of Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>let Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence have its perfect work in thoſe your</hi> deep Tribulations and ſorrowful Exerciſes: fret not becauſe of evil Men, nor their evil Works, for behold the Judg of Heaven and Earth, he ſees them and you; he will not ſuffer you to be tryed by them above what he will give you Ability to travel through without hurt, and fear, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loſs or diſadvantage to your Eternal Eſtates, if you diligently wait upon him, and move, ſpeak, and act in his Council.</hi> It is true which was anciently written by an Experienced Man of God, Tribulation worketh Patience, and Patience Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Experience Hope, and the living Hope is as an Anchor which is ſure and ſtedfaſt; <hi>ſo keep this living Hope, that none of you may faint in'this or any other Exerciſe which you undergo for Chriſts
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:65439:90"/> and the Goſpels</hi> ſake, but all wait diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly upon the living God, who daily renew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſtrength of his People, ſo that they can truly ſay, <hi>Sufficient is the day to the Evil thereof;</hi> and can truly ſay, <hi>The Lord is our Rock and our Salvation, and we cannot fear what man can do unto us,</hi> he is an Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting <hi>Sun</hi> unto us, who gives us his Light to walk in, in which there is no occaſion of ſtumbling; which Light ſhines in the Diligent, Watchful, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ones more and more, unto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day, our God is a <hi>Shield</hi> unto his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to defend them <hi>againſt the Arrows</hi> of the Deſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er; he <hi>Arms</hi> his Lambs and Children with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight and Power, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Fiery Darts</hi> of Satan are <hi>quenched.</hi> Eternal Glory to his honourable and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Name, for evermore, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh my dear Friends, keep cloſe to the powerful Spirit of Truth in all your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, and particularly when you are Exerciſed with this ſort of Evil Agents; keep cloſe to the power of God, that in that you may feel that you have the command of your own Spirits, that no wrong or unnatural heats, ſharpneſs or falſe fire may be kindled by you or any of you, but that your Minds and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits may be kept ſteady and cool in the Lambs patience;</hi> for that will lead to
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:65439:91"/> run the race to the end, and will give the Victory: take heed and <hi>keep out of too many words, with reſtleſs diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented perſons,</hi> under the Profeſſion of the Truth, whoſe evil life and ſtrength ſtands in multiplying words, wilfully ſtriving for Victory or Maſtery in a fretful, lofty, and impatient frame of mind; and alſo <hi>beware</hi> of ſuch who are ſmooth and ſubtle in their contending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Truth and its Children, leſt any of you be drawn out thereby to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of Truth, hurting of your own Souls, and ſtrengthening the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous in their way; but all be ſteady in your Teſtimony, againſt deceit in all things: and all Friends Male and Female, keep your Meetings in the Light and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, and in them ſerve God and each other faithfully; be tender and wiſe in your carriage one towards another, at all times, particularly in your Meetings; hear one another tenderly, in a right frame of mind and in good order; and if weakneſs appear in thoſe who intend well in their ſpeaking about Truths concerns in your Meetings, or that weakly manage any thing of Truths concerns, either in your Meetings or at other times, let them be tenderly ſpoken to in the Order of Truth, at ſeaſonable times, that ſuch may
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:65439:91"/> be helped, and Peace and Unity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and all that avoided that tends to bring forth contrary Effects; and cheriſh and encourage one another in your ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Service, that ye may be mutually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed together therein, and that your precious unity and fellowſhip may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved without breach, and grow and flouriſh more and more, that the fruits of Righteouſneſs may be more and more plentifully ſown and reaped amongſt you, to the Glory and Praiſe of the great God, whoſe building and husbandry you are; and living Branches in Chriſt the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vine, bringing for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h more and more Fruit in him, to the Glory of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who is worthy of Glory over all Heaven and Earth for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And my dear Friends, be very careful that none of you go into too many words in Diſpute or Argument for, or in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or Commendation of thoſe good things which God hath led you into (in which you are oppoſed by ſome who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Light of Chriſt within to be their Guide and Teacher, and by them reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and derided for your obedience to God therein:) but let thoſe good things ſpeak forth their own worth and praiſe, in their good Fruits and Effects in and by you, to the Glory of God, and to your
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:65439:92"/> Profit, Comfort and Juſtification; and to the cutting off occaſion from thoſe who watch for, and ſeek occaſion againſt you. And to the Convincement of ſuch Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, who have not ſinned out the day of Gods tender Viſitation to them; and for the ſtaying, preſerving, and effectually convincing ſuch who are not clear in their underſtandings concerning thoſe things, but are in ſome degree hurt and darkned by the Evil Example, Words, and Actions, of ſome Evil Agents, whom Satan hath made Inſtruments of Evil to them; yet do they not wilfully, ſcornfully, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly oppoſe, or ſtrive againſt Friends in thoſe good things God hath led them into; but being ſhort in their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and wrong, jealouſies and doubts having entred them, they do not freely joyn with Friends in ſome things which God hath led them into, wherein he is honoured and his People profitted.</p>
               <p>Oh my dear Friends, he who wins Souls to God, is wiſe in the Wiſdom of God, which is Pure and Peaceable. God Almighty inrich his People every where more &amp; more with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Heavenly Wiſdom, that in it they may ſerve him and each other in unfeigned Love, that therein their Peace and Unity may remain and increaſe daily more and more to his Eternal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and our everlaſting profit and comfort; even ſo <hi>Amen,</hi> ſaith my Soul.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:65439:92"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
